<article xmlns="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Non Linear Mech</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>International Journal of Non-Linear Mechanics</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0020-7462</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1878-5638</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Pergamon Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3268561</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22298913</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">NLM1866</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijnonlinmec.2011.04.030</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Axisymmetric indentation of curved elastic membranes by a convex rigid indenter</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Pearce</surname>
            <given-names>S.P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>simon.pearce@nottingham.ac.uk</email>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
          <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>King</surname>
            <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>etzjrk@maths.nottingham.ac.uk</email>
          <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
          <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Holdsworth</surname>
            <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>michael.holdsworth@nottingham.ac.uk</email>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Plant and Crop Sciences, School of Biosciences, University of Nottingham, Nottingham, LE12 5RD, UK</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>School of Mathematical Sciences, University of Nottingham, Nottingham, NG7 2RD, UK</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Centre for Plant Integrative Biology, School of Biosciences, University of Nottingham, LE12 5RD, UK</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. <email>simon.pearce@nottingham.ac.uk</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>46</volume>
      <issue>9</issue>
      <fpage>1128</fpage>
      <lpage>1138</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>3</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2011 Elsevier Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/authorsview.authors/supplementalterms1.0">certain conditions</ext-link>.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Motivated by applications to seed germination, we consider the transverse deflection that results from the axisymmetric indentation of an elastic membrane by a rigid body. The elastic membrane is fixed around its boundary, with or without an initial pre-stretch, and may be initially curved prior to indentation. General indenter shapes are considered, and the load–indentation curves that result for a range of spheroidal tips are obtained for both flat and curved membranes. Wrinkling may occur when the membrane is initially curved, and a relaxed strain-energy function is used to calculate the deformed profile in this case. Applications to experiments designed to measure the mechanical properties of seed endosperms are discussed.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract abstract-type="graphical">
        <title>Highlights</title>
        <p>► Axisymmetric indentation of elastic membranes. ► General axisymmetric indenter profiles considered. ► Initially curved elastic membranes, not just flat membranes. ► Strain-energy function important for large deformations.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Indentation</kwd>
        <kwd>Hyperelastic</kwd>
        <kwd>Membrane</kwd>
        <kwd>Deformation</kwd>
        <kwd>Endosperm</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>An elastic shell may be defined as a three-dimensional elastic body with one dimension that is much thinner than the other two <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. This enables us to consider the deformation of only the mid-plane of the elastic body in this thinner direction. A membrane may then be defined as a shell which has negligible resistance to bending <xref rid="bib18 bib12" ref-type="bibr">[18,12]</xref>. Elastic membranes are commonly found in biological and engineering contexts, where they may span relatively large areas despite having little volume or weight <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>.</p>
      <p>There are two different classes of non-linear elastic membrane theories and we refer to Haughton <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> for a more complete comparison of the two theories, but give a brief description here. The first of these membrane theories may be called a ‘membrane-like shell’ <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, which takes the shell theory of three-dimensional elasticity and introduces the membrane assumption of no stress in the direction normal to the membrane. In this formulation the thickness is included in the derivation, as the principal stretch in the thickness direction, <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si0026.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, appears in the governing equations, which explicitly allows the membrane to get thinner to conserve mass when the constraint of incompressibility is imposed. This is a common method of treating membranes, and a comprehensive derivation may be found in Libai and Simmonds <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> and Steigmann <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. A variational treatment may also be considered, for example see Le Dret and Raoult <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The second class of membrane theories occurs from considering the mid-plane of the membrane as a two-dimensional sheet of elastic material embedded in three-dimensional space, entirely neglecting thickness effects through the membrane <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Nadler and Rubin <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref> call this a ‘simple membrane’, and a consequence of this reduction is that the stretch through the membrane is not included in the formulation. The deformation gradient is then two-dimensional, and there are only two strain invariants and two principal stretches, rather than the three that arise in the three-dimensional theory, see Steigmann <xref rid="bib36 bib39" ref-type="bibr">[36,39]</xref> for details.</p>
      <p>It has been shown that the simple membrane and membrane-like shell approaches give the same governing equations to leading order <xref rid="bib26 bib7 bib38" ref-type="bibr">[26,7,38]</xref>, and it is the specification of the constitutive behaviour which varies between the two theories. It is possible to define two-dimensional strain-energy functions which have no counterpart in the three-dimensional theory, as discussed by Haughton <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, as well as to use three-dimensional strain-energy functions in the two-dimensional theory. Further details of such matters may be found in Libai and Simmonds <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> and Steigmann <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>.</p>
      <p>When considering membrane deformations using either of the above theories, it is important to ensure that the membrane is in a state of tension, with both principal stresses remaining positive throughout the deformation <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. If compressive (negative) stresses occur then the membrane may wrinkle, a local buckling event <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> where alternating crests and troughs appear parallel to the direction of principal tension <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, at which point additional refinements are required. In particular, Andra et al. <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref> show that equilibrium states with distributions of infinitesimal wrinkles are possible when bending stiffness is neglected, due to loss of convexity of the strain-energy function. Pipkin <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref> showed how to modify the constitutive behaviour of the material in regions where compressive stresses exist, such that a pseudo-surface is considered which is in simple tension in these regions, neglecting the local details of the wrinkled structure in favour of global results; this is called tension-field theory. For further details on treatments of wrinkling see for example Pipkin <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, Steigmann <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, Epstein and Forcinito <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, and Libai and Givoli <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. A physical example of such wrinkles may be seen when a pointed object is pushed into a fixed curved piece of plastic wrap, causing straight crests to radiate from the point of contact.</p>
      <p>The indentation of an axisymmetric elastic membrane by a rigid body has been considered previously, although mostly through the use of linear elasticity. Here we are interested in large deformations, and therefore use non-linear elasticity theory to model the deflection of the membrane. Physical applications/occurrences of such indentations include puncture of rubber gloves by medical needles <xref rid="bib27 bib28" ref-type="bibr">[27,28]</xref>, stones embedding into rubber tyres <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref> and our specific interest of seed germination, which we shall discuss later.</p>
      <p>Yang and Hsu <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref> considered the indentation of a flat circular hyperelastic membrane by a rigid sphere, in the large deformation regime, using the three-dimensional Mooney–Rivlin strain-energy function. Liu and Ju <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> estimate the elastic modulus of a specific elastomeric film by comparing numerical simulations of the model introduced by Yang and Hsu <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref> with their experimental observations. Steigmann <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref> and Nadler and Steigmann <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref> consider the indentation and penetration of a material described by a compressible two-dimensional Varga strain-energy function by a spherical-tipped cylindrical indenter, and assume that the membrane will break if a punctured state, with a discontinuous membrane, is energetically favourable. Selvadurai <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref> compares finite element simulations of indentation with a spherical indenter with experimental results, and provides a thorough literature review on rubber membranes, including a discussion of friction effects.</p>
      <p>This rigid body indentation is closely related to the adhesion behaviour of a rigid punch attached to a membrane, which exhibits stretching as the rigid body is pulled away. This has been considered by, for example, Nadler and Tang <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, who show that non-linear elastic effects are important; they also find that the imposition of pre-stress on the material has a strong effect on the force required to separate the punch from the membrane.</p>
      <p>Haughton <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> consider the response of planar and hemispherical elastic membranes to filling with a specific volume of incompressible liquid, using a relaxed strain-energy function when the membrane becomes wrinkled. They find an instability whereby the depth of the liquid increases very rapidly with only a slight increase in volume. Depending on the strain-energy function this unstable behaviour may continue indefinitely or re-stabilise, corresponding to the bifurcation points of a uniformly inflated spherical membrane. Haughton <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> finds that the plane membrane is a special case in that it remains tense throughout the deformation, whereas a hemispherical membrane contains a wrinkled section when the volume of liquid is small, which also reappears briefly after the instability.</p>
      <p>In this article we shall generalise the previous work in three directions. First, we allow the profile of the indenter tip to be of general axisymmetric shape rather than only considering spherical indenters, although we shall exclude sharply pointed tips by imposing mild continuity requirements. Second, we wish to investigate membranes which are initially curved, introducing this change of reference configuration into the elastic equilibrium equations. Last, we also wish to compare the effects of using different strain-energy functions to describe the constitutive behaviour of the membrane.</p>
      <p>Our primary motivation behind considering this deformation lies in seed germination, in particular the stretching and rupture of the endosperm by the root-tip in certain species of germinating seeds, specifically the two related Brassicaceae species <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref> and <italic>Lepidium sativum</italic> <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. These two species have approximately ellipsoidal seeds, including a thin, deformable tissue called the endosperm which surrounds the embryo. During the germination process the embryo grows, pushing the root-tip against the endosperm, stretching it before rupture occurs. The shape of the root-tip is approximately prolate spheroidal, as is the surrounding endosperm, hence our interest here in non-flat membranes and non-spherical indenter tips.</p>
      <p>The endosperm itself is thin and highly curved, and rapidly dehydrates when separated from the rest of the seed. It is therefore difficult to use conventional techniques to measure the elastic properties of this tissue, and so an indirect method is required. We are particularly interested in determining the elastic properties of the endosperm as biological changes occur during germination which alter the cell wall microstructure.</p>
      <p>We therefore wish to lay the mathematical groundwork before modelling biological puncture force experiments in a later work. In these experiments the seed is dissected and the embryo removed before a metal indenter is pushed through the endosperm, examples of such experiments are given by Muller et al. <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. The force and position of the indenter are measured during this experiment, and we then wish to estimate the elastic properties of the endosperm using this technique, particularly how these properties change over time. It has been shown by Muller et al. <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> that the force required to puncture through <italic>L. sativum</italic> endosperms decreases during the germination timescale. In preliminary experiments it has been shown that the vertical length of endosperm may double in size before rupture, clearly requiring non-linear elasticity to model this effect.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0010">
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Theory</title>
      <sec id="s0015">
        <label>2.1</label>
        <title>Governing equations</title>
        <p>We shall use the theory of non-linear elasticity as detailed in Ogden <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> to model the deformation. We assume that the midsurface of the undeformed membrane has symmetry about a particular axis, and may therefore be described by cylindrical coordinates with respect to the usual basis <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">(<bold>e</bold><sub><italic>r</italic></sub>, <bold>e</bold><sub><italic>θ</italic></sub>, <bold>e</bold><sub><italic>z</italic></sub>)</textual-form><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si0027.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="eq0005"><label>(2.1)</label><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si0028.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>Θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>Θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si0029.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> is the arclength along the reference midsurface, which will be used as the independent variable throughout. We shall take the origin of our coordinates to be the centre of the membrane, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si0030.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, as well as requiring that the membrane be smooth there, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si0031.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>. If the membrane is initially flat we set <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si0032.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, in this case <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si0033.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> may be used as the independent coordinate as in previous studies.</p>
        <p>We are interested in axisymmetric deformations that map the reference configuration <bold>X</bold> to the deformed configuration <bold>x</bold>, the midsurface of which is given by<disp-formula id="eq0010"><label>(2.2)</label><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si0036.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mtext>.</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>A point in the deformed surface is therefore given by two variables, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si0037.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" altimg="si0038.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>, the three-dimensional shape being then given by rotation around the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" altimg="si0039.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>-axis. Immediately, due to the imposed axisymmetry, we may identify <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>Θ</italic> = <italic>θ</italic></textual-form><mml:math id="M13" altimg="si0040.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>Θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. We also impose the same conditions as in the undeformed state at the axis, that is <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" altimg="si0041.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
        <p>Here we shall solve the static problem, where we assume that there is no time-dependence involved in the deformation. This is appropriate to the quasi-steady cases in which we are interested, for which the indentation is slow compared to the inertia of the membrane.</p>
        <p>Appendix A outlines the derivation of the equilibrium equations for a curved membrane, using the membrane-like shell approximation to the three-dimensional theory of elasticity, as discussed above. The principal stretch ratios may be defined in the circumferential, radial, and normal directions in the form (see Appendix A for details):<disp-formula id="eq0015"><label>(2.3)</label><mml:math id="M15" altimg="si0042.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" altimg="si0043.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" altimg="si0044.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> are the deformed and undeformed thicknesses and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M18" altimg="si0045.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> is the arclength in the deformed configuration. We assume that the membrane is made of a hyperelastic material with a strain-energy function given by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" altimg="si0046.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, where we have already assumed that the material is incompressible and therefore set <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>θ</italic></sub><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> = 1</textual-form><mml:math id="M20" altimg="si0047.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>; see <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> for more details. The principal stress resultants per unit length in the deformed membrane are therefore defined as<disp-formula id="eq0020"><label>(2.4)</label><mml:math id="M21" altimg="si0048.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>which may be seen to be <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" altimg="si0049.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" altimg="si0050.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the usual principal Cauchy stress in incompressible three-dimensional elasticity, and similarly for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" altimg="si0051.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. Appendix A shows how the stresses only occur in the combination <inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" altimg="si0052.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, and hence we introduce <inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" altimg="si0053.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> with dimensions of force per length.</p>
        <p>While the theory presented here is appropriate for any isotropic incompressible strain-energy function, we shall study some specific examples in order to make later comparisons. One commonly used such function is the Mooney–Rivlin strain-energy function:<disp-formula id="eq0025"><label>(2.5)</label><mml:math id="M27" altimg="si0054.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>μ</italic> is the infinitesimal shear modulus of the elastic material and <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">0 ≤ <italic>α</italic> ≤ 1</textual-form><mml:math id="M28" altimg="si0056.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is a parameter that controls the deviation from a Hookean response. An important special case of <xref rid="eq0025" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.5)</xref> is the neo-Hookean strain-energy function, which occurs when <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>α</italic> = 0</textual-form><mml:math id="M29" altimg="si0057.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. The <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">(1 + <italic>α</italic>)</textual-form><mml:math id="M30" altimg="si0058.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> in the denominator of <xref rid="eq0025" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.5)</xref> is necessary to ensure that <italic>μ</italic> is the infinitesimal shear modulus of the material. Ref. <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref> introduced a strain-energy function designed for the modelling of biological soft tissues such as healthy arterial tissue, which commonly feature strongly strain-stiffening behaviour:<disp-formula id="eq0030"><label>(2.6)</label><mml:math id="M31" altimg="si0060.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>Γ</italic> is a positive parameter representing the degree of strain-stiffening. In the limit as <italic>Γ</italic> approaches zero, <xref rid="eq0030" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.6)</xref> also recovers the neo-Hookean strain-energy function.</p>
        <p>As shown in Appendix A, the equilibrium equations in the tangential and normal directions are respectively given by<disp-formula id="eq0035"><label>(2.7a)</label><mml:math id="M32" altimg="si0063.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="eq0040"><label>(2.7b)</label><mml:math id="M33" altimg="si0064.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M34" altimg="si0065.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the pressure difference across the membrane in the normal direction, and the principal curvatures <inline-formula><mml:math id="M35" altimg="si0066.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> are defined in <xref rid="eq0180" ref-type="disp-formula">(A.16)</xref>. The system <xref rid="eq0035 eq0040" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.7)</xref> contains terms involving <inline-formula><mml:math id="M36" altimg="si0067.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>″</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>″</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, and is therefore a third order differential system, as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M37" altimg="si0068.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> does not appear explicitly. Rearranging <xref rid="eq0035" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.7a)</xref> for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M38" altimg="si0069.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and using Codazzi's equation <xref rid="eq0185" ref-type="disp-formula">(A.17)</xref>, we may integrate <xref rid="eq0040" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.7b)</xref> to find<disp-formula id="eq0045"><label>(2.8)</label><mml:math id="M39" altimg="si0070.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>π</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>which may be used, provided <inline-formula><mml:math id="M40" altimg="si0071.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> is constant, to reduce the differential order of the system by one. We note that this integral exists for a membrane of any undeformed shape, and corresponds to the resultant in the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M41" altimg="si0072.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> direction. The integration constant <inline-formula><mml:math id="M42" altimg="si0073.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the total transverse force acting on the membrane <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0020">
        <label>2.2</label>
        <title>Wrinkling</title>
        <p>Using <xref rid="eq0035 eq0040" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.7)</xref> we may calculate the deformed shape of the membrane, assuming that the stress resultants both stay positive over the region. If either stress resultant becomes negative then the theory as outlined above is not appropriate, as a true membrane can not support compressive stresses. The regions with such a negative compressive stress are assumed to have wrinkled, with the crests of the wrinkles perpendicular to the compressive stress direction; this is a local buckling instability <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. We therefore introduce tension-field theory to consider a smoothed-out ‘pseudo-surface’ that is in equilibrium, with the corresponding stress exactly zero everywhere.</p>
        <p>For the strain-energy functions considered here, the minimum of <italic>W</italic> with respect to <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>θ</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M43" altimg="si0074.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, subject to both stretches being positive, occurs when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M44" altimg="si0075.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>≡</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, with an equivalent expression for <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M45" altimg="si0076.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. This is termed as the natural width of the strip in tension by Pipkin <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Following Pipkin <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref> we introduce the tension-field theory by defining a relaxed strain-energy density function as<disp-formula id="eq0050"><label>(2.9)</label><mml:math id="M46" altimg="si0077.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>⁎</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="{"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></disp-formula>which is the quasiconvexification of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M47" altimg="si0078.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>. Using this definition of <italic>W</italic><sup>⁎</sup> we recover the normal behaviour in the taut region while resolving the wrinkled regions. When both stretches are less than unity, the membrane becomes slack, with no tension in either direction. If this occurs here then <xref rid="eq0045" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.8)</xref> implies that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M48" altimg="si0079.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and thus there is no indentation, when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M49" altimg="si0080.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
        <p>We find numerically that the wrinkled region, if it exists, occurs when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M50" altimg="si0081.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>. We therefore have the following system of equations in the wrinkled region:<disp-formula id="eq0055"><label>(2.10)</label><mml:math id="M51" altimg="si0082.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>s</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mtext>.</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>When the pressure <inline-formula><mml:math id="M52" altimg="si0083.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> is zero, <xref rid="eq0055" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.10)</xref><sub>1</sub> implies that either the membrane is slack (and thus there is no indentation) or <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>κ</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub> = 0</textual-form><mml:math id="M53" altimg="si0084.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. We may therefore integrate <xref rid="eq0055" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.10)</xref> to give<disp-formula id="eq0060"><label>(2.11)</label><mml:math id="M54" altimg="si0085.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>const</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>s</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>const</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>where the constants are determined by the values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M55" altimg="si0086.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M56" altimg="si0087.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> at the point at which the membrane first becomes wrinkled, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M57" altimg="si0088.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
        <p>The first order differential equation in <xref rid="eq0060" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.11)</xref> may then be integrated until <inline-formula><mml:math id="M58" altimg="si0089.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>˜</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, at which point <inline-formula><mml:math id="M59" altimg="si0090.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> as given by <xref rid="eq0020" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.4)</xref> becomes zero again, this is <inline-formula><mml:math id="M60" altimg="si0091.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. This process may then be repeated if the membrane becomes wrinkled again, if required. Clearly, in the pseudo-surface the lines in the <italic>s</italic>-direction must be straight as the associated curvature <inline-formula><mml:math id="M61" altimg="si0092.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is zero. Libai and Givoli <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> present a general algorithm for dealing with axisymmetric wrinkling, and this approach conforms to their technique.</p>
        <p>Haughton and McKay <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> and Haughton <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> state that the extent (in terms of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M62" altimg="si0093.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>) of the wrinkled region is determined solely by the tense theory, and suggest that if you use the tense theory even when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M63" altimg="si0094.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, then <inline-formula><mml:math id="M64" altimg="si0095.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M65" altimg="si0096.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. However, this is contrary to what we find numerically here, and so we integrate the wrinkled region exactly.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0025">
        <label>2.3</label>
        <title>Indenter profile</title>
        <p>We assume that the indenter is a cylinder with a curved tip, with a specified axisymmetric profile where the components in the <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><bold>e</bold><sub><italic>r</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M66" altimg="si0097.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><bold>e</bold><sub><italic>z</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M67" altimg="si0098.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> directions are given parametrically in terms of an angle <italic>ϕ</italic> from the negative <italic>z</italic>-axis. We therefore assume the indenter surface is described by<disp-formula id="eq0065"><label>(2.12)</label><mml:math id="M68" altimg="si0100.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="{"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M69" altimg="si0101.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> is the radius of the cylindrical part of the indenter to which this curved tip is attached. We require that the axisymmetry around the <italic>z</italic>-axis is maintained and hence <italic>A</italic>(0)=0, and also that the indenter tip smoothly connects to the cylindrical part, <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>A</italic>(<italic>π</italic> / 2) = 1,  <italic>A</italic>′(<italic>π</italic> / 2) = 0</textual-form><mml:math id="M70" altimg="si0102.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. In addition, we require the smoothness condition of <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>B</italic>′(0) = 0</textual-form><mml:math id="M71" altimg="si0103.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, which prevents the consideration of perfectly sharp pointed tips, although we may approach these. We shall also impose the restriction that the indenter profile is convex, although for some non-convex profiles replacing the profile by its convex hull may give the appropriate shape, although the calculation of the load exerted on the membrane may need to be adjusted.</p>
        <p>If the indenter tip is spherical, then <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>A</italic>(<italic>ϕ</italic>) = sin<italic>ϕ</italic>,  <italic>B</italic>(<italic>ϕ</italic>) =  − cos<italic>ϕ</italic></textual-form><mml:math id="M72" altimg="si0104.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>sin</mml:mi><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>cos</mml:mi><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, where the negative sign merely ensures that we consider the indentation to occur in the negative <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><bold>e</bold><sub><italic>z</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M73" altimg="si0105.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> direction. Spheroidal tips may be considered by setting <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>B</italic>(<italic>ϕ</italic>) =  − <italic>γ</italic>cos<italic>ϕ</italic></textual-form><mml:math id="M74" altimg="si0106.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>cos</mml:mi><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>γ</italic> &gt; 1</textual-form><mml:math id="M75" altimg="si0107.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> for a prolate spheroid and <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">0 &lt; <italic>γ</italic> &lt; 1</textual-form><mml:math id="M76" altimg="si0108.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> for an oblate spheroid. As <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>γ</italic> → 0</textual-form><mml:math id="M77" altimg="si0109.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, the case of the indentation by a flat cylindrical punch is approached, while <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>γ</italic> →  ∞ </textual-form><mml:math id="M78" altimg="si0110.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mo>∞</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> approximates indentation by a sharp tip.</p>
        <p>We note that it is possible to use an indenter which consists of just the ‘tip’ by modifying <xref rid="eq0065" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.12)</xref>, for instance when a solid sphere is allowed to deform the membrane under gravity as in the experiments of Liu and Ju <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. For a given applied force this may be modelled by a spherical-tipped cylindrical indenter, provided that the deformed surface does not touch the sides of the cylinder. Indeed, it has been stated in Selvadurai <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref> and Nadler and Steigmann <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref> that the deformed surface never makes contact with the cylindrical part prior to membrane penetration, although our preliminary experimental results and the second figure in Nguyen and Vu-Khanh <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref> suggest otherwise, so perhaps that statement is a specification to their equations. In particular for the Varga strain-energy function we agree with Nadler and Steigmann <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, but not for general strain-energy functions. Hence we do allow the membrane to touch the cylindrical part of the indenter, where we set <inline-formula><mml:math id="M79" altimg="si0111.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≡</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> and solve for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M80" altimg="si0112.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>, although these regions will be dashed on the load–indentation graphs presented in <xref rid="s0040" ref-type="sec">Section 3</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0030">
        <label>2.4</label>
        <title>Solution procedure</title>
        <p>We now non-dimensionalise with respect to the undeformed radius, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M81" altimg="si0113.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, and the infinitesimal shear modulus, <italic>μ</italic>: <disp-formula id="eq0070"><mml:math id="M82" altimg="si0115.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="eq0075"><label>(2.13)</label><mml:math id="M83" altimg="si0116.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">HF</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mtext>.</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>For flat membranes <inline-formula><mml:math id="M84" altimg="si0117.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≡</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>, but for a curved membrane this is not generally true. This rescaling leaves the previously stated equations for the stretches, stress resultants and curvatures unchanged, apart from dropping the hats from all variables and removing <inline-formula><mml:math id="M85" altimg="si0118.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> from <xref rid="eq0020" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.4)</xref>. The parameter <italic>ρ</italic> is now a non-dimensional ratio relating the radius of the indenter to the radius of the undeformed membrane.</p>
        <p>The problem may be divided into two distinct regions of <italic>S</italic>, that is the region in the undeformed geometry that is now in contact with the indenter, <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">0 ≤ <italic>S</italic> ≤ <italic>S</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M86" altimg="si0120.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, and the outer region where the membrane is free, <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>S</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> &lt; <italic>S</italic> ≤ <italic>L</italic></textual-form><mml:math id="M87" altimg="si0121.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. For a flat membrane, <italic>S</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> is the radius of the circle in the undeformed membrane which is in contact with the indenter in the deformed configuration, while for a curved reference surface <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>R</italic>(<italic>S</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>)</textual-form><mml:math id="M88" altimg="si0122.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the radius of the corresponding circle in the undeformed membrane. If wrinkling occurs in the free region there will be four distinct regions instead, as we find numerically that the membrane returns to biaxial tension by <italic>S</italic>=<italic>L</italic> in the examples considered here.</p>
        <p>While the membrane is in contact with the indenter, we assume that the deformed shape follows the surface of the indenter and we therefore have<disp-formula id="eq0080"><label>(2.14)</label><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>r</italic>(<italic>S</italic>) = <italic>ρ</italic><italic>A</italic>(<italic>ϕ</italic>(<italic>S</italic>)),  <italic>z</italic>(<italic>S</italic>) =  − <italic>δ</italic> + <italic>ρ</italic><italic>B</italic>(<italic>ϕ</italic>(<italic>S</italic>)),</textual-form><mml:math id="M89" altimg="si0123.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>δ</italic> is the depth of indentation to be found as part of the solution. Therefore in the contact region<disp-formula id="eq0085"><label>(2.15)</label><mml:math id="M90" altimg="si0125.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dA</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dB</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dS</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>where we have used <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ϕ</italic>′(<italic>S</italic>) &gt; 0</textual-form><mml:math id="M91" altimg="si0126.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. We may therefore evaluate the first equilibrium equation, <xref rid="eq0035" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.7a)</xref>, to find <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ϕ</italic>(<italic>S</italic>)</textual-form><mml:math id="M92" altimg="si0127.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> given appropriate boundary conditions. The second equilibrium equation enables us to calculate the pressure <italic>P</italic> exerted by the indenter on the membrane after calculating the membrane deformation, but is auxiliary to computing the deformation itself in the contact region.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0035">
        <label>2.5</label>
        <title>Boundary conditions</title>
        <p>We now specify the boundary conditions in order to integrate the equations above. The requirement of axisymmetry implies that <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ϕ</italic>(0) = 0</textual-form><mml:math id="M93" altimg="si0128.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, while using the restrictions on <italic>A</italic> and <italic>B</italic> we find <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ϕ</italic>′(0) = <italic>ρ</italic><sup> − 1</sup><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub>(0) / <italic>A</italic>′(0)</textual-form><mml:math id="M94" altimg="si0129.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, and we can therefore integrate <xref rid="eq0035" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.7a)</xref> to find <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ϕ</italic>(<italic>S</italic>)</textual-form><mml:math id="M95" altimg="si0130.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> for a given stretch at the pole <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub>(0)</textual-form><mml:math id="M96" altimg="si0131.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p>
        <p>In the region <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>S</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> &lt; <italic>S</italic> ≤ <italic>L</italic></textual-form><mml:math id="M97" altimg="si0132.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, the membrane is governed by <xref rid="eq0035 eq0040" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.7)</xref> with <italic>P</italic>=0, which gives us a third order system for <italic>r</italic> and <italic>z</italic>, or <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M98" altimg="si0133.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>θ</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M99" altimg="si0134.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. We require continuity of the membrane shape, and so we prescribe <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>r</italic>(<italic>S</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>), <italic>r</italic>′(<italic>S</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>), <italic>z</italic>′(<italic>S</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>)</textual-form><mml:math id="M100" altimg="si0135.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> to be those given from the inner region. We allow for the membrane to be stretched prior to indentation, imposing a pre-stretch of <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> ≥ 1</textual-form><mml:math id="M101" altimg="si0136.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> on the material, that is <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> = <italic>r</italic>(<italic>L</italic>)</textual-form><mml:math id="M102" altimg="si0137.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. This pre-stretch corresponds to moving the circular boundary <italic>S</italic>=<italic>L</italic> outwards in the <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><bold>e</bold><sub><italic>r</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M103" altimg="si0138.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> direction, inducing a deformation in the membrane; if the membrane is not initially flat then this will have the result of changing the shape of the initial profile by decreasing the vertical ‘height’ of the membrane, as the material moves towards the level of the boundary circle.</p>
        <p>Utilising a shooting method we specify the stretch at the pole, <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub>(0) = <italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>θ</italic></sub>(0) = <italic>λ</italic><sub>0</sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M104" altimg="si0139.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, and then guess a value of <italic>S</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub>. We then iterate on <italic>S</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> to satisfy the condition <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>θ</italic></sub>(<italic>L</italic>) = <italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M105" altimg="si0140.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. Having found the appropriate value of <italic>S</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> for a given <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub>0</sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M106" altimg="si0141.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M107" altimg="si0142.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, we may then calculate the value of the central displacement of the membrane which is given by<disp-formula id="eq0090"><label>(2.16)</label><mml:math id="M108" altimg="si0143.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dz</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dS</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dS</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dz</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dS</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dS</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dz</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dS</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dS</mml:mi><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>where the solutions in the appropriate regions are substituted into each integral of <xref rid="eq0090" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.16)</xref>. From this we calculate the indentation depth, <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>δ</italic> = <italic>z</italic><sub><italic>h</italic></sub> − <italic>Z</italic><sub><italic>h</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M109" altimg="si0144.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>Z</italic><sub><italic>h</italic></sub> = <italic>Z</italic>(<italic>L</italic>) − <italic>Z</italic>(0)</textual-form><mml:math id="M110" altimg="si0145.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the original depth of the membrane. Having done this, we may vary <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub>0</sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M111" altimg="si0146.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and repeat the process in order to solve for a variety of indentation depths, or equivalently for values of the applied force <italic>F</italic>.</p>
        <p>We therefore require the following parameters to be specified: the membrane pre-stretch <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M112" altimg="si0147.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, the radius of the cylindrical part of the indenter <italic>ρ</italic>, the undeformed membrane shape (<italic>R</italic>,<italic>Z</italic>) and the shape of the indenter tip (<italic>A</italic>,<italic>B</italic>). In addition, the strain-energy function must be specified, along with the value of any parameters included therein. The choice of strain-energy function is not a trivial matter in the large indentation regime, and we will show how the force required to indent the membrane is strongly dependent on the form of the strain-energy function used, past the initial linear regime.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0040">
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Results and discussion</title>
      <p><xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> shows how the deformed configuration changes with increasing <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub>0</sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M113" altimg="si0149.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> for a spherical indenter and a flat membrane, reproducing Fig. 2 of Yang and Hsu <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. It may be seen that the deformed shape goes from having positive curvature while in contact with the indenter to a negative curvature in the free region. This is as expected as Eq. <xref rid="eq0040" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.7b)</xref> implies that an odd number of the quantities <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>T</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub>, <italic>T</italic><sub><italic>θ</italic></sub>, <italic>κ</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub>, <italic>κ</italic><sub><italic>θ</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M114" altimg="si0150.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> must be negative in the free region, and therefore in unwrinkled parts of the membrane one of the curvatures must be negative. When the membrane is initially flat wrinkling is never observed, as found by Haughton and McKay <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> for the fluid-loaded case.</p>
      <p>Having calculated the deformed shape of the membrane we may evaluate the transverse force <italic>F</italic> in the free region, this corresponds to an indentation displacement <italic>δ</italic>. <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> shows a variety of non-dimensional force–indentation curves for spheroidal indenter tips of varying shape. As is intuitively obvious, blunter indenter tips require more force to achieve the same indentation depth. The two extremal curves in <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> approach indentation with a flat punch and a point load respectively. In <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, and in the following figures, dashed lines represent where the membrane has come into contact with the cylindrical part of the indenter, which occurs sooner with flatter tips.</p>
      <p><xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> shows the load–indentation curves for a variety of strain-energy functions, where it may be seen that for this set of parameters up to <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>δ</italic> ≈ 0.4</textual-form><mml:math id="M115" altimg="si0152.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.4</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> the material responses are identical, which is consistent to the results of Pujara and Lardner <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref> regarding the inflation of circular membranes. Past this range the varied stress–strain behaviour of the strain-energy functions give different loads for the same indentation, and thereafter the specification of the strain-energy function becomes important. The Fung material model, generally used for biological tissues such as arteries and muscles, predicts much higher loads than the other models for the same amount of indentation, as expected due to the strain-stiffening behaviour the Fung model encapsulates.</p>
      <p>The neo-Hookean material model gives a horizontal asymptote in <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, with a constant <italic>F</italic> corresponding to an infinite range of indentation. This is a consequence of using the neo-Hookean strain-energy function outside its range of validity. The Mooney–Rivlin material gives linear growth of <italic>F</italic> with <italic>δ</italic>, depending on the value of <italic>α</italic>, while the Fung material shows an exponential growth.</p>
      <p>In particular, when the membrane is touching the cylindrical portion of the indenter we have <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>r</italic>′ = 0</textual-form><mml:math id="M116" altimg="si0155.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, and therefore evaluating <xref rid="eq0045" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.8)</xref> at <italic>S</italic>=<italic>S</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> gives<disp-formula id="eq0095"><label>(3.17)</label><mml:math id="M117" altimg="si0156.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo minsize="13pt">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>which explains how the response is dominated by the behaviour of the stress–strain relationship, as <xref rid="eq0095" ref-type="disp-formula">(3.17)</xref> indicates that force is proportional to the stress.</p>
      <p><xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> shows how the size of the indenter affects the load behaviour, although the quantitative response behaviour is not affected. For large indentation depths the curves are parallel to each other, both before and after the membrane begins to touch the sides of the indenter. <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> shows how the shape of the indenter tip affects the indentation of an initially curved membrane. More pointed indenters require less force to achieve the same indentation depth, as is intuitively obvious.</p>
      <p>In all the force–indentation curves for flat membranes presented above, in the linear elastic limit the relation <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>F</italic> ∝ <italic>δ</italic><sup>3</sup></textual-form><mml:math id="M118" altimg="si0157.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>∝</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> may be seen, corresponding to the Schwerin-type solution in linear elasticity <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Begley and Mackin <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> derive an approximate solution with such a cubic relationship for a finite-sized spherical indenter and a flat membrane, but we do not agree numerically with their proportionality constant <xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">(Fig. 6</xref>).</p>
      <p><xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> shows the indentation of an initially spherical membrane by a spherical indenter of smaller radius. It can be seen that the deformed shape does not follow the curvature of the reference surface, which may be expected from the previous comment that <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>κ</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M119" altimg="si0158.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>T</italic><sub><italic>θ</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M120" altimg="si0159.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> must be negative, and from the fact that the governing equations do not include a term involving the reference curvatures, i.e. <xref rid="eq0180" ref-type="disp-formula">(A.16)</xref> but with <italic>r</italic> and <italic>z</italic> replaced by <italic>R</italic> and <italic>Z</italic>. In order to include such a term in the governing equations, we would need to consider a shell theory where the energy depends on the curvature of the shell in addition to the stretching, as discussed in <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref> for example. This increases the order of the governing equations from third to seventh order, and also introduces the question of determining how the strain-energy function depends on a further set of invariants; an additional two which depend only on the curvatures and three coupling terms between the curvatures and the stretches.</p>
      <p><xref rid="f0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> shows the load–indentation curves for initially curved surfaces of the form, <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>R</italic>(<italic>S</italic>) = <italic>S</italic>, <italic>Z</italic>(<italic>S</italic>) =  − <italic>ψ</italic>cos(<italic>π</italic><italic>S</italic> / 2), 0 ≤ <italic>S</italic> ≤ 1</textual-form><mml:math id="M121" altimg="si0160.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mi>cos</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. As <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ψ</italic> → 0</textual-form><mml:math id="M122" altimg="si0161.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> we recover the flat membrane, and we see that as the reference surface departs from this shape the required load for greater indentation increases.</p>
      <p>For pronouncedly curved reference surfaces, <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ψ</italic> ≈ 0.5</textual-form><mml:math id="M123" altimg="si0162.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, we find that the theory used here gives a vanishingly small load for a finite indentation displacement. As we take the numerical limit <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub>0</sub> → 1</textual-form><mml:math id="M124" altimg="si0163.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, the calculated load tends towards zero but there is a non-zero displacement, <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>δ</italic> ≈ 0.09</textual-form><mml:math id="M125" altimg="si0164.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.09</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> in the membrane shown in <xref rid="f0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>. We believe that the reason this occurs is that the membrane wrinkles in the indentation region, where we are prescribing the displacement to be that of the indenter.</p>
      <p>This limitation does not prevent us from solving for larger values of <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub>0</sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M126" altimg="si0165.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> due to the quasi-static solution procedure used here. <xref rid="f0045" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> shows the same curved membrane as <xref rid="f0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>, but with the Fung strain-energy function instead of the Mooney–Rivlin. The linear elastic behaviour of the two graphs is the same, but at large displacement or load the impact of the strain-energy function may be seen.</p>
      <p>When the membrane is flat, both the stress resultants stay positive and wrinkling does not occur. For curved membranes, it is possible to increase the radial pre-stretch <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M127" altimg="si0166.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> or the indentation distance <italic>δ</italic> to ensure that the membrane remains in tension in the deformed configuration. This finding agrees directly with that of Haughton <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> for fluid filled membranes. For instance, if a spherical indenter nearly fills a spherical membrane, i.e. <italic>ρ</italic> is close to one, then wrinkling is only found for very small levels of <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub>0</sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M128" altimg="si0169.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> with no pre-stretch, and eliminated entirely for slight amounts of pre-stretch, such as <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> ≥ 1.1</textual-form><mml:math id="M129" altimg="si0170.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.1</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. However, the imposition of the pre-strain will change the shape of the non-flat membrane prior to indentation, requiring knowledge of the shape of the membrane prior to the pre-strain, which may not be available in experimental situations.</p>
      <p>As the indenter is pushed into a flat membrane the contact point <italic>S</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> initially increases as more of the indenter comes into contact with the material, before reaching a maximum value and then decreasing, as shown in <xref rid="f0050" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>. This later decrease is due to the fact that, at larger indentation depth, a comparatively small area of the reference membrane is highly stretched over the indenter tip. Once the membrane begins to touch the cylindrical sides of the indenter the behaviour of <italic>S</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> is governed by the strain-energy function in the same manner as <italic>F</italic>. This behaviour is found by Nadler and Steigmann <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref> for the two-dimensional compressible Varga strain-energy function, although in this case the membrane never comes into contact with the cylindrical part of the indenter.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0045">
      <label>4</label>
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>We have shown how to extend the previously presented non-linear elasticity theories of indentation with a finite radius indenter to include the effects of different strain-energy functions, non-spherical indenter tips and initially curved membranes. The importance of correctly specifying the strain-energy function is shown clearly, along with the effects that changing the shape of the indenter has.</p>
      <p>Indentation tests are a useful method of determining the properties of an elastic membrane at large strain, and with experimental data from a wide variety of shapes and sizes of indenter a suitable strain-energy function may be fitted to the data, giving more information than merely spherical indenter tips. One difficulty may be in identifying where the start of the force–indentation curve occurs experimentally, due to the detection limits of the equipment used, which may mean that the beginning of the curve is missed.</p>
      <p>As mentioned in the Introduction, we plan to compare with experimental data from puncture force experiments on germinating seeds, with the aim of estimating the elastic properties of the endosperm using the theory presented here. The experiments will result in load–indentation curves, which we may then use to fit to the load–indentation curves resulting from the method here. In this case, the unknown parameters are the infinitesimal shear modulus and the strain-energy function of the material, and we shall attempt to characterize these through the indirect indentation method.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Andra</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Warby</surname>
              <given-names>M.K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Whiteman</surname>
              <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Contact problems of hyperelastic membranes: existence theory</article-title>
          <source>Mathematical Methods in the Applied Sciences</source>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2000</year>
          <fpage>865</fpage>
          <lpage>895</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Begley</surname>
              <given-names>M.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mackin</surname>
              <given-names>T.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spherical indentation of freestanding circular thin films in the membrane regime</article-title>
          <source>Journal of the Mechanics and Physics of Solids</source>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <year>2004</year>
          <fpage>2005</fpage>
          <lpage>2023</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Epstein</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Forcinito</surname>
              <given-names>M.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Anisotropic membrane wrinkling: theory and analysis</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Solids and Structures</source>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <issue>30–31</issue>
          <year>2001</year>
          <fpage>5253</fpage>
          <lpage>5272</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Perturbation methods and nonlinear stability analysis</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Fu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogden</surname>
              <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <series>Nonlinear Elasticity: Theory and Applications</series>
          <year>2001</year>
          <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fung</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Biomechanics: Mechanical Properties of Living Tissues</chapter-title>
          <year>1993</year>
          <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Haughton</surname>
              <given-names>D.M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Axisymmetric elastic membranes subjected to fluid loading</article-title>
          <source>IMA Journal of Applied Mathematics</source>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <year>1996</year>
          <fpage>303</fpage>
          <lpage>320</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Haughton</surname>
              <given-names>D.M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Elastic membranes</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Fu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogden</surname>
              <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <series>Nonlinear Elasticity: Theory and Applications</series>
          <year>2001</year>
          <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Haughton</surname>
              <given-names>D.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McKay</surname>
              <given-names>B.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wrinkling of annular discs subjected to radial displacements</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Engineering Science</source>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>1995</year>
          <fpage>335</fpage>
          <lpage>350</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Haughton</surname>
              <given-names>D.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogden</surname>
              <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>On the incremental equations in non-linear elasticity I. Membrane theory</article-title>
          <source>Journal of the Mechanics and Physics of Solids</source>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <year>1978</year>
          <fpage>93</fpage>
          <lpage>110</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Holdsworth</surname>
              <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bentsink</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soppe</surname>
              <given-names>W.J.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular networks regulating Arabidopsis seed maturation, after-ripening, dormancy and germination</article-title>
          <source>New Phytologist</source>
          <volume>179</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>33</fpage>
          <lpage>54</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18422904</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Humphrey</surname>
              <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Review: computer methods in membrane biomechanics</article-title>
          <source>Computer Methods in Biomechanics and Biomedical Engineering</source>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>1998</year>
          <fpage>171</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11264803</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Humphrey</surname>
              <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Review paper: Continuum biomechanics of soft biological tissues</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences</source>
          <volume>459</volume>
          <issue>2029</issue>
          <year>2003</year>
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <lpage>46</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jenkins</surname>
              <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leonard</surname>
              <given-names>J.W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nonlinear dynamic response of membranes: state of the art</article-title>
          <source>Applied Mechanics Reviews</source>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <year>1991</year>
          <fpage>319</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Komaragiri</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Begley</surname>
              <given-names>M.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simmonds</surname>
              <given-names>J.G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The mechanical response of freestanding circular elastic films under point and pressure loads</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Applied Mechanics</source>
          <volume>72</volume>
          <year>2005</year>
          <fpage>203</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Le Dret</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raoult</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The membrane shell model in nonlinear elasticity: a variational asymptotic derivation</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Nonlinear Science</source>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>1996</year>
          <fpage>59</fpage>
          <lpage>84</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steigmann</surname>
              <given-names>D.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Point loads on a hemispherical elastic membrane</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Non-linear Mechanics</source>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>1995</year>
          <fpage>569</fpage>
          <lpage>581</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Libai</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Givoli</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analysis of pulled axisymmetric membranes with wrinkling</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Solids and Structures</source>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2002</year>
          <fpage>1259</fpage>
          <lpage>1274</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Libai</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simmonds</surname>
              <given-names>J.G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>The Nonlinear Theory of Elastic Shells</chapter-title>
          <year>1998</year>
          <publisher-name>Cambridge Univ Press</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>K.K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ju</surname>
              <given-names>B.F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel technique for mechanical characterization of thin elastomeric membrane</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Physics D: Applied Physics</source>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <year>2001</year>
          <fpage>L91</fpage>
          <lpage>L94</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Miyamura</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wrinkling on stretched circular membrane under in-plane torsion: bifurcation analyses and experiments</article-title>
          <source>Engineering Structures</source>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <year>2000</year>
          <fpage>1407</fpage>
          <lpage>1425</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Muller</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tintelnot</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leubner-Metzger</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Endosperm-limited Brassicaceae seed germination: abscisic acid inhibits embryo-induced endosperm weakening of <italic>Lepidium sativum</italic> (cress) and endosperm rupture of cress and <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant and Cell Physiology</source>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>864</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16705010</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib22">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nadler</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rubin</surname>
              <given-names>M.B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analysis of constitutive assumptions for the strain energy of a generalized elastic membrane in a nonlinear contact problem</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Elasticity</source>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>77</fpage>
          <lpage>95</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nadler</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steigmann</surname>
              <given-names>D.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Modeling the indentation, penetration and cavitation of elastic membranes</article-title>
          <source>Journal of the Mechanics and Physics of Solids</source>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>2005</fpage>
          <lpage>2029</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nadler</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Decohesion of a rigid punch from non-linear membrane undergoing finite axisymmetric deformation</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Non-Linear Mechanics</source>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>716</fpage>
          <lpage>721</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib25">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Naghdi</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Large deformation possible in every isotropic elastic membrane</article-title>
          <source>Philosophical Transactions for the Royal Society of London. Series A, Mathematical and Physical Sciences</source>
          <volume>287</volume>
          <issue>1341</issue>
          <year>1977</year>
          <fpage>145</fpage>
          <lpage>187</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib26">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Naghdi</surname>
              <given-names>P.M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>The theory of shells and plates</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Trusdell</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <series>Flugge's Handbuch der Physik</series>
          <volume>VI</volume>
          <year>1972</year>
          <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
          <fpage>425</fpage>
          <lpage>460</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib27">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nguyen</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vu-Khanh</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dolez</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lara</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Puncture of elastomer membranes by medical needles. Part I: mechanisms</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Fracture</source>
          <volume>155</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>75</fpage>
          <lpage>81</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib28">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nguyen</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vu-Khanh</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dolez</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lara</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Puncture of elastomer membranes by medical needles. Part II: mechanics</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Fracture</source>
          <volume>155</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>83</fpage>
          <lpage>91</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib29">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nguyen</surname>
              <given-names>C.T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vu-Khanh</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mechanics and mechanisms of puncture of elastomer membranes</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Materials Science</source>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <issue>24</issue>
          <year>2004</year>
          <fpage>7361</fpage>
          <lpage>7364</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib30">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ogden</surname>
              <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Non-linear elastic deformations</chapter-title>
          <year>1997</year>
          <publisher-name>Dover Publications</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib31">
        <label>31</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ogden</surname>
              <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Elements of the theory of finite elasticity</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Fu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogden</surname>
              <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <series>Nonlinear Elasticity: Theory and Applications</series>
          <year>2001</year>
          <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib32">
        <label>32</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pipkin</surname>
              <given-names>A.C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The relaxed energy density for isotropic elastic membranes</article-title>
          <source>IMA Journal of Applied Mathematics</source>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>1986</year>
          <fpage>85</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib33">
        <label>33</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pujara</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lardner</surname>
              <given-names>T.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Deformations of elastic membranes – effect of different constitutive relations</article-title>
          <source>Zeitschrift Fur Angewandte Mathematik und Physik</source>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>1978</year>
          <fpage>315</fpage>
          <lpage>327</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib34">
        <label>34</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Selvadurai</surname>
              <given-names>A.P.S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Deflections of a rubber membrane</article-title>
          <source>Journal of the Mechanics and Physics of Solids</source>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>1093</fpage>
          <lpage>1119</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib35">
        <label>35</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Steigmann</surname>
              <given-names>D.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tension-field theory</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London. Series A, Mathematical and Physical Sciences</source>
          <volume>429</volume>
          <issue>1876</issue>
          <year>1990</year>
          <fpage>141</fpage>
          <lpage>173</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib36">
        <label>36</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Steigmann</surname>
              <given-names>D.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Elastic surfaces</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Fu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogden</surname>
              <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <series>Nonlinear Elasticity: Theory and Applications</series>
          <year>2001</year>
          <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib37">
        <label>37</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Steigmann</surname>
              <given-names>D.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Puncturing a thin elastic sheet</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Non-linear Mechanics</source>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <issue>2–3</issue>
          <year>2005</year>
          <fpage>255</fpage>
          <lpage>270</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib38">
        <label>38</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Steigmann</surname>
              <given-names>D.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thin-plate theory for large elastic deformations</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Non-Linear Mechanics</source>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>233</fpage>
          <lpage>240</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib39">
        <label>39</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Steigmann</surname>
              <given-names>D.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A concise derivation of membrane theory from three-dimensional nonlinear elasticity</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Elasticity</source>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>97</fpage>
          <lpage>101</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib40">
        <label>40</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Steigmann</surname>
              <given-names>D.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogden</surname>
              <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Elastic surface-substrate interactions</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering Sciences</source>
          <volume>455</volume>
          <issue>1982</issue>
          <year>1999</year>
          <fpage>437</fpage>
          <lpage>474</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib41">
        <label>41</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>W.H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hsu</surname>
              <given-names>K.H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Indentation of a circular membrane</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Applied Mechanics</source>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <year>1971</year>
          <fpage>227</fpage>
          <lpage>229</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <sec id="s0050">
      <title>Appendix</title>
      <p>In this appendix we shall provide a sketch of the derivation of the equilibrium equations given in <xref rid="eq0035 eq0040" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.7)</xref>, using the membrane-like shell approach. For full details including proofs and error estimates of the derivation here see Haughton <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> or Haughton and Ogden <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Where possible we shall use upper case letters to describe the undeformed configuration and lower case letters to describe the deformed configuration. In addition, Greek indices vary over (1,2), and the summation convention for repeated indices is used unless otherwise noted.</p>
      <p>We consider a thin shell with position vector:<disp-formula id="eq0100"><label>(A.1)</label><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><bold>X</bold> = <bold>Y</bold>(<italic>ξ</italic><sup>1</sup>, <italic>ξ</italic><sup>2</sup>) + <italic>ξ</italic><sup>3</sup><bold>N</bold>(<italic>ξ</italic><sup>1</sup>, <italic>ξ</italic><sup>2</sup>),</textual-form><mml:math id="M130" altimg="si0171.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">Y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">(<italic>ξ</italic><sup>1</sup>, <italic>ξ</italic><sup>2</sup>)</textual-form><mml:math id="M131" altimg="si0172.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> are curvilinear coordinates describing the midsurface of the shell, <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"> − <italic>H</italic> / 2 ≤ <italic>ξ</italic><sup>3</sup> ≤ <italic>H</italic> / 2</textual-form><mml:math id="M132" altimg="si0173.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is a thickness coordinate in the positive normal direction <bold>N</bold> and <italic>H</italic> is the thickness of the undeformed shell. We assume that the shell is thin enough such that if <italic>η</italic> is the minimum principal radii of curvature of the midsurface then,<disp-formula id="eq0105"><label>(A.2)</label><mml:math id="M133" altimg="si0176.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>max</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>⪡</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>H</italic><sub>max</sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M134" altimg="si0177.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>max</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the maximum thickness throughout the shell.</p>
      <p>We assume that the position vector <bold>x</bold> of the deformed membrane may be decomposed in the same way into a surface vector <bold>y</bold> and a thickness component in the deformed normal direction <bold>n</bold>, <disp-formula id="eq0110"><label>(A.3)</label><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><bold>x</bold> = <bold>y</bold>(<italic>ζ</italic><sup>1</sup>, <italic>ζ</italic><sup>2</sup>) + <italic>ζ</italic><sup>3</sup><bold>n</bold>(<italic>ζ</italic><sup>1</sup>, <italic>ζ</italic><sup>2</sup>),</textual-form><mml:math id="M135" altimg="si0181.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">n</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">(<italic>ζ</italic><sup>1</sup>, <italic>ζ</italic><sup>2</sup>)</textual-form><mml:math id="M136" altimg="si0182.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> are coordinates describing the deformed surface of the shell and <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"> − <italic>h</italic> / 2 ≤ <italic>ζ</italic><sup>3</sup> ≤ <italic>h</italic> / 2</textual-form><mml:math id="M137" altimg="si0183.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> expresses the distance through the thickness direction of the membrane. Haughton <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> show that, correct to within <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">𝒪(<italic>ε</italic>)</textual-form><mml:math id="M138" altimg="si0184.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">O</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, the surface <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ζ</italic><sup>3</sup> = 0</textual-form><mml:math id="M139" altimg="si0185.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> corresponds to the midsurface of the reference membrane <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ξ</italic><sup>3</sup> = 0</textual-form><mml:math id="M140" altimg="si0186.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, so that <bold>y</bold> may be used as the midsurface of the deformed membrane. Expanding <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ζ</italic><sup>3</sup></textual-form><mml:math id="M141" altimg="si0188.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> around <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ξ</italic><sup>3</sup></textual-form><mml:math id="M142" altimg="si0189.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, we may also find that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M143" altimg="si0190.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> to the same order. The tangent vectors to the undeformed and deformed surfaces may be written as<disp-formula id="eq0115"><label>(A.4)</label><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><bold>G</bold><sub><italic>α</italic></sub> = <bold>Y</bold><sub>, <italic>α</italic></sub>,  <bold>g</bold><sub><italic>α</italic></sub> = <bold>y</bold><sub>, <italic>α</italic></sub>,</textual-form><mml:math id="M144" altimg="si0191.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula>and we also define dual vectors:<disp-formula id="eq0120"><label>(A.5)</label><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><bold>G</bold><sup><italic>α</italic></sup> = <italic>G</italic><sup><italic>α</italic><italic>β</italic></sup><bold>G</bold><sub><italic>β</italic></sub>,  <bold>g</bold><sup><italic>α</italic></sup> = <italic>g</italic><sup><italic>α</italic><italic>β</italic></sup><bold>g</bold><sub><italic>β</italic></sub>,</textual-form><mml:math id="M145" altimg="si0192.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M146" altimg="si0193.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. The deformation gradient <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref> may be given by <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <disp-formula id="eq0125"><label>(A.6)</label><mml:math id="M147" altimg="si0194.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">F</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">X</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>⊗</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">N</mml:mi><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>from which we conclude that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M148" altimg="si0195.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> is a principal stretch. We may write the two-dimensional deformation gradient as,<disp-formula id="eq0130"><label>(A.7)</label><mml:math id="M149" altimg="si0196.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">Y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>⊗</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>which can then be directly computed. Following Haughton <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> we now define an orthonormal set of basis vectors <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">(<bold>a</bold><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>)</textual-form><mml:math id="M150" altimg="si0197.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> by<disp-formula id="eq0135"><label>(A.8)</label><mml:math id="M151" altimg="si0198.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:mi>no</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:mi>sum</mml:mi><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>which enables us to dispense with the distinction between covariant and contravariant tensors when we use <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><bold>a</bold><sub><italic>α</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M152" altimg="si0199.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> as a basis <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Referred to this basis, the general non-linear elasticity equilibrium equation <inline-formula><mml:math id="M153" altimg="si0200.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>div</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> becomes at zeroth order in <italic>ε</italic> <xref rid="bib9 bib7" ref-type="bibr">[9,7]</xref>, <disp-formula id="eq0140"><label>(A.9a)</label><mml:math id="M154" altimg="si0202.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="eq0145"><label>(A.9b)</label><mml:math id="M155" altimg="si0203.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M156" altimg="si0204.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">(<italic>α</italic>, <italic>β</italic>)‐th</textual-form><mml:math id="M157" altimg="si0205.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mtext>‐</mml:mtext><mml:mi>th</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> element of the stress tensor <bold><italic>σ</italic></bold>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M158" altimg="si0207.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> is a hydrostatic pressure applied to the inner surface and due to the use of the orthonormal basis vectors we have the additional definition <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">()<sub>, <italic>μ</italic></sub> = |∂ <bold>y</bold> / ∂ <italic>ζ</italic><sup><italic>μ</italic></sup>|<sup> − 1</sup>∂ () / ∂ <italic>ξ</italic><sup><italic>μ</italic></sup></textual-form><mml:math id="M159" altimg="si0208.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">y</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. The third principal stress, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M160" altimg="si0209.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>33</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, is of order <italic>ε</italic> at most, and therefore does not appear in <xref rid="eq0165" ref-type="disp-formula">(A.13)</xref>. This is often called the membrane assumption, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M161" altimg="si0211.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>33</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
      <p>It was shown by Naghdi and Tang <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> that the equilibrium equations presented above may be shown to be equivalent to those derived by considering the two-dimensional surface theory, under certain assumptions on <inline-formula><mml:math id="M162" altimg="si0212.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M163" altimg="si0213.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ij</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. This may be verified by a direct calculation of the equilibrium equations using the membrane theory detailed by Steigmann and Ogden <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref> or Steigmann <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref> for instance. See Haughton <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> for more details on the comparison between the two theories.</p>
      <p>We now use the coordinate systems introduced in <xref rid="eq0005" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.1)</xref> and <xref rid="eq0010" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.2)</xref> to describe the undeformed and deformed configurations respectively. We may therefore associate the two curvilinear coordinate systems <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">(<italic>ξ</italic><sup><italic>α</italic></sup>), (<italic>ζ</italic><sup><italic>α</italic></sup>)</textual-form><mml:math id="M164" altimg="si0214.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> with the arclength and polar angle:<disp-formula id="eq0150"><label>(A.10)</label><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ξ</italic><sup>1</sup> = <italic>A</italic><italic>Θ</italic>,  <italic>ξ</italic><sup>2</sup> = <italic>S</italic>,  <italic>ζ</italic><sup>1</sup> = <italic>A</italic><italic>θ</italic>,  <italic>ζ</italic><sup>2</sup> = <italic>S</italic>,</textual-form><mml:math id="M165" altimg="si0215.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>Θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.5em"/><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>A</italic> is a representative length. The orthonormal basis then becomes<disp-formula id="eq0155"><label>(A.11)</label><mml:math id="M166" altimg="si0216.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∧</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>where a prime represents differentiation with respect to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M167" altimg="si0217.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula>. It may be seen that these vectors are unit vectors in the meridional, tangential and normal directions of the deformed surface. A similar orthonormal basis <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><bold>A</bold><sub><italic>α</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M168" altimg="si0218.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> may be described with respect for the undeformed configuration with upper case letters replacing all equivalent lower case ones. The deformation gradient <xref rid="eq0130" ref-type="disp-formula">(A.7)</xref> is then given by<disp-formula id="eq0160"><label>(A.12)</label><mml:math id="M169" altimg="si0219.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">F</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>⊗</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>⊗</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>⊗</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">N</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>⊗</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>⊗</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>⊗</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">N</mml:mi><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>which shows that the principal directions are the meridional, tangential and normal directions respectively. As the deformation gradient can be written in a diagonal form, the stress tensor must also be diagonal with respect to the same basis, and so the only non-zero terms of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M170" altimg="si0220.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> relative to this basis are <inline-formula><mml:math id="M171" altimg="si0221.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M172" altimg="si0222.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. Additionally, using this basis we may immediately see the principal stretches in the three directions as the coefficients in <xref rid="eq0160" ref-type="disp-formula">(A.12)</xref>. Using <xref rid="eq0155" ref-type="disp-formula">(A.11)</xref> in <xref rid="eq0140" ref-type="disp-formula">(A.9a)</xref>, along with some rearrangement and noting that <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">()<sub>, 2</sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M173" altimg="si0223.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> in <xref rid="eq0140" ref-type="disp-formula">(A.9a)</xref> becomes <inline-formula><mml:math id="M174" altimg="si0224.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:math></inline-formula>, we find the equilibrium equations:<disp-formula id="eq0165"><label>(A.13)</label><mml:math id="M175" altimg="si0225.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="eq0170"><label>(A.14)</label><mml:math id="M176" altimg="si0226.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∂</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="eq0175"><label>(A.15)</label><mml:math id="M177" altimg="si0227.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mtext>.</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>The first equation in <xref rid="eq0165" ref-type="disp-formula">(A.13)</xref> is immediately satisfied due to the restriction of axisymmetry in the deformed configuration. The remaining two equations are the governing equations for the deformation, and represent force balances in the tangential and normal directions respectively. In <xref rid="eq0165" ref-type="disp-formula">(A.13)</xref><sub>3</sub> the coefficients of the stresses are actually the principal curvatures in the deformed configuration:<disp-formula id="eq0180"><label>(A.16)</label><mml:math id="M178" altimg="si0228.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.0em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>κ</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub>, <italic>κ</italic><sub><italic>θ</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M179" altimg="si0229.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> are the principal curvatures in the circumferential and radial directions respectively. These curvatures may be found from the components of the embedded deformed curvature tensor <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><bold><italic>κ</italic></bold> = <italic>κ</italic><sub><italic>α</italic><italic>β</italic></sub><bold>G</bold><sup><italic>α</italic></sup> ⊗ <bold>G</bold><sup><italic>β</italic></sup></textual-form><mml:math id="M180" altimg="si0230.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">κ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>⊗</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> using the definition <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>κ</italic><sub><italic>α</italic><italic>β</italic></sub> = <bold>n</bold>·<bold>g</bold><sub><italic>α</italic>, <italic>β</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M181" altimg="si0231.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">n</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, and then referred to the appropriate basis by <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>κ</italic><sub><italic>θ</italic></sub> = <italic>κ</italic><sub>11</sub><italic>g</italic><sup>11</sup>, <italic>κ</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub> = <italic>κ</italic><sub>22</sub><italic>g</italic><sup>22</sup></textual-form><mml:math id="M182" altimg="si0232.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>22</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p>
      <p>When the undeformed surface is flat or spherical we have <inline-formula><mml:math id="M183" altimg="si0233.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and the radicals in Eq. <xref rid="eq0180" ref-type="disp-formula">(A.16)</xref> may be expressed neatly including the principal stretch <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub></textual-form><mml:math id="M184" altimg="si0234.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, but for a general surface this is not the case. We also note that the curvatures are always related by Codazzi's equation:<disp-formula id="eq0185"><label>(A.17)</label><mml:math id="M185" altimg="si0235.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>′</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>^</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:math></disp-formula>which enables us to integrate one of the equilibrium equations under certain conditions, see <xref rid="eq0045" ref-type="disp-formula">(2.8)</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>This work has been funded by an ERANET-PG grant for the vSEED project (BBSRC grant BBG02488X1). JRK additionally acknowledges the support of the Royal Society and the Wolfson Foundation.</p>
    </ack>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="f0005">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Deformed configuration after indentation of a flat membrane by a spherical indenter for, from top to bottom, <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub>0</sub> = 1.05, 1.1, 1.2, 1.4, 1.6, 2</textual-form><mml:math id="M186" altimg="si0001.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.05</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.4</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.6</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, with <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> = 1</textual-form><mml:math id="M187" altimg="si0002.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ρ</italic> = 0.2</textual-form><mml:math id="M188" altimg="si0003.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. The strain-energy function used is the Mooney–Rivlin with <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>α</italic> = 0.1</textual-form><mml:math id="M189" altimg="si0004.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0010">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>A variety of spheroidal indenter tips with <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>A</italic>(<italic>θ</italic>) = sin<italic>θ</italic>, <italic>B</italic>(<italic>θ</italic>) =  − <italic>γ</italic>cos<italic>θ</italic>, <italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> = 1, <italic>ρ</italic> = 0.2</textual-form><mml:math id="M190" altimg="si0005.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>sin</mml:mi><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>cos</mml:mi><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. From top to bottom, <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>γ</italic> = 0.005, 0.125, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 200</textual-form><mml:math id="M191" altimg="si0006.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.005</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.125</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.25</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>200</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0015">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Force–indentation curves for the indentation by a spherical indenter of a flat membrane modelled using the neo-Hookean, Mooney–Rivlin and Fung strain-energy functions with <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> = 1, <italic>ρ</italic> = 0.2</textual-form><mml:math id="M192" altimg="si0007.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0020">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Force–indentation curves for the indentation of a flat Mooney–Rivlin membrane by a spherical indenter of varying size, from bottom to top, <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ρ</italic> = 0.1, 0.2, …, 0.9</textual-form><mml:math id="M193" altimg="si0008.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.9</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr4"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0025">
      <label>Fig. 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Load–indentation curves for the indentation of an initially curved membrane with <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>R</italic>(<italic>S</italic>) = <italic>S</italic>, <italic>Z</italic>(<italic>S</italic>) =  − cos(<italic>π</italic><italic>S</italic> / 2) / 4</textual-form><mml:math id="M194" altimg="si0009.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>cos</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> by various spheroidal indenter tips, from top to bottom: <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>γ</italic> = 0.25, 0.5, 1, 2, 4, 8</textual-form><mml:math id="M195" altimg="si0010.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.25</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> = 1, <italic>ρ</italic> = 0.2</textual-form><mml:math id="M196" altimg="si0011.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr5"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0030">
      <label>Fig. 6</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Close-up of the force–indentation curve for a spherical indenter and a flat membrane with the Mooney–Rivlin strain-energy function with <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>α</italic> = 0.1</textual-form><mml:math id="M197" altimg="si0012.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> = 1</textual-form><mml:math id="M198" altimg="si0013.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ρ</italic> = 0.2</textual-form><mml:math id="M199" altimg="si0014.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. Curve is given by <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>F</italic> = 4.7292<italic>δ</italic><sup>3</sup></textual-form><mml:math id="M200" altimg="si0015.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4.7292</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr6"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0035">
      <label>Fig. 7</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Deformation of an initially spherical surface <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>R</italic>(<italic>S</italic>) = sin<italic>S</italic>, <italic>Z</italic>(<italic>S</italic>) =  − cos<italic>S</italic>, <italic>ρ</italic> = 0.4, <italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> = 1</textual-form><mml:math id="M201" altimg="si0016.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>sin</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>cos</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.4</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> with a spherical indenter and a Mooney–Rivlin strain-energy function with <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>α</italic> = 0.1</textual-form><mml:math id="M202" altimg="si0017.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. From top to bottom: <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub>0</sub> = 1.2, 1.4, 1.6, 2</textual-form><mml:math id="M203" altimg="si0018.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.4</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.6</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. Dashed line shows the undeformed shape of the membrane, dotted sections of the deformed surface are wrinkled.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr7"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0040">
      <label>Fig. 8</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Load–indentation curves for the indentation with a spherical indenter of a range of initially curved membranes with <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>R</italic>(<italic>S</italic>) = <italic>S</italic>,  <italic>Z</italic>(<italic>S</italic>) =  − <italic>ψ</italic>cos(<italic>π</italic><italic>S</italic> / 2)</textual-form><mml:math id="M204" altimg="si0019.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mi>cos</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, from top to bottom: <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ψ</italic> = 0.5, 0.25, 0.125, 0.1, 0.05, 0</textual-form><mml:math id="M205" altimg="si0020.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.25</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.125</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> = 1, <italic>ρ</italic> = 0.2</textual-form><mml:math id="M206" altimg="si0021.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr8"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0045">
      <label>Fig. 9</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Load–indentation curves for the indentation with a spherical indenter of an range of initially curved membranes with <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>R</italic>(<italic>S</italic>) = <italic>S</italic>,  <italic>Z</italic>(<italic>S</italic>) =  − <italic>ψ</italic>cos(<italic>π</italic><italic>S</italic> / 2)</textual-form><mml:math id="M207" altimg="si0022.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mi>Z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mi>cos</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, from top to bottom: <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>ψ</italic> = 0.5, 0.25, 0.125, 0.1, 0.05, 0</textual-form><mml:math id="M208" altimg="si0023.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>ψ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.25</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.125</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> = 1, <italic>ρ</italic> = 0.2</textual-form><mml:math id="M209" altimg="si0024.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, using the Fung strain-energy function.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr9"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0050">
      <label>Fig. 10</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Position of contact point <italic>S</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> as indentation depth changes for the indentation of a flat membrane with a spherical indenter, <inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>λ</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> = 1, <italic>ρ</italic> = 0.2</textual-form><mml:math id="M210" altimg="si0025.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>. The neo-Hookean (NH), Mooney-Rivlin (MR) and Fung strain-energy functions are shown.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr10"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>