<article xmlns="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Chromatogr A</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Chromatography. a</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9673</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1873-3778</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3223526</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21227439</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CHROMA351729</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chroma.2010.12.090</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Toroidal coil chromatography: The effect of scale-up and “g” field on stage efficiency</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sutherland</surname>
            <given-names>Ian</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>ian.sutherland@brunel.ac.uk</email>
          <xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hewitson</surname>
            <given-names>Peter</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>de Folter</surname>
            <given-names>Joost</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>Brunel Institute for Bioengineering, Brunel University, Kingston Lane, Uxbridge, Middlesex UB8 3PH, UK</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor0005"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. Tel.: +44 1895 266920; fax: +44 1895 274608. <email>ian.sutherland@brunel.ac.uk</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>09</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>09</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>1218</volume>
      <issue>36</issue>
      <fpage>6144</fpage>
      <lpage>6147</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2011 Elsevier B.V.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Elsevier B.V.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/authorsview.authors/supplementalterms1.0">certain conditions</ext-link>.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Selected test results have been taken from various publications and resolution and stage efficiency measured using an established model. All experiments used the same sample and, where possible, the same sample loading. The results show that stage mixing efficiencies have increased from 1.1% in 1998 to greater than 25% in the latest scaled-up version of a Toroidal coil chromatography (TCC) instrument working at 240 g.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Process scale</kwd>
        <kwd>Toroidal coil chromatography</kwd>
        <kwd>TCC</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec0005">
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Toroidal coil chromatography (TCC) is proving to be a very effective way of purifying proteins using aqueous two-phase systems (ATPS). As it is a hydrostatic counter-current chromatography (CCC) process with a defined number of stages, it lends itself to analysis using a counter-current distribution (CCD) based modelling system <xref rid="bib0005 bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[1,2]</xref>. The challenge in the future will be to extend the range of CCC instruments to work on the isolation and production of biologics or larger molecules. These are not very stable in organic solvents and require gentle phase systems with a low interfacial tension such as aqueous two-phase systems (ATPS). Ito and Ma <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref> demonstrated a separation of lysozyme and myoglobin in a toroidal coil centrifuge (TCC) as early as 1998, but the quantities were small and throughputs very low. Shinomiya et al. <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> later showed that higher resolution separations were feasible using the cross-axis coil planet centrifuge with similar tubing and flow rates as Ito, although he wound his tubing onto a 5 mm core rather than the 3 mm core used by Ito. Later in our own BBSRC funded study (BB/C506364/1) we were able to show that hydrodynamic CCC with wave mixing could give excellent retentions of stationary phase in the column, but when model separation studies were performed it was found that there was poor resolution <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. It was concluded that wave mixing was too gentle when working with these considerably more viscous solutions. The BBSRC study then went on to show that centrifugal partition chromatography (CPC), another form of liquid–liquid chromatography, which uses a series of chambers mounted circumferentially on a disk interconnected with input and outlet leads and cascade mixing between the phases, could successfully separate the proteins and could be scaled up to larger CPC centrifuges <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. However the study also showed that there was a large carry-over of the stationary phase (i.e., the process was not an equilibrium one). Also, the process was not completely sterile, as there were rotating seals and the interconnecting chambers were difficult to completely clean between runs. This carry-over was not found when toroidal coils were used instead of spirally wound coils on a multilayer coil planet centrifuge <xref rid="bib0035 bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[7,8]</xref>. This paper compares the stage efficiencies from 5 different papers using 5 different hydrostatic<xref rid="fn0005" ref-type="fn">1</xref> CCC columns – a centrifugal TCC column <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>; a cross-axis coil planet centrifuge <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, two multilayer coil planet centrifuge TCC columns <xref rid="bib0035 bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[7,8]</xref> and a centrifugal partition chromatography (CPC) column <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> – and specifically looks at the effects of increasing “g” field in the TCC columns.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0010">
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Modelling</title>
      <p>In all cases, chromatograms have been fitted using the theoretical model based on CCD theory <xref rid="bib0005 bib0010 bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[1,2,9]</xref>, with the equivalent number of mixing and settling transfers (as if the experiment were being performed using a series of liquid–liquid extraction steps in test tubes). Ideally, each mixing stage (or loop with a cascade mixing step or stage) should be 100% efficient, with complete mass transfer between each stage. In practice, the mobile phase often tracks round the path of least resistance and misses the large volumes of stationary phase present. In hydrostatic CCC, where there is cascade mixing like a series of waterfalls, there is an effect known as the “Coriolis Effect” <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref> which causes the mixing stream to curve in the direction of rotation when the heavy phase is mobile; this curve varies according to the strength of the “g” field. From the theoretical model <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, knowing the partition coefficients of the sample mixture, myoglobin and lysozyme (<italic>K</italic><sub>d</sub> = 0.6 and 1.9), and knowing the retention (<italic>S</italic><sub>f</sub>), it is possible to find the number of transfers (or mixing and settling steps) to achieve the given resolution (<italic>R</italic><sub>s</sub>). Efficiency is then obtained by dividing this number by the fixed number of loops/chambers or mixing and settling stages in the instrument being evaluated.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0015">
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Preparative scale toroidal coil bobbin</title>
      <p>A pair of preparative scale stainless steel toroidal coil columns (334 ml coil volume; 5 mm bore and 404 loops each column <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>) are installed in a commercial high performance Midi rotor (supplied by Dynamic Extractions, Slough, UK). These columns and rotor can therefore be operated at up to 240 g. The winding configuration is similar to that used by Shinomiya et al. <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> for his cross-axis rotor (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). As the stainless steel tubing was thin walled, the overall weight increase in each completed bobbin was only 6.7% when compared to a standard high performance Midi-bobbin (8.0 kg cf. 7.5 kg), so the mechanical robustness of the overall centrifuge system was not compromised by the use of stainless steel instead of fluoropolymer tubing.</p>
      <p>The use of stainless steel for the coils means back pressure generated by the hydrostatic coils can be accommodated. The maximum pressure recorded for the coils in operation was 21 bar (∼300 psi), a backpressure that is within the working pressure of the PTFE flying leads on the Midi instrument, which connect the bobbin to the peripheral equipment.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0020">
      <label>4</label>
      <title>Experimental</title>
      <sec id="sec0025">
        <label>4.1</label>
        <title>Sample preparation</title>
        <p>The sample was prepared by mixing 2.2 mg/ml each of lysozyme and myoglobin in equal quantities of upper and lower phase (exceptions 10 mg/ml for <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref> and 1 mg/ml for <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec0030">
        <label>4.2</label>
        <title>Sample loading</title>
        <p>Sample loading was from 1 to 1.5% of the coil volume (exceptions 5% for <xref rid="bib0015 bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[3,4]</xref> and 10% for <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec0035">
        <label>4.3</label>
        <title>Phase system</title>
        <p>The phase systems in all cases were 12.5% (w/w) PEG-1000:12.5% (w/w) K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub> ATPS with the heavy phase mobile.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0040">
      <label>5</label>
      <title>Results and discussion</title>
      <p>The results in <xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> show that the mixing efficiency in Ito's conventional toroidal coil centrifuge with its uniform acceleration field and small bore tubing is very low. Shinomiya in using a cross-axis coil planet centrifuge with a non-uniform acceleration field managed to increase the stage efficiency from 1.1 to 7.9% in the same bore tubing. In our PTFE 1.6 mm bore tubing wound on Midi bobbins, where there is also a fluctuating acceleration field, the efficiency is between 2.5 and 3.7% depending on the flow. As the bore increases to 5 mm, with the same rotor speed and increasing the flow from 1.25 to 10 ml/min in the same ratio as the cross section areas of the tubing (linear scale up), the efficiency of mixing increases from 2.5 to 7.4%. This occurred despite the sample loading increasing from 1 mg/ml at 1% coil volume sample loading to 2.2 mg/ml at 1.5% coil volume sample loading. When scaling up to larger bore tubing, the helix angle of the toroid inevitably increases. This means that even higher speeds will be needed to bend the flow stream (Coriolis) into the centre of the tubing and maximise mass transfer from the cascade mixing stream. When rotation speed is increased, there is a dramatic increase in stage efficiency from 7.4% at 800 rpm to 25% at 1400 rpm.</p>
      <p>This is can be seen clearly in <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> where the chromatograms for 800, 1000, 1200 and 1400 rpm have been superimposed upon one another. While the number of theoretical transfers (which is proportional to efficiency) rises significantly with speed (<xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>a), the resolution appears to plateau (<xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>b). This is because stationary phase retention (<italic>S</italic><sub>f</sub>) reduces from 38% at 1200 rpm to 30% at 1400 rpm (<xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>c).</p>
      <p>Ito and Ma <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, when observing “Coriolis flow” in toroidal coils made the following observation: “the best partition efficiency may be obtained when the Coriolis flow is nearly parallel to the toroidal segment where the partition process is taking place”. The huge increase in efficiency observed here is attributed to this effect where at 800 rpm the flow stream is most probably running down the tubing wall and as the speed increases from 800 to 1200 rpm lifts off the wall to become parallel with the wall and at 1400 rpm either starts to hit the opposite wall or as the stream has higher kinetic energy, starts to emulsify – hence the loss of stationary phase. In Ito's case he had a constant acceleration field. While the mean acceleration field at 1400 rpm is 240 g the actual acceleration field in the “J” type coil planet centrifuge fluctuates as shown in <xref rid="fig0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> between 720 and 1200 g in the active part of the column. This will result in a huge fluctuation of the cascade mixing stream in both speed and direction facilitating excellent mixing and mass transfer. While the optimum in this case appears to be 1200 rpm there will be a range of operation between 1200 and 1400 rpm where optimum conditions can be achieved.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0045">
      <label>6</label>
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>Step change increases in stage efficiency have been demonstrated in a preparative toroidal coil stainless steel column with stage efficiencies increasing from 7.4 to 25% and resolution (<italic>R</italic><sub>s</sub>) from 0.39 to 1.1 as rotational speed increases from 800 rpm (79 g) to 1400 rpm (241 g). These efficiencies are compared very favourably against other technology using the same model system.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bib0005">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sutherland</surname>
              <given-names>I.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>de Folter</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wood</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>J. Liq. Chromatogr. Relat. Technol.</source>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <year>2003</year>
          <fpage>1449</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0010">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>de Folter</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sutherland</surname>
              <given-names>I.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>J. Chromatogr. A</source>
          <volume>1216</volume>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>4218</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19070863</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0015">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ito</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>J. Liq. Chromatogr. Relat. Technol.</source>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <year>1998</year>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0020">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shinomiya</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kabasawa</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ito</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Prep. Biochem. Biotechnol.</source>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <year>1999</year>
          <fpage>139</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10231893</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0025">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guan</surname>
              <given-names>Y.H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smulders</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fisher</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sutherland</surname>
              <given-names>I.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>J. Chomatogr. A</source>
          <volume>1151</volume>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>115</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0030">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sutherland</surname>
              <given-names>I.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>J. Chomatogr. A</source>
          <volume>1190</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>57</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0035">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guan</surname>
              <given-names>Y.H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bourton</surname>
              <given-names>E.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hewitson</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sutherland</surname>
              <given-names>I.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fisher</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Sep. Purif. Technol.</source>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>79</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0040">
        <label>8</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">R. van den Heuvel, R. Siebers, P. Hewitson, Y.H. Guan, I.A. Sutherland, Scale up of protein separation using J-type toroidal coil counter-current chromatography, <italic>ibid</italic>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0045">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">J. de Folter model can be downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://theliquidphase.org/index.php%3Ftitle=Modeling">http://theliquidphase.org/index.php?title=Modeling</ext-link></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We are extremely grateful to the UK BBSRC for funding this study (Follow-on Grant No. BB/FOF/206) following on from the BBSRC protein purification study (DEMPRO-Grant No. BB/C506364/1). Thanks also to Dynamic Extractions Ltd, Tony Bunce and Remco van den Heuvel for their support in constructing the bobbin and to Rick Siebers and Hugh Guan for experimental testing of the scaled-up bobbins.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn0005">
        <label>1</label>
        <p>Where “hydrostatic” means that the stationary phase stays where it is when the flow stops, as opposed to “hydrodynamic” where the phases move to opposite ends of the column. Hydrostatic columns have cascade mixing and hydrodynamic columns have wave mixing.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="fig0005">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Schematic of toroidal coil bobbin used by Shinomiya et al. <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. The Brunel toroidal coil uses a similar configuration but wound on a commercial bobbin supplied by Dynamic Extractions with a 334 ml coil volume; 5 mm bore and 404 loops.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig0010">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Visualisation of the change in separation resolution with rotational speed changing from 800 rpm (76 g) to 1400 rpm (240 g) <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig0015">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Variation of (a) stage efficiency; (b) stationary phase volume retention (<italic>S</italic><sub>f</sub>) and (c) resolution (<italic>R</italic><sub>s</sub>) with rotational speed.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig0020">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Variation of TCC acceleration field (<italic>x</italic> unit gravity) with time at a constant rotational speed of 1400 rpm.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr4"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="tbl0005" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Selection of results comparing the new 5 mm bore TCC instrument with Ito's original TCC unit <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, Shinomiya's cross axis coil planet centrifuge <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, early feasibility studies at Brunel with 1.6 mm bore tubing <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, scale-up with the 5 mm bore tubing <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> and CPC <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>.</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Centrifuge</th>
            <th align="left">Speed (rpm)</th>
            <th align="left">Flow (ml/min)</th>
            <th align="left">Volume (ml)</th>
            <th align="left">Mixing stages</th>
            <th align="left">No. of transfers</th>
            <th align="left">Mixing efficiency (%)</th>
            <th align="left">Resolution (<italic>R</italic><sub>s</sub>)</th>
            <th align="left">Plates (<italic>N</italic><sub>1</sub>)</th>
            <th align="left">Plates (<italic>N</italic><sub>2</sub>)</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">TOC <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref></td>
            <td align="char">1200</td>
            <td align="char">0.2</td>
            <td align="char">20</td>
            <td align="char">1310</td>
            <td align="char">15</td>
            <td align="char">1.1</td>
            <td align="char">0.96</td>
            <td align="char">121</td>
            <td align="char">57</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">XCCC <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref></td>
            <td align="char">800</td>
            <td align="char">0.2</td>
            <td align="char">29</td>
            <td align="char">887</td>
            <td align="char">70</td>
            <td align="char">7.9</td>
            <td align="char">1.40</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">CCC <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref></td>
            <td align="char">800</td>
            <td align="char">0.62</td>
            <td align="char">51.7</td>
            <td align="char">909</td>
            <td align="char">28</td>
            <td align="char">3.1</td>
            <td align="char">0.94</td>
            <td align="char">111</td>
            <td align="char">39</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">CCC <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref></td>
            <td align="char">800</td>
            <td align="char">1.25</td>
            <td align="char">51.7</td>
            <td align="char">909</td>
            <td align="char">23</td>
            <td align="char">2.5</td>
            <td align="char">0.77</td>
            <td align="char">151</td>
            <td align="char">37</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">CCC <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref></td>
            <td align="char">800</td>
            <td align="char">0.62</td>
            <td align="char">107.1</td>
            <td align="char">1884</td>
            <td align="char">70</td>
            <td align="char">3.7</td>
            <td align="char">1.45</td>
            <td align="char">178</td>
            <td align="char">110</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">CCC <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref></td>
            <td align="char">800</td>
            <td align="char">10</td>
            <td align="char">333.6</td>
            <td align="char">404</td>
            <td align="char">30</td>
            <td align="char">7.4</td>
            <td align="char">0.39</td>
            <td align="char">340</td>
            <td align="char">57</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">CCC <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref></td>
            <td align="char">1000</td>
            <td align="char">10</td>
            <td align="char">333.6</td>
            <td align="char">404</td>
            <td align="char">55</td>
            <td align="char">13.6</td>
            <td align="char">0.70</td>
            <td align="char">400</td>
            <td align="char">108</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">CCC <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref></td>
            <td align="char">1200</td>
            <td align="char">10</td>
            <td align="char">333.6</td>
            <td align="char">404</td>
            <td align="char">91</td>
            <td align="char">22.5</td>
            <td align="char">1.05</td>
            <td align="char">324</td>
            <td align="char">145</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">CCC <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref></td>
            <td align="char">1400</td>
            <td align="char">10</td>
            <td align="char">333.6</td>
            <td align="char">404</td>
            <td align="char">101</td>
            <td align="char">25.0</td>
            <td align="char">1.10</td>
            <td align="char">380</td>
            <td align="char">200</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">CCC <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref></td>
            <td align="char">1400</td>
            <td align="char">10</td>
            <td align="char">672.1</td>
            <td align="char">814</td>
            <td align="char">226</td>
            <td align="char">27.8</td>
            <td align="char">1.68</td>
            <td align="char">665</td>
            <td align="char">381</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">CPC <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref></td>
            <td align="char">2000</td>
            <td align="char">10</td>
            <td align="char">429</td>
            <td align="char">1008</td>
            <td align="char">80</td>
            <td align="char">7.9</td>
            <td align="char">1.28</td>
            <td align="char">308</td>
            <td align="char">224</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>