<article xmlns="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Prev Vet Med</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Preventive Veterinary Medicine</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0167-5877</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1809-399X</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier Scientific Publishing</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2722901</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">19523702</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PREVET2596</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.prevetmed.2009.05.009</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The impact of habitat fragmentation on tsetse abundance on the plateau of eastern Zambia<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="N0x1c830d0N0x2ac03d0">☆</xref></sup></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Ducheyne</surname>
            <given-names>E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>educheyne@avia-gis.be</email>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
          <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Mweempwa</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
          <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>De Pus</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Vernieuwe</surname>
            <given-names>H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>De Deken</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hendrickx</surname>
            <given-names>G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Van den Bossche</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
          <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <addr-line><sup>a</sup>Avia-GIS, Risschotlei 33, 2980 Zoersel, Belgium</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <addr-line><sup>b</sup>Department of Veterinary and Livestock Development, Zambia</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <addr-line><sup>c</sup>Animal Health Department, Institute of Tropical Medicine, Antwerpen, Belgium</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff4">
        <addr-line><sup>d</sup>Department of Veterinary Tropical Diseases, Faculty of Veterinary Science, South Africa</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. Tel.: +32 3 458 29 79. <email>educheyne@avia-gis.be</email></corresp>
        <fn id="fn1">
          <label>1</label>
          <p>Both the authors have contributed equally to the work presented in this paper.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>01</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2009</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>91</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>11</fpage>
      <lpage>18</lpage>
      <history/>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2009 Elsevier B.V.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Elsevier B.V.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/authorsview.authors/supplementalterms1.0">certain conditions</ext-link>.</p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>Abstract</title>
        <p>Tsetse-transmitted human or livestock trypanosomiasis is one of the major constraints to rural development in sub-Saharan Africa. The epidemiology of the disease is determined largely by tsetse fly density. A major factor, contributing to tsetse population density is the availability of suitable habitat. In large parts of Africa, encroachment of people and their livestock resulted in a destruction and fragmentation of such suitable habitat. To determine the effect of habitat change on tsetse density a study was initiated in a tsetse-infested zone of eastern Zambia. The study area represents a gradient of habitat change, starting from a zone with high levels of habitat destruction and ending in an area where livestock and people are almost absent. To determine the distribution and density of the fly, tsetse surveys were conducted throughout the study area in the dry and in the rainy season. Landsat ETM+ imagery covering the study area were classified into four land cover classes (munga, miombo, agriculture and settlements) and two auxiliary spectral classes (clouds and shadow) using a Gaussian Maximum Likelihood Classifier. The classes were regrouped into natural vegetation and agricultural zone. The binary images were overlaid with hexagons to obtain the spatial spectrum of spatial pattern. Hexagonal coverage was selected because of its compact and regular form. To identify scale-specific spatial patterns and associated entomological phenomena, the size of the hexagonal coverage was varied (250 and 500 m). Per coverage, total class area, mean patch size, number of patches and patch size standard deviation were used as fragmentation indices. Based on the fragmentation index values, the study zone was classified using a Partitioning Around Mediods (PAM) method. The number of classes was determined using the Wilks’ lambda coefficient. To determine the impact of habitat fragmentation on tsetse abundance, the correlation between the fragmentation indices and the index of apparent density of the flies was determined and habitat changes most affecting tsetse abundance was identified. From this it followed that there is a clear relationship between habitat fragmentation and the abundance of tsetse flies. Heavily fragmented areas have lower numbers of tsetse flies, but when the fragmentation of natural vegetation decreases, the number of tsetse flies increases following a sigmoidal-like curve.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Tsetse</kwd>
        <kwd>GIS</kwd>
        <kwd>Fragmentation analysis</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Tsetse-transmitted trypanosomiasis is a major constraint to rural development in large parts of Africa (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Swallow, 1998</xref>).</p>
      <p>The tsetse flies occur in about 10 million km<sup>2</sup> of sub-Saharan Africa and the trypanosomes they transmit can cause severe illness in livestock and people. The prevalence of bovine trypanosomiasis, transmitted by <italic>Glossina morsitans morsitans</italic> (Diptera: Glossinidae) the only species present, is about 30% (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Simukoko et al., 2007</xref>). For their survival, tsetse flies are highly dependent on the presence of suitable habitat and hosts. The seasonal distribution of the flies is correlated with the distribution of its main host, cattle (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Van den Bossche and Staak, 1997</xref>). However, in large parts of tsetse-infested sub-Saharan Africa the progressive clearing of the natural vegetation for cultivation, the introduction of domestic animals and the almost complete disappearance of large game animals have had important repercussions for the distribution and density of tsetse flies. In Malawi, for example, the distribution of tsetse flies is almost restricted to protected areas, where the vegetation is undisturbed whereas the extensive clearing of natural vegetation outside the protected areas has led to the disappearance of the tsetse flies and the disease they transmit (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Van den Bossche et al., 2000</xref>). It can be anticipated that in the years to come and with continued population growth and the environmental change a similar decline in the distribution and density of the tsetse population and the disease prevalence will be observed elsewhere. This process of gradual reduction in challenge may in certain areas ultimately lead to autonomous, anthropogenic clearing of tsetse and thus the disappearance of the disease (<xref rid="bib1 bib10" ref-type="bibr">Bourn et al., 2000; Reid et al., 2000</xref>). Understanding this process may contribute to the development of focused trypanosomiasis control strategies that exploit this autonomous tsetse clearing.</p>
      <p>While the landscape structure has a strong potential to influence disease dynamics, the importance of landscape composition (number and type of patches) and configuration (spatial relationship among patches) is only beginning to be explored (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Ostfeld et al., 2005</xref>). The quantification of the spatial heterogeneity of a landscape, also referred to as landscape fragmentation, is necessary to elucidate the relationship between the landscape and the ecological processes (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Turner, 2005</xref>). A wide range of landscape fragmentation indices (or metrics) is now readily available to quantify the landscape composition and configuration for categorical data through dedicated software packages such as Fragstats (stand alone, <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.umass.edu/landeco/research/fragstats/fragstats.html" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.umass.edu/landeco/research/fragstats/fragstats.html</ext-link>) or Patch Analyst (GIS-integrated, <ext-link xlink:href="http://flash.lakeheadu.ca/~rrempel/patch/" ext-link-type="uri">http://flash.lakeheadu.ca/∼rrempel/patch/</ext-link>).</p>
      <p>Examples of landscape indices include the total area of a given land cover class, the number of patches of that land cover class, the shape of remaining land cover patches for composition, and the distance to the nearest patch of the same land cover class for landscape configuration. Often several indices are combined to completely quantify the entire landscape.</p>
      <p>Even though the relationship between species diversity or species abundance and fragmentation characteristics is acknowledged, this relationship is not necessarily linear, and thresholds or minimum sizes for these factors may exist (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Drinnan, 2005</xref>) below which species diversity or abundance declines more than linear. Determining these thresholds is important from a management/control perspective. To investigate the relationship between tsetse abundance and habitat fragmentation a study was initiated in the tsetse-infested livestock production area of the plateau of eastern Zambia where human population growth and agricultural expansion have brought about profound changes to the environment (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Van den Bossche, 2001</xref>). Those changes have resulted in a substantial reduction in and fragmentation of the natural tsetse habitat and in the abundance of wildlife host.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec>
        <label>2.1</label>
        <title>Study area</title>
        <p>The study was carried out in an area situated between 31°47′ and 31°55′E (31.788–31.916E) and between 13°55′ and 14°12′S (13.916–14.12S) in Katete District, Eastern Province, Zambia. It is a highly cultivated area with a cattle population of approximately 8–10 animals/km<sup>2</sup>.</p>
        <p>The vegetation in the study area can be classified into two main types.</p>
        <p>(i) Miombo, a one-storied open woodland with dominant genera <italic>Brachystegi</italic>a and <italic>Julbernardia</italic>, and which is found mainly on poorer soils on ridges or slopes and (ii) munga, a one- or two-storied woodland where the principal tree genera are <italic>Acacia</italic>, <italic>Terminalia</italic> and <italic>Combretum</italic>, which is associated with flat topography and which follows the streams and their smaller tributaries. Most villages are found in the miombo vegetation type. Tsetse flies are found in both vegetation types but their abundance in each of them varies seasonally (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Van den Bossche and De Deken, 2002</xref>). The annual climatic cycle in the study area comprises three seasons: the warm rainy season (from early November to late April), the cold dry season (from early May to late August) and the hot dry season (from early September to late October). The study area is a subsistence farming area with maize and cotton being the most important crops. It represents a gradient of habitat change, starting from a zone with high levels of vegetation destruction and fragmentation as a result of human settlements and clearing for agriculture in the south and ending in an area where livestock and people are almost absent and where natural vegetation is largely untouched in the north (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <label>2.2</label>
        <title>Tsetse distribution</title>
        <p>To obtain up to date information on the distribution and density of <italic>G. m. morsitans</italic>, two surveys were carried out. The first survey was conducted during the rainy season (February/March 2006) and the second at the end of the hot dry season (October/November 2006). Use was made of the fly-round method along transects as described by <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Potts (1930)</xref> and <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Ford et al. (1959)</xref>. According to this method a sample team of two men traversed a transect using a black screen (1.5 m × 1 m) baited with acetone released at approximately 200 mg/h (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Shereni, 1984</xref>). The screen hung from a bamboo pole and was kept hanging vertically by weighting with a second bamboo pole at the bottom.</p>
        <p>Each transect was about 6 km long and had about 30 sectors of roughly 200 m each. At the end of each sector was a stop. The fly-round team remained at each stop for 2 min and, using hand nets, captured tsetse alighting on the screen. All flies were killed immediately after capture. The fly-rounds started between 07:00 and 08:00 h or 15:00 and 16:00 h in the rainy and hot dry seasons, respectively. Records were kept of the number and sex of the tsetse captured at each stop along each transect.</p>
        <p>All fly-round stops were georeferenced with a GPS using latitude–longitude coordinates (datum = WGS84). The dry season survey aimed at covering the same area as the one carried out during the rainy season. The starting points of each transect were identical but the position of the remainder of each transect could deviate slightly from its position during the rainy season survey. Moreover, during the dry season the area surveyed was extended to a zone that was not covered during the rainy season.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <label>2.3</label>
        <title>Land cover classification</title>
        <p>Because of cloud contamination, only the dry season was available for selecting high quality satellite data. Due to the Scan Line Failure of the ETM+ sensor in May 2003, the most recent Landsat data was from 6 October 2002. Two consecutive Landsat scenes (Path/Rows = 170/069 and 170/070, respectively) were ordered through the GLOVIS portal from the United States Geological Survey (<ext-link xlink:href="http://glovis.usgs.gov/" ext-link-type="uri">http://glovis.usgs.gov</ext-link>).</p>
        <p>The two images were preprocessed separately prior to mosaicking to reduce any effects of differences in illumination and atmospheric absorption. The digital numbers were converted into near-surface reflectance taking into account atmospheric correction using a dark pixel subtraction method (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Chavez, 1988</xref>). Subsequently, they were co-registered to remove any geometric distortions using a second order polynomial followed by a nearest neighbour resampling method. Finally, the imagery was mosaicked using a grey level matching method (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Richards and Jia, 1999</xref>).</p>
        <p>During the tsetse surveys, four different land cover types were identified, i.e. munga, miombo, agriculture and villages. In total, 560 reference points were georeferenced, this number was determined using the rule of thumb by <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Jensen (1996)</xref> who states the number of training sites should be &gt;10<italic>n</italic>, distributed equally across the entire image. In the case, we need at least 10 × 7 = 70 training sites. For each point the landscape was described and pictures were taken. Using those ground truth data, training sites were delineated on the satellite imagery as input for a supervised classification. From these training sites, spectral signatures are derived for four land cover types and two additional classes (clouds, shadow). The satellite image was classified using a Gaussian Maximum Likelihood Classifier with equal prior probabilities for each spectral class. The accuracy assessment was performed using an independent validation set and was evaluated using a confusion matrix, the overall accuracy and the Kappa Index of Agreement, which represents the agreement between ground truth and prediction after removing the proportion of agreement that could be expected to occur by chance (Congalton, 2001). A Kappa Index of Agreement close to 1 indicates a high accuracy. All image processing was carried out in Idrisi Andes (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.clarklabs.org/" ext-link-type="uri">www.clarklabs.org</ext-link>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <label>2.4</label>
        <title>Fragmentation analysis</title>
        <p>The classified image was reduced to two classes: “natural vegetation” comprising the miombo and munga land cover types and “disturbed vegetation” comprising the agriculture and villages land cover types. The classified image was overlaid with a grid of regular hexagons (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">De Clercq et al., 2007</xref>). Hexagons are selected because of their compact and regular form. Since habitat fragmentation occurs at different scales and to allow for the tsetse fly's mobility, two hexagon side sizes taking into account daily displacement capacity of <italic>G. m. morsitans</italic> (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Hargrove, 2003</xref>) were used, i.e. 250 and 500 m. The landscape fragmentation was assessed using Patch Analyst in ArcView3.2 (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.esri.com/" ext-link-type="uri">www.esri.com</ext-link>) by calculating the following indices for each hexagon for the disturbed vegetation class: total class area, number of patches, mean patch size and patch size standard deviation. Based on these indices, the hexagons with similar fragmentation characteristics were grouped in classes using an unsupervised clustering method Partioning Around Mediods (PAM). In this method each point is initially randomly assigned to one of the clusters. During the subsequent iterative phase, the cost of the configuration is determined and the mediod is adjusted to the configuration that reduces the cost maximally. In essence, this is a hill-climbing search method. The iterative process finishes when no configuration with lower energy can be found. The cost is calculated as the distance from each point to the nearest mediod. The number of clusters in the dataset was determined by means of the Wilk's Lambda and the silhouette width in R Stats. Using the fragmentation indices for the mediod hexagon of each cluster, the clusters could be arranged according to fragmentation degree.</p>
        <p>To link the entomological data to the fragmentation classes the index of apparent density (IAD) of tsetse was calculated for each polygon as follows:<disp-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>IAD</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> = index of apparent density for polygon <italic>p</italic>, <italic>NbCatches</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> = number of flies captured in polygon <italic>p</italic>, <italic>NbStops</italic><sub><italic>p</italic></sub> = number of stops in polygon <italic>p</italic>.</p>
        <p>Subsequently the IAD for all fragmentation classes was derived as the mean of the IAD of each polygon belonging to the fragmentation class. In order to test whether there is a significant difference between the different classes, the odds ratio of presence (i.e. IAD &gt; 0) over absence (i.e. IAD = 0) was determined. In a next step, a general linear model with binomial distribution in R Stats was used to determine the difference between the categories.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <label>3.1</label>
        <title>Tsetse distribution</title>
        <p>The entire study area was covered using 238 transects (119 in the dry and 119 in the rainy season, respectively) consisting of 6645 stops. A total of 210 <italic>G. m. morsitans</italic> (140 male and 70 female flies) were captured during the dry season survey. During the rainy season survey, 182 flies (122 male and 60 female flies) were captured. The flies were captured at 304 stops located throughout the study area (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <label>3.2</label>
        <title>Vegetation classification</title>
        <p>Using the four vegetation types, the overall accuracy as tested with an independent validation set using the Gaussian Maximum Likelihood Classifier was 96%, while the Kappa Index of Agreement was 0.93. For all different vegetation types, except for miombo, a conditional Kappa Index of Agreement of more than 0.90 was obtained (agriculture = 0.9483, miombo = 0.7693, munga = 0.9580, villages = 0.9794, clouds = 1.0000, shadow = 0.9625). The lower conditional Kappa Index of Agreement for miombo was due to the misclassification of 17% of the miombo pixels as munga (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Since prior to the fragmentation analysis these two vegetation types were combined into a single ‘natural vegetation class’, the confusion between these two classes therefore did not affect the fragmentation analysis.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <label>3.3</label>
        <title>Fragmentation trends at different scales</title>
        <p>In both cases the best clustering (lowest Wilk's lambda) was obtained for five clusters. All fragmentation indices contributed to the identification of the different fragmentation classes. However, it was noted that a subset of two indices (number of patches and class area) was sufficient to discriminate the clusters both at the 250 and 500 m scale. <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> illustrates the mediods per fragmentation class for both the 250 and 500 m scale.</p>
        <p>At the 250 m scale (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, top), there is a strong north–south axis of highly fragmented habitat along the road between Chipopera and Budula Siliya. Fragmentation decreases further away from this road in both directions. To the west, fragmentation becomes minimal when approaching the Nyamadzi river, and to the east close to protected forest west of Fungulani. Fragmentation is also more pronounced in the southern than in the northern part of the study area, especially in the area around Chipopera. Northwest of the Nyamadzi river, close to the game management area (GMA), the habitat is still intact.</p>
        <p>The same phenomenon can be observed at the 500 m (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) scale but the fragmentation patterns observed at this scale seem more clustered. From <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> both the north/south (game management area vs. Chipopera/Katete) as well as the east–west gradient away from the road between Chipopera and Budula Siliya are observed. The protected forest north of Msoro appears as a non-fragmented zone as is the miombo/munga complex south of the GMA. Though the number of fragmentation classes is the same for both scales, the interpretation of the classes based on the mediods is slightly different (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). While at the 250 m scale the hexagons with the highest degree of fragmentation (class 5) contain a single large patch of agriculture, hexagons with several (but a small number) of large patches are also included in this category at the 500 m scale. On the other hand, the hexagons with a fragmentation class 4 degree of fragmentation at the 250 m scale are similar to those which were assigned to fragmentation class 3 at the 500 m scale. Both categories show a considerable area of disturbed landscape consisting of large number of small patches. Finally at the 500 m scale, the clusters differentiated within the ‘lightly fragmented’ fragmentation class whilst these two categories are collapsed into one category at the 250 m.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <label>3.4</label>
        <title>Influence of fragmentation on tsetse abundance</title>
        <p>Independent of the scale (250 and 500 m) the impact of fragmentation on tsetse abundance was similar (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). During the dry as well as the rainy season the majority of the tsetse flies were captured in a non-fragmented landscape. Increasing levels of fragmentation resulted in a gradual decline in the IAD of male and female <italic>G. m. morsitans</italic> until a level of fragmentation (fragmentation class 4) is reached where the IAD is constant but low.</p>
        <p>From <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> follows that based on the odds ratio fragmentation classes 1 (<italic>α</italic> = 0.99), 2 (<italic>α</italic> = 0.95) and 3 (<italic>α</italic> = 0.9) are significantly higher from the reference category (fragmentation class 5) (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <label>4</label>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec>
        <label>4.1</label>
        <title>Fragmentation quantification at different scales</title>
        <p>The landscape fragmentation in the study zone can be characterized using two landscape indices that are easy to measure, i.e. class area and number of patches or by any other subset of landscape indices. This is due to the correlation between the estimated parameters.</p>
        <p>At both scales the fragmentation trends are similar but they appear more clustered at 500 m due to the generalization of the landscape pattern within the hexagons. At the 250 m scale the trends are less obvious but the hexagons have a more homogeneous landscape within. This is simply caused by the smaller surface of the smaller hexagons.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <label>4.2</label>
        <title>Entomological repercussions</title>
        <p>The outcome of this study shows that in the study area the destruction and fragmentation of the natural habitat of tsetse flies has significant repercussions for the density of those flies. Extensive clearing, mainly for cotton production in the southern part of the study area has resulted in the disappearance of large parts of the tsetse habitat and in a significant reduction in the apparent density of tsetse compared to the areas closer to the Luangwa escarpment where human density is much lower and the natural vegetation largely undisturbed. This reduction in the IAD of tsetse in the southern part can also be observed over time. Between 1990 and 1993, a longitudinal study monitoring the apparent density of the tsetse population in the southern part around Chipopera (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>), which is currently characterized by fragmentation classes 1 and 2, using identical sampling methods revealed an average monthly IAD of 0.64 flies during the rainy season (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Van den Bossche and De Deken, 2002</xref>). This is substantially higher than the average IAD of 0.01 and 0.02 flies observed during the rainy season survey in the fragmentation classes 1 and 2 and at a scale of 250 m, respectively. Hence, over a period of about 15 years anthropogenic changes have resulted in the almost disappearance of tsetse from this area.</p>
        <p>The results from this study suggest that the effect of habitat fragmentation on the apparent density of male and female tsetse flies is a gradual process with the IAD of tsetse increasing with decreasing levels of fragmentation. The results also show that this effect seems to be more pronounced in male flies. This difference between male and female flies is rather a result of a sampling bias inherent to the fly-round method that is less attractive to female compared to male <italic>G. m. morsitans</italic> (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Vale and Phelps, 1978</xref>). The observed variations in the IAD occur between habitats with high levels of fragmentation or areas where tsetse are most likely to disappear autonomously and habitats with low levels of fragmentation or areas where the tsetse population is thriving and where control interventions are required to reduce its density.</p>
        <p>Although suitable tsetse habitat is still present in all fragmentation classes it is expected that its degree of fragmentation affects the movements of tsetse flies in their quest for food. Since most of the wild hosts have disappeared from most of the study area, tsetse flies have become highly dependent on cattle for their survival (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Van den Bossche and Staak, 1997</xref>). The cattle availability is highest in the highly fragmented landscape but distribution of cattle varies seasonally. Therefore tsetse are highly dependent on seasonal changes in their distribution to find their host (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Van den Bossche and De Deken, 2002</xref>). All factors (especially habitat fragmentation) hindering those seasonal movements of the flies will thus have direct repercussions on the flies’ feeding success and their survival. The effect of those changes in apparent fly density on disease transmission requires further investigation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <label>4.3</label>
        <title>Conclusions</title>
        <p>The approach presented in this paper may form the basis for rationalizing area-wide tsetse fly control activities by identifying areas where tsetse flies are likely to disappear as a result of autonomous clearing and where control may not be required and identifying areas where tsetse flies are likely to persist and where control is thus more appropriate.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Conflict of interest statement</title>
      <p>None of the authors (Els Ducheyne, Cornelius Mweempwa, Claudia De Pus, Hilde Vernieuwe, Redginald De Deken, Guy Hendrickx, Peter Van den Bossche) has a financial or personal relationship with other people or organisations that could inappropriately influence or bias the paper entitled “The impact of habitat fragmentation on tsetse abundance on the plateau of eastern Zambia”.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>This work was funded by the Wellcome Trust (Grant 075824/B/04/Z). Ir. Eva De Clercq is gratefully acknowledged for her valuable input to the fragmentation analysis.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="N0x1c830d0N0x2ac03d0">
        <label>☆</label>
        <p>This paper is part of a special issue entitled “GisVet 2007”, Guest Edited by Annette Kjær Ersbøll.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bourn</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reid</surname>
              <given-names>R.S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rogers</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Snow</surname>
              <given-names>W.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wint</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Environmental Change and the Autonomous Control of Tsetse and Trypanosomosis in Sub-Saharan Africa</article-title>
          <year>2000</year>
          <publisher-name>AHP/ERGO</publisher-name>
          <comment>248 pp.</comment>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chavez</surname>
              <given-names>P.S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An improved dark-object subtraction technique for atmoshperic scattering correction of multispectral data</article-title>
          <source>Remote Sensing of Environment</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>459</fpage>
          <lpage>479</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>De Clercq</surname>
              <given-names>E.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Wulf</surname>
              <given-names>R.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Herzele</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Relating spatial pattern of forest cover to accessibility</article-title>
          <source>Landscape and Urban Planning</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>14</fpage>
          <lpage>22</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Drinnan</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The search for fragmentation thresholds in southern Sydney suburb</article-title>
          <source>Biological Conservation</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>124</volume>
          <fpage>339</fpage>
          <lpage>349</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ford</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Glasgow</surname>
              <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johns</surname>
              <given-names>D.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Welch</surname>
              <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transect flyrounds in the field studies of Glossina</article-title>
          <source>Bulletin of Entomological Research</source>
          <year>1959</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <fpage>275</fpage>
          <lpage>285</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hargrove</surname>
              <given-names>J.W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Optimized simulation of the control of tsetse flies Glossina pallidipes and G. m. morsitans (Diptera: Glossinidae) using odour-baited targets in Zimbabwe</article-title>
          <source>Bulletin of Entomological Research</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>19</fpage>
          <lpage>29</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12593679</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jensen</surname>
              <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Introductory Digital Image Processing: A Remote Sensing Perspective</article-title>
          <edition>2nd ed.</edition>
          <year>1996</year>
          <publisher-name>Prentice-Hall Inc.</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Engelwood Cliffs, New Jersey</publisher-loc>
          <comment>318 p.</comment>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ostfeld</surname>
              <given-names>R.S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Glass</surname>
              <given-names>G.E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kessing</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spatial epidemiology: an emerging (or re-emerging) discipline</article-title>
          <source>Trends in Ecology and Evolution</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>328</fpage>
          <lpage>336</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16701389</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Potts</surname>
              <given-names>W.H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A contribution to the study of numbers of tsetse-fly (Glossina morsitans Westw.) by quantitative methods</article-title>
          <source>South African Journal of Science</source>
          <year>1930</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>491</fpage>
          <lpage>497</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Reid</surname>
              <given-names>R.S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kruska</surname>
              <given-names>R.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deichmann</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thornton</surname>
              <given-names>P.K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leak</surname>
              <given-names>S.G.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Human population growth and extinction of the tsetse fly</article-title>
          <source>Agriculture, Ecosystems and Environment</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>77</volume>
          <fpage>227</fpage>
          <lpage>236</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Richards</surname>
              <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jia</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Remote Sensing Digital Image Analysis: An Introduction</article-title>
          <edition>3rd ed.</edition>
          <year>1999</year>
          <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>
          <comment>363 p.</comment>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shereni</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The use of cloth screens and acetone vapour as alternatives to a bait-ox for sampling populations of tsetse flies (Diptera: Glossinidae)</article-title>
          <source>Transactions of the Zimbabwe Scientific Association</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <fpage>22</fpage>
          <lpage>27</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Simukoko</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marcotty</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Phiri</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Geysen</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vercruysse</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van den Bossche</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The comparative role of cattle, goats and pigs in the epidemiology of livestock trypanosomiasis on the plateau of eastern Zambia</article-title>
          <source>Veterinary Parasitology</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>147</volume>
          <fpage>231</fpage>
          <lpage>238</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17493757</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <citation citation-type="other">Swallow, B.M., 1998. Impacts of African Animal Trypanosomosis on Migration, Livestock and Crop Production. Nairobi, ILRI, pp. 1–19.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Turner</surname>
              <given-names>M.G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Landscape ecology: what is the state of the science?</article-title>
          <source>Annual Review of Ecology, Evolution, and Systematics</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>319</fpage>
          <lpage>344</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vale</surname>
              <given-names>G.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Phelps</surname>
              <given-names>R.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sampling problems with tsetse flies</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Applied Ecology</source>
          <year>1978</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>715</fpage>
          <lpage>726</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Van den Bossche</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Some general aspects of the distribution and epidemiology of bovine trypanosomosis in southern Africa</article-title>
          <source>International Journal for Parasitology</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>592</fpage>
          <lpage>598</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11334947</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Van den Bossche</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>De Deken</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Seasonal variations in the distribution and abundance of the tsetse fly, Glossina morsitans morsitans in eastern Zambia</article-title>
          <source>Medical and Veterinary Entomology</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>170</fpage>
          <lpage>176</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12109711</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Van den Bossche</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Staak</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The importance of cattle as a food source for Glossina morsitans morsitans Westwood (Diptera: Glossinidae) in Katete District, Eastern Province, Zambia</article-title>
          <source>Acta Tropica</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>105</fpage>
          <lpage>109</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9164604</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Van den Bossche</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shumba</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Makhambera</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The distribution and epidemiology of bovine trypanosomosis in Malawi</article-title>
          <source>Veterinary Parasitology</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>163</fpage>
          <lpage>176</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10714455</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-wrap>
    <fig id="fig1">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(A) Map of study area, location of fly-round transects and tsetse fly captures during the dry and wet season survey. (B) Map of index of apparent density, interpolated using kriging.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig2">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Representation of the degree of fragmentation of natural habitat in each of the fragmentation classes for hexagon side sizes of 250 m (left) or 500 m (right).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig3">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Mediods for each of the fragmentation classes for hexagon side sizes of 250 m (top) or 500 m (bottom).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig4">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Number of patches (—) and class area (– – –) of disturbed vegetation in each of the habitat fragmentation classes for hexagon side sizes of 250 m (■) or 500 m (○). To allow for comparison between the two scales the number of patches at 500 m was divided by 4.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr4"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig5">
      <label>Fig. 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Index of apparent density of male and female tsetse (●), index of apparent density of males (○) and index of apparent density of females (▾) for each of the fragmentation classes and for hexagon side sizes of 250 and 500 m in dry season (A and B) and wet season (C and D).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr5"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Error matrix of classification: true land cover (columns) versus predicted land covers (rows). ErrorO: error of omission, the number of pixels that should have been added to the class but where omitted; ErrorC: error of commission, the number of pixels that were committed in the class but should have been added to another class.</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th/>
            <th colspan="8" align="left">Truth<hr/></th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th/>
            <th align="left">Agriculture</th>
            <th align="left">Miombo</th>
            <th align="left">Munga</th>
            <th align="left">Villages</th>
            <th align="left">Clouds</th>
            <th align="left">Shadow</th>
            <th align="left">Total</th>
            <th align="left">ErrorC</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="9" align="left">Predicted</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"> Agriculture</td>
            <td align="char">637</td>
            <td align="char">22</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td align="char">4</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td align="char">1</td>
            <td align="char">664</td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>0.041</bold>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"> Miombo</td>
            <td align="char">26</td>
            <td align="char">646</td>
            <td align="char">65</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td align="char">3</td>
            <td align="char">740</td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>0.127</bold>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"> Munga</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td align="char">140</td>
            <td align="char">3346</td>
            <td align="char">1</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td align="char">20</td>
            <td align="char">3507</td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>0.046</bold>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"> Villages</td>
            <td align="char">5</td>
            <td align="char">1</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td align="char">248</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td align="char">254</td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>0.024</bold>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"> Clouds</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td align="char">3</td>
            <td align="char">1</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td align="char">606</td>
            <td align="char">1</td>
            <td align="char">611</td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>0.008</bold>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"> Shadow</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td align="char">725</td>
            <td align="char">725</td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>0.000</bold>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"> Total</td>
            <td align="char">668</td>
            <td align="char">812</td>
            <td align="char">3412</td>
            <td align="char">253</td>
            <td align="char">606</td>
            <td align="char">750</td>
            <td align="char">6501</td>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="9" align="left">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"> ErrorO</td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>0.046</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>0.204</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>0.019</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>0.020</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>0.000</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>0.033</bold>
            </td>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>0.045</bold>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2">
      <label>Table 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Odds ratio of presence over absence for the different fragmentation classes.</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Fragm. class</th>
            <th align="left">Absence</th>
            <th align="left">Presence</th>
            <th align="left">Odds ratio</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="char">1</td>
            <td align="char">1962</td>
            <td align="char">137</td>
            <td align="char">0.07</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="char">2</td>
            <td align="char">1397</td>
            <td align="char">75</td>
            <td align="char">0.05</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="char">3</td>
            <td align="char">1466</td>
            <td align="char">52</td>
            <td align="char">0.04</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="char">4</td>
            <td align="char">698</td>
            <td align="char">12</td>
            <td align="char">0.02</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="char">5</td>
            <td align="char">240</td>
            <td align="char">3</td>
            <td align="char">0.01</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3">
      <label>Table 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Statistical analysis of odds ratio using a general linear model with a binomial distribution.</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th/>
            <th align="left">Estimate</th>
            <th align="left">S.D.</th>
            <th align="left">Error</th>
            <th align="left"><italic>z</italic>-Value</th>
            <th align="left">Pr(&gt;|<italic>z</italic>|)</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Frag 4</td>
            <td align="char">0.3187</td>
            <td align="char">0.6492</td>
            <td align="char">0.491</td>
            <td align="char">0.62349</td>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Frag 3</td>
            <td align="char">1.043</td>
            <td align="char">0.5972</td>
            <td align="char">1.746</td>
            <td align="char">0.08075</td>
            <td align="left">
              <xref rid="tbl3fn1" ref-type="table-fn">•</xref>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Frag 2</td>
            <td align="char">1.4574</td>
            <td align="char">0.5923</td>
            <td align="char">2.461</td>
            <td align="char">0.01387</td>
            <td align="left">
              <xref rid="tbl3fn2" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Frag 1</td>
            <td align="char">1.7203</td>
            <td align="char">0.587</td>
            <td align="char">2.931</td>
            <td align="char">0.00338</td>
            <td align="left">
              <xref rid="tbl3fn3" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn>
          <p>Fragmentation class 5 (the class which is most fragmented) is the baseline category to which the other classes are compared.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn id="tbl3fn1">
          <label>•</label>
          <p><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.1.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn id="tbl3fn2">
          <label>*</label>
          <p><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn id="tbl3fn3">
          <label>**</label>
          <p><italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.01.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-wrap>
</article>