<article xmlns="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Neuropsychologia</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Neuropsychologia</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0028-3932</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Pergamon Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2430985</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18387640</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">NSY2838</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2008.01.028</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Keeping the goal in mind: Prefrontal contributions to spatial navigation</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Spiers</surname>
            <given-names>Hugo J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>h.spiers@ucl.ac.uk</email>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>
        <addr-line>Institute of Behavioural Neuroscience, Department of Psychology, University College London, 26 Bedford Way, London WC1H 0AP, United Kingdom</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Tel.: +44 7670 7553. <email>h.spiers@ucl.ac.uk</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>46</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <fpage>2106</fpage>
      <lpage>2108</lpage>
      <history/>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2008 Elsevier Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/authorsview.authors/supplementalterms1.0">certain conditions</ext-link>.</p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Wayfinding</kwd>
        <kwd>Spatial memory</kwd>
        <kwd>Inhibition</kwd>
        <kwd>Planning</kwd>
        <kwd>Orbitofrontal</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>On his voyage home, Odysseus is nearly seduced to his death by the singing of the sirens. Odysseus's crew, their ears plugged with wax, thankfully do not hear his desperate pleas to change course. While such trials are not a feature of our daily travels, a variety of distractions can send us off course. In this issue, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Ciaramelli (2008)</xref> reports a patient who repeatedly suffers from this affliction, being lured away to unintended locations. The study provides new insights into the neural basis of spatial navigation.</p>
    <p>Our capacity for navigation is thought to rely on a distributed network of brain regions, which include the hippocampus, parahippocampus, retrosplenial cortex, parietal cortex, and caudate nucleus (see e.g. <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Aguirre &amp; D’Esposito, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Spiers &amp; Maguire, 2007a</xref>). Each region is thought to serve a different function of our navigation machinery, such as representing a map of large-scale space, converting the map to egocentric space, or representing our current viewpoint. However, the neural substrate of one particular function remains a mystery. How does the brain represent spatial goal locations or guide navigation to them? Several lines of evidence suggest this may be the preserve of the prefrontal cortex.</p>
    <p>The prefrontal cortex has long been associated with behavioural flexibility, working memory and planning; functions important for achieving goals (<xref rid="bib6 bib14 bib18" ref-type="bibr">Fuster, 1989; Luria, 1969; Passingham, 1993</xref>). It also integrates highly processed information important for guiding goal-directed behaviour (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Pandya &amp; Barnes, 1987</xref>). Several functional neuroimaging studies have revealed increased activity in prefrontal areas during spatial navigation tasks (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Gron, Wunderlich, Spitzer, Tomczak, &amp; Riepe, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Hartley, Maguire, Spiers, &amp; Burgess, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Maguire et al., 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Yoshida &amp; Ishii, 2006</xref>), one directly linking prefrontal activity to goal processing (<xref rid="bib20 bib22" ref-type="bibr">Spiers &amp; Maguire, 2006, 2007b</xref>). In rodents, medial and orbital prefrontal lesions have been found to impair certain aspects of navigation (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Lacroix, White, &amp; Feldon, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Vafaei &amp; Rashidy-Pour, 2004</xref>), and recently cells in these regions have been found to code spatial information about goals (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Feierstein, Quirk, Uchida, Sosulski, &amp; Mainen, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Hok, Save, Lenck-Santini, &amp; Poucet, 2005</xref>). However, it remains uncertain whether the human prefrontal cortex is <italic>necessary</italic> for navigation.</p>
    <p>In a recent article in Neuropsychologia new evidence has emerged suggesting that the ventromedial prefrontal cortex (vmPFC) is required for navigation (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Ciaramelli, 2008</xref>). <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Ciaramelli (2008)</xref> tested a patient with bilateral damage to the ventromedial prefrontal and rostral anterior cingulate cortices whose central complaint, following recovery, was of way-finding difficulties. Despite good topographical knowledge of his hometown he performed very poorly, compared to healthy controls, when asked to describe a set of routes between locations in the town. However, his performance improved substantially when he was given the name of his destination or a cue to rehearse the destination at regular intervals. No such improvement occurred when a visual stimulus was presented at similar intervals. Thus, it appears the vmPFC is necessary for navigation and its role may be to maintain the goal destination in working memory (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Ciaramelli, 2008</xref>). That the problem lies with working memory is further supported by the patient's generalised deficits on standardized tasks requiring working memory.</p>
    <p>However, deficits elicited by laboratory tasks do not always predict deficits in the ‘real world’ (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Habib &amp; Sirigu, 1987</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Kapur &amp; Pearson, 1983</xref>; <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Maguire, Burke, Phillips, &amp; Staunton, 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Spiers, Burgess, Hartley, Vargha-Khadem, &amp; O’Keefe, 2001</xref>). Indeed, a cue to rehearse the destination might not be as beneficial during navigation of a complex and bustling town. Appropriately, the patient's ability to actively navigate in the town was assessed under similar cue conditions to the laboratory task, with a strikingly similar pattern of results.</p>
    <p>Further insight into this patient's problem was generated by an analysis of the errors made in relation to several factors, including familiarity, route length, number of turns, etc. (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Ciaramelli, 2008</xref>). Of these factors, only familiarity was found to be associated with the number of errors. While successful routes were rated more familiar, surprisingly, the reverse was true of highly familiar locations on the route. Intriguingly, two-thirds of error trials involved the route ending at one of a number of personally familiar locations, each associated with the patient's previous work or hobbies. According to <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Ciaramelli (2008)</xref> these locations, being highly salient, acted as “attractor” locations, luring the patient away from his true goal. Thus, the vmPFC may be necessary not only to maintain the goal in memory, but also to suppress irrelevant information.</p>
    <p>These findings agree well with those of a recent neuroimaging study exploring the brain activity of London taxi drivers as they navigated a highly accurate virtual simulation of London (UK) (<xref rid="bib20 bib22" ref-type="bibr">Spiers &amp; Maguire, 2006, 2007b</xref>). In this study, the relationship between the subject's thoughts during navigation and their brain activity was examined using a retrospective verbal report protocol. Immediately post-scan, subjects watched a video replay of their performance and reported what they had been thinking while they were doing the task in the scanner. Of the wide variety of thoughts reported, the most frequent concerned thinking about the goal and the route to it (see <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Spiers &amp; Maguire, in press</xref>, for full details). These were associated with increased activity in anterior BA10 and in a medial prefrontal region overlapping with the dorsal extent of the lesion of the patient described by <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Ciaramelli (2008)</xref>. Given the latest findings, it could be argued the medial region is involved in maintaining goal representation while B10 may be important for manipulating information for planning (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Koechlin, Basso, Pietrini, Panzer, &amp; Grafman, 1999</xref>). Further evidence that cells in the medial prefrontal region might monitor spatial goals comes from the finding that activity in a region on the border of BA9 and BA32 correlated with proximity to the goal during navigation (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Spiers &amp; Maguire, 2007b</xref>). A more ventral medial prefrontal region was activated when subjects listened to navigationally irrelevant comments of customers whilst navigating (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Spiers &amp; Maguire, 2006</xref>). <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Ciaramelli (2008)</xref> suggests this may have been related to the mental rehearsal or ‘energizing’ of the actual goals. An alternative, related, interpretation is that the region is activated by the requirement to suppress processing of the new information in posterior cortical regions.</p>
    <p><xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Ciaramelli (2008)</xref> argues that the patient's deficit may arise from three related difficulties. These are: (a) an inability to actively maintain the goal in working memory, (b) a reversal-learning problem, and (c) a loss of the grammar that prescribes the transitions between attractor states in cortical networks. The last problem would make it difficult for the patient to avoid personally familiar locations, as these would be represented by strong attractors. A view favoured here, in line with other authors (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Burgess, Veitch, Costello, &amp; Shallice, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Shallice &amp; Burgess, 1991</xref>), is that the deficit can more readily be summarised as a failure to maintain the <italic>intention</italic> to reach the destination in working memory and a reduced suppression of previously learned information (in this case routes). A similar lack of suppression may underlie the reversal-learning deficit seen in such patients (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Fellows &amp; Farah, 2003</xref>), rather than vice versa.</p>
    <p>Most new research generates more questions than answers, as is the case here. Along with replicating the findings in other similar patients, a number of questions remain to be answered. Can the patient learn routes in an unfamiliar environment? At what point in the route is the intention lost? Given that medial prefrontal activity is correlated with goal proximity (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Spiers &amp; Maguire, 2007b</xref>), might the patient be unable to make use of novel shortcuts or reach the goal after a detour? Which region calculates proximity or directional information to goals? Though there is much still to be explored, the results from <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Ciaramelli (2008)</xref> add to our understanding of the neural processes supporting navigation. Given this new insight, when your mind next drifts and you arrive at a familiar but unintended destination, you will know which part of your neuroanatomy to blame.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgement</title>
      <p>The author is funded by a Wellcome Trust advanced training fellowship in basic biomedical science.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <label>Aguirre and D’Esposito, 1999</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aguirre</surname>
              <given-names>G.K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D’Esposito</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Topographical disorientation: A synthesis and taxonomy</article-title>
          <source>Brain</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>122</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>1613</fpage>
          <lpage>1628</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10468502</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <label>Burgess et al., 2000</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Burgess</surname>
              <given-names>P.W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Veitch</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costello</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shallice</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The cognitive and neuroanatomical correlates of multitasking</article-title>
          <source>Neuropsychologia</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>848</fpage>
          <lpage>863</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10689059</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <label>Ciaramelli, 2008</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ciaramelli</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The role of ventromedial prefrontal cortex in navigation: A case of impaired wayfinding and rehabilitation</article-title>
          <source>Neuropsychologia</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>2099</fpage>
          <lpage>2105</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18201735</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <label>Feierstein et al., 2006</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Feierstein</surname>
              <given-names>C.E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quirk</surname>
              <given-names>M.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Uchida</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sosulski</surname>
              <given-names>D.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mainen</surname>
              <given-names>Z.F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Representation of spatial goals in rat orbitofrontal cortex</article-title>
          <source>Neuron</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>495</fpage>
          <lpage>507</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16908414</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <label>Fellows and Farah, 2003</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fellows</surname>
              <given-names>L.K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farah</surname>
              <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ventromedial frontal cortex mediates affective shifting in humans: Evidence from a reversal learning paradigm</article-title>
          <source>Brain</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>126</volume>
          <fpage>1830</fpage>
          <lpage>1837</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12821528</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <label>Fuster, 1989</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fuster</surname>
              <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The prefrontal cortex</source>
          <volume>vol. 2</volume>
          <year>1989</year>
          <publisher-name>Raven</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <label>Gron et al., 2000</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gron</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wunderlich</surname>
              <given-names>A.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spitzer</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tomczak</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riepe</surname>
              <given-names>M.W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Brain activation during human navigation: Gender-different neural networks as substrate of performance</article-title>
          <source>Nature Neuroscience</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>404</fpage>
          <lpage>408</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <label>Habib and Sirigu, 1987</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Habib</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sirigu</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pure topographical disorientation: A definition and anatomical basis</article-title>
          <source>Cortex</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>73</fpage>
          <lpage>85</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3568707</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <label>Hartley et al., 2003</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hartley</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maguire</surname>
              <given-names>E.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spiers</surname>
              <given-names>H.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burgess</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The well-worn route and the path less travelled: Distinct neural bases of route following and wayfinding in humans</article-title>
          <source>Neuron</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>877</fpage>
          <lpage>888</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12628177</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <label>Hok et al., 2005</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hok</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Save</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lenck-Santini</surname>
              <given-names>P.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Poucet</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Coding for spatial goals in the prelimbic/infralimbic area of the rat frontal cortex</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Science USA</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>4602</fpage>
          <lpage>4607</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <label>Kapur and Pearson, 1983</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kapur</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pearson</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Memory symptoms and memory performance of neurological patients</article-title>
          <source>British Journal of Psychology</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>409</fpage>
          <lpage>415</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6616131</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <label>Koechlin et al., 1999</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koechlin</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Basso</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pietrini</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Panzer</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grafman</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The role of the anterior prefrontal cortex in human cognition</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>399</volume>
          <fpage>148</fpage>
          <lpage>151</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10335843</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <label>Lacroix et al., 2002</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lacroix</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>White</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feldon</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effect of excitotoxic lesions of rat medial prefrontal cortex on spatial memory</article-title>
          <source>Behavioural Brain Research</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>133</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>69</fpage>
          <lpage>81</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12048175</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <label>Luria, 1969</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Luria</surname>
              <given-names>A.R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Frontal lobe syndromes</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Vinken</surname>
              <given-names>P.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bruyn</surname>
              <given-names>G.W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Handbook of clinical neurology</source>
          <year>1969</year>
          <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <fpage>725</fpage>
          <lpage>757</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <label>Maguire et al., 1996</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maguire</surname>
              <given-names>E.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burke</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Phillips</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Staunton</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Topographical disorientation following unilateral temporal lobe lesions in humans</article-title>
          <source>Neuropsychologia</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>993</fpage>
          <lpage>1001</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8843066</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <label>Maguire et al., 1998</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maguire</surname>
              <given-names>E.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burgess</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Donnett</surname>
              <given-names>J.G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frackowiak</surname>
              <given-names>R.S.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frith</surname>
              <given-names>C.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O’Keefe</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Knowing where and getting there: A human navigation network</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>280</volume>
          <fpage>921</fpage>
          <lpage>924</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9572740</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <label>Pandya and Barnes, 1987</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pandya</surname>
              <given-names>D.N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barnes</surname>
              <given-names>C.L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Architecture and connections of the frontal lobe</article-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Perecman</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The frontal lobes revisited</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <publisher-name>IRBN</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <fpage>41</fpage>
          <lpage>72</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <label>Passingham, 1993</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Passingham</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The frontal lobes and voluntary action</article-title>
          <year>1993</year>
          <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <label>Shallice and Burgess, 1991</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shallice</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burgess</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Deficits of strategy application following frontal lobe damage in man</article-title>
          <source>Brain</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>114</volume>
          <fpage>727</fpage>
          <lpage>741</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2043945</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <label>Spiers and Maguire, 2006</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Spiers</surname>
              <given-names>H.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maguire</surname>
              <given-names>E.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Thoughts, behaviour, and brain dynamics during navigation in the real world</article-title>
          <source>Neuroimage</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>1826</fpage>
          <lpage>1840</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16584892</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <label>Spiers and Maguire, 2007a</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Spiers</surname>
              <given-names>H.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maguire</surname>
              <given-names>E.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The neuroscience of remote spatial memory: A tale of two cites</article-title>
          <source>Neuroscience</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>149</volume>
          <fpage>7</fpage>
          <lpage>27</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17850977</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib22">
        <label>Spiers and Maguire, 2007b</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Spiers</surname>
              <given-names>H.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maguire</surname>
              <given-names>E.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A navigational guidance system in the human brain</article-title>
          <source>Hippocampus</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>618</fpage>
          <lpage>626</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17492693</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <label>Spiers and Maguire, in press</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Spiers, H. J., &amp; Maguire, E. A. (in press). The dynamic nature of cognition during wayfinding. <italic>Journal of Environmental Psychology</italic>, <ext-link xlink:href="doi:10.1016/j.jenvp.2008.02.006" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1016/j.jenvp.2008.02.006</ext-link>.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <label>Spiers et al., 2001</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Spiers</surname>
              <given-names>H.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burgess</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hartley</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vargha-Khadem</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O’Keefe</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bilateral hippocampal pathology impairs topographical and episodic memory but not visual pattern matching</article-title>
          <source>Hippocampus</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>715</fpage>
          <lpage>725</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11811666</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib25">
        <label>Vafaei and Rashidy-Pour, 2004</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vafaei</surname>
              <given-names>A.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rashidy-Pour</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reversible lesions of the rat's orbitofrontal cortex interferes with hippocampus-dependent spatial memory</article-title>
          <source>Behavioural Brain Research</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>149</volume>
          <fpage>61</fpage>
          <lpage>68</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14739010</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib26">
        <label>Yoshida and Ishii, 2006</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yoshida</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ishii</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Resolution of uncertainty in prefrontal cortex</article-title>
          <source>Neuron</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>781</fpage>
          <lpage>789</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16731515</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>