<article xmlns="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biochim Biophys Acta</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0006-3002</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier Pub. Co</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3161177</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21782973</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">BBAMCB57132</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbalip.2011.07.004</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>YALI0E32769g (<italic>DGA1</italic>) and YALI0E16797g (<italic>LRO1</italic>) encode major triacylglycerol synthases of the oleaginous yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Athenstaedt</surname>
            <given-names>Karin</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>karin.athenstaedt@tugraz.at</email>
          <xref rid="cr0005" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="af0005">Graz University of Technology, Institute of Biochemistry, Petersgasse 12/2, A-8010 Graz, Austria</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cr0005"><label>⁎</label>Technische Universität Graz, Institut für Biochemie, Petersgasse 12/2, A-8010 Graz, Austria. Tel.: +43 316 873 6460; fax: +43 316 873 6952. <email>karin.athenstaedt@tugraz.at</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>1811</volume>
      <issue>10</issue>
      <fpage>587</fpage>
      <lpage>596</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>14</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2011 Elsevier B.V.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Elsevier B.V.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/authorsview.authors/supplementalterms1.0">certain conditions</ext-link>.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The oleaginous yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> has an outstanding capacity to produce and store triacylglycerols resembling adipocytes of higher eukaryotes. Here, the identification of two genes YALI0E32769g (<italic>DGA1</italic>) and YALI0E16797g (<italic>LRO1</italic>) encoding major triacylglycerol synthases of <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> is reported. Heterologous expression of either <italic>DGA1</italic> or <italic>LRO1</italic> in a mutant of the budding yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> defective in triacylglycerol synthesis restores the formation of this neutral lipid. Whereas Dga1p requires acyl-CoA as a substrate for acylation of diacylglycerol, Lro1p is an acyl-CoA independent triacylglycerol synthase using phospholipids as acyl-donor. Growth of <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> strains deleted of <italic>DGA1</italic> and/or <italic>LRO1</italic> on glucose containing medium significantly decreases triacylglycerol accumulation. Most interestingly, when oleic acid serves as the carbon source the ratio of triacylglycerol accumulation in mutants to wild-type is significantly increased in strains defective in <italic>DGA1</italic> but not in <italic>lro1Δ</italic>. In vitro experiments revealed that under these conditions an additional acyl-CoA dependent triacylglycerol synthase contributes to triacylglycerol synthesis in the respective mutants. Taken together, evidence is provided that <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> contains at least four triacylglycerol synthases, namely Lro1p, Dga1p and two additional triacylglycerol synthases whereof one is acyl-CoA dependent and specifically induced upon growth on oleic acid.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract abstract-type="graphical">
        <title>Highlights</title>
        <p>►Identification of 2 triacylglycerol synthases of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic>, Dga1p and Lro1p. ►Dga1p is an acyl-CoA dependent triacylglycerol synthase. ►Lro1p uses phospholipids as acyl donor for triacylglycerol formation. ►Growth on oleic acid induces additional triacylglycerol synthase(s).</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Abbreviation</title>
        <kwd>TAG, triacylglycerols</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Triacylglycerol synthesis</kwd>
        <kwd>Oleic acid</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>Yeast</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Major neutral lipids occurring in most eukaryotic cells are triacylglycerols (TAG) and steryl esters. These lipids accumulate when cells are provided with an excess of nutrients. During starvation periods these storage lipids are mobilized serving as a source of energy and/or building blocks for the formation of membrane lipids. Due to the importance of TAG as an inert storage molecule, its metabolism appears to be conserved from bacteria to men. Synthesis of TAG occurs by acylation of the free hydroxyl-group of its direct precursor diacylglycerol. This final step of TAG formation is either catalyzed by an acyl-CoA dependent or acyl-CoA independent enzyme (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, for reviews see <xref rid="bb0005 bb0010" ref-type="bibr">[1,2]</xref>).</p>
      <p>In the yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> Lro1p has been identified as an acyl-CoA independent acyltransferase <xref rid="bb0015 bb0020" ref-type="bibr">[3,4]</xref>. This enzyme is a homolog of the human lecithin:cholesterol acyltransferase (LCAT). Similar to its human counterpart, Lro1p cleaves off an acyl group from the <italic>sn</italic>-2 position of phosphatidylcholine or phosphatidylethanolamine, but uses diacylglycerol as the acceptor molecule instead. Lro1p is the only acyl-CoA independent acyltransferase of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, since an acyl-CoA independent activity has not been detected in the respective deletion mutant. In contrast, three enzymes are known to catalyze acylation of DAG yielding TAG via the acyl-CoA dependent pathway. The acyl-CoA:diacylglycerol acyltransferase Dga1p is the major acyl-CoA dependent TAG synthase in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> <xref rid="bb0025 bb0030 bb0035" ref-type="bibr">[5–7]</xref>. Dga1p is a member of the DGAT2 family. Are1p and Are2p, two ACAT (acyl-CoA:cholesterol acyltransferase) related enzymes originally considered to acylate specifically sterols, have been demonstrated to be responsible for the residual acyl-CoA dependent TAG synthase activity in an <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> double mutant <xref rid="bb0030 bb0040" ref-type="bibr">[6,8]</xref>. This is not surprising insofar, since Are1p and Are2p are members of the DGAT1 family, containing the mammalian DGAT1 and acyl-CoA:cholesterol acyltransferases of plants and mammals. Deletion of <italic>ARE1</italic> and <italic>ARE2</italic> in an <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> mutant background results in a quadruple mutant, i.e., <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ,</italic> lacking TAG. This fact indicates that in contrast to plants and mammalian cells, in <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> no enzyme exists which catalyzes the transacylase reaction converting two diacylglycerol molecules to TAG and monoacylglycerol <xref rid="bb0045 bb0050" ref-type="bibr">[9,10]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In the fission yeast <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> Plh1p, an acyl-CoA independent TAG synthase, and Dga1p, catalyzing the acyl-CoA dependent acylation of diacylglycerol, have been identified by gene and function <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Plh1p and Dga1p of the fission yeast are the respective counterparts of Lro1p and Dga1p of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>. Whereas a defect in either <italic>LRO1</italic> or <italic>DGA1</italic> of the budding yeast is reflected by a decreased amount of TAG <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, no difference in the accumulation of TAG compared to control has been detected in the single deletion mutants <italic>plh1Δ</italic> and <italic>dga1Δ</italic> of <italic>S. pombe</italic> <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. This finding reveals that in the latter yeast one TAG synthase compensates the defect/lack of the other enzyme. Plh1p and Dga1p are the only TAG synthases of <italic>S. pombe,</italic> since the <italic>plh1Δdga1Δ</italic> double mutant lacks TAG.</p>
      <p>In the oleaginous yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> mainly TAG and only minor quantities of steryl esters accumulate as storage lipids <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Like in all eukaryotic cells these neutral lipids are sequestered from the cytosolic environment in so-called lipid particles. The structure of these storage compartments of neutral lipids is rather simple. TAG and steryl esters are forming a hydrophobic core which is surrounded by a phospholipid monolayer with few proteins embedded (for a review see <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>). Under specific growth conditions, e.g., when industrial fats or glycerol are used as a carbon source, the amount of TAG can be increased up to 40% of cell dry weight <xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Microscopic inspection of cells grown under such conditions reveals that nearly the entire cell is filled with lipid particles <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. This outstanding capacity of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> to accumulate neutral lipids (mainly TAG) leads to its application in biotechnological processes such as single cell oil production or production of nutrients enriched in essential fatty acids which can serve as nutritional complements. However, <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> may also serve as a model organism for studying lipid turnover in adipocytes, since not only the ability to store excessive amounts of TAG in lipid particles but also the composition of this cell compartment resembles adipocytes of higher eukaryotes. Despite these potentials of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> current information about TAG (lipid) metabolism in this yeast is rather limited.</p>
      <p>Here, evidence is provided that the gene products of YALI0E32769g (<italic>DGA1</italic>) and YALI0E16797g (<italic>LRO1</italic>) are major TAG synthases of the oleaginous yeast <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic>. This conclusion is based on results from analyses of lipid profiles and measurements of enzymatic activities of wild-type, the single deletion strains <italic>lro1Δ</italic> and <italic>dga1Δ</italic>, and the double deletion mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic>. Most importantly, heterologous expression of the respective genes in cells of a <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> mutant defective in TAG synthesis complements the defect of the host cells. Furthermore, the results reveal that growth on oleic acid containing medium but not on glucose containing medium induces acyl-CoA dependent TAG synthase activity in a <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> mutant lacking <italic>DGA1</italic> and <italic>LRO1</italic>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s0010">
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="s0015">
        <label>2.1</label>
        <title>Strains and culture conditions</title>
        <p>Yeast strains used throughout this study are listed in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> cells were grown aerobically in Erlenmeyer flasks at 30 °C in medium containing 0.67% yeast nitrogen base (US Biological), 0.1% yeast extract (Oxoid), 0.5% NH<sub>4</sub>Cl (Merck), 50 mM potassium phosphate buffer (pH 6.8), 0.01% leucine (Roth) and either 2% glucose (Merck) or 1% oleic acid (Merck) dissolved with 1% Brij58 as a carbon source. Fifty milliliters of culture medium were inoculated to an optical density (OD<sub>600</sub>) of 0.01 from an over night culture grown aerobically. Growth was monitored by measuring OD<sub>600</sub>.</p>
        <p>For heterologous expression studies <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> cells transformed with plasmids containing either <italic>LRO1</italic> or <italic>DGA1</italic> of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> were grown aerobically in Erlenmeyer flasks at 30 °C in synthetic minimal (SM) media containing 2% glucose or 2% galactose (Merck), respectively, and 0.67% yeast nitrogen base (US Biological) supplemented with the appropriate amino acids.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0020">
        <label>2.2</label>
        <title>Genetic techniques</title>
        <p>For heterologous expression of either Dga1p or Lro1p of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> in the quadruple deletion mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> of the budding yeast <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> the respective open reading frames YALI0E32769g (<italic>DGA1</italic>) and YALI0E16797g (<italic>LRO1</italic>) were inserted into the pYES2 vector (Invitrogen). Insertion cassettes were obtained by PCR using genomic DNA derived from a <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> wild-type strain as template. Primers used for amplification are shown in <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. PCR products were purified with NucleoSpin purification kit (Marcherey-Nagel). The plasmid was cleaved with <italic>Bam</italic>HI and <italic>Eco</italic>RI. PCR products and the cleaved plasmid were purified by agarose gel electrophoresis and fragments recovered from the gel with NucleoSpin gel extraction kit (Macherey-Nagel). The cleaved plasmid and the purified PCR fragment of either <italic>DGA1</italic> or <italic>LRO1</italic> were used for transformation of the quadruple deletion mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>. The respective plasmids were formed upon homologous recombination. The correct insertion of the PCR fragments into the plasmid was verified by colony PCR with control primers listed in <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p>
        <p>The quadruple mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> of the budding yeast <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> was obtained by crossings and tetrad dissection of the respective single deletion strains (EUROSCARF strain collection). The disruption of all four genes in the respective mutant was verified by control PCR and confirmed by the absence of TAG and steryl esters resulting in a lack of lipid particles (see below).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0025">
        <label>2.3</label>
        <title>Preparation of enzyme sources for activity measurements</title>
        <p>Homogenates and microsomes of the strains listed in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> were isolated as described previously <xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Strains of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> grown on oleic acid containing media were washed three times with 0.5% BSA solution prior to application of the protocol for spheroplast and organelle preparation. Spheroplasts were prepared by treatment with zymolyase as described by Daum et al. <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Microsomal fractions were obtained by following the protocol of Zinser et al. <xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>.</p>
        <p>For protein quantification polypeptides were precipitated from the aqueous phase with trichloroacetic acid at a final concentration of 10%. The protein pellet was solubilized in 0.1% SDS – 0.1 M NaOH at 37 °C. Protein quantification was performed by the method of Lowry et al. <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> using bovine serum albumin as a standard.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0030">
        <label>2.4</label>
        <title>Lipid analysis</title>
        <p>Total lipids of cells grown to the stationary phase (24 h) were extracted by the procedure of Folch et al. <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. Strains of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> grown in the presence of oleic acid were washed three times with 0.5% BSA solution prior to lipid extraction. Analysis of neutral lipids was performed as described in <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. In brief, lipids were separated by thin-layer chromatography (TLC) using the solvent systems petroleum ether-diethyl ether-acetic acid (25:25:1; per vol.; developed to 1/3 of the total distance) and petroleum ether-diethyl ether (49:1; vol./vol.; total distance). Neutral lipids were visualized on TLC plates by post-chromatographic staining. Plates were dipped for 6 s into a developing reagent consisting of 0.63 g of MnCl<sub>2</sub>.4H<sub>2</sub>O, 60 ml of water, 60 ml of methanol, and 4 ml of concentrated sulphuric acid, briefly dried, and heated to 105 °C for 30 min. Subsequently, TAG were quantified by densitometric scanning at 400 nm with triolein (NuCheck, Inc., Elysian, MN) as a standard.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0035">
        <label>2.5</label>
        <title>Fluorescence microscopy</title>
        <p><italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> cells were grown either on glucose or on oleic acid containing medium for 24 h prior to microscopic inspection. To analyze the functionality of <italic>DGA1</italic> and <italic>LRO1</italic>, respectively, upon heterologous expression in the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> quadruple mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> transformants were grown to the stationary phase in Ura<sup>-</sup> minimal medium containing either glucose or galactose as the carbon source. Cells were harvested by centrifugation washed twice and put onto microscope slides. By mixing the cell suspension with a solution of 1 mg/ml Nile Red® (Sigma) in ethanol, cells were stained directly on the slide. Microscopic analysis was performed on a Zeiss Axiovert 35 microscope using a 100-fold oil immersion objective, a UV lamp, and a detection range between 450 and 490 nm. Images were taken with a CCD camera.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0040">
        <label>2.6</label>
        <title>Enzyme assays</title>
        <p>The diacylglycerol acyltransferase assay was performed as described previously <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. In brief, enzymatic activity was measured in a final volume of 400 μl containing 10 nmol dipalmitoylglycerol, 100 nmol unlabeled (Sigma) and radioactively labeled [1-<sup>14</sup>C]oleoyl-CoA or [1-<sup>14</sup>C]palmitoyl-CoA (0.04 μCi; Perkin Elmer), 400 μg BSA, 30 μg dithiothreitol, 0.25% Triton X-100, 150 mM Tris/Cl<sup>-</sup> (pH 7.0), 15 mM KCl, 15 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and either homogenate (0.7 to 0.9 mg) or microsomes (0.1 to 0.3 mg) as the respective enzyme source. For measuring the phospholipid:diacylglycerol acyltransferase activity the assay mixture was essentially the same as for the diacylglycerol acyltransferase assay but the amount of dipalmitoylglycerol was increased to 20 nmol, [<sup>14</sup>C]phospholipids (75,000 dpm; approx. 25 μg) were used as the labeled substrate and acyl-CoA was omitted. Both assays were carried out at 30 °C and the reaction was terminated after 30 min by the addition of 3 ml chloroform-methanol (2:1; vol./vol.). Lipids were extracted <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, separated by thin-layer chromatography with the solvent system petroleum ether-diethyl ether-acetic acid (70:30:2; per vol.), scraped off the plate and radioactivity was measured by liquid scintillation counting in 8 ml liquid-scintillation cocktail containing 5% water.</p>
        <p>Radioactively labeled phospholipids were synthesized by incubation of a <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> strain with 0.1 mCi of [1-<sup>14</sup>C]palmitic acid for 24 h at 30 °C in 100 ml medium containing 2% glucose (Merck), 1% yeast extract (Oxoid) and 2% peptone (Oxoid). Lipids were extracted by using the method of Folch et al. <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> and separated by thin-layer chromatography. The band containing phospholipids was scraped off the plate and phospholipids extracted from the silica gel with chloroform-methanol (1:4; vol./vol.). Label-distribution between major glycerophospholipids: phosphatidylcholine 45%, phosphatidylethanolamine 30%, phosphatidylinositol 14%, phosphatidylserine 11%.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0045">
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="s0050">
        <label>3.1</label>
        <title>Two open reading frames (ORFs) of <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> homologous to genes encoding TAG synthases</title>
        <p>Analysis of the lipid particle proteome of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> revealed the presence of a protein encoded by the open reading frame YALI0E32769g sharing 50% identity and 71% homology to the acyl-CoA:diacylglycerol acyltransferase Dga1p of the budding yeast <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> and 51% identity and 72% homology to the respective enzyme in the fission yeast <italic>S. pombe</italic> (blast search: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ch.embnet.org">http://www.ch.embnet.org</ext-link>). In addition, the sequence of the potential TAG synthase of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> reveals homology to acyl-CoA:diacylglycerol acyltransferases of mammals, e.g., mouse, rat and human (56% homology). The predicted molecular mass of the Dga1p homolog of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> is 57.8 kDa (514 amino acids) with a pI of 8.7 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ch.embnet.org/software/TMPRED_form.html">http://www.ch.embnet.org/software/TMPRED_form.html</ext-link>). Noteworthy, this protein contains after the first ~ 120 amino acids an insertion of 113 and 155 amino acids, respectively, compared to Dga1p of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> and <italic>S. pombe</italic> (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A).</p>
        <p>The second major TAG-synthase of the budding yeast <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> is Lro1p (<underline>l</underline>ecithin:cholesterol acyltransferase (LCAT) <underline>r</underline>elated <underline>O</underline>RF). Homology searches in the genome of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> with <italic>LRO1</italic> of the budding yeast as a query highlighted the ORF YALI0E16797g as a sequence encoding a potential acyl-CoA independent TAG synthase. The respective protein encoded by YALI0E16797g shares 51% identity and 68% homology to Lro1p of <italic>S. cerevisiae,</italic> and 46% identity and 64% homology to Plh1p, the Lro1p counterpart of <italic>S. pombe</italic> (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>B). Furthermore, the potential TAG synthase of the oleaginous yeast is related to lecithin:cholesterol acyltransferases (LCAT) of mammals, e.g., rabbit, mouse, human. The Lro1p homolog of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> is formed of 648 amino acids with an estimated molecular mass of 72.6 kDa and a pI of 5.5 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ch.embnet.org/software/TMPRED_form.html">http://www.ch.embnet.org/software/TMPRED_form.html</ext-link>).</p>
        <p>For both potential TAG synthases of the oleaginous yeast a transmembrane domain is predicted at the N-terminus (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>C). Similarly, Dga1p and the phospholipid:diacylglycerol acyltransferase of the budding and fission yeast, respectively, contain an N-terminal transmembrane domain (Kyte Doolittle blot: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://fasta.bioch.virginia.edu">http://fasta.bioch.virginia.edu</ext-link>/).</p>
        <p>Due to the homologies of the respective gene products to already identified TAG synthases of other eukaryotes these unassigned genes of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> are named hereafter <italic>DGA1</italic> (YALI0E32769g) and <italic>LRO1</italic> (YALI0E16797g).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0055">
        <label>3.2</label>
        <title>The number and size of lipid particles is changed in <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> cells</title>
        <p>Since TAG and steryl esters lack charged groups they do not fit into the phospholipid bilayer of membranes and are sequestered from the cytosolic environment in the hydrophobic core of so-called lipid particles. In the oleaginous yeast <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> the hydrophobic core of lipid particles consists mainly of TAG <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. To analyze whether deletion of <italic>DGA1</italic> and/or <italic>LRO1</italic> affects the size and/or number of lipid particles, cells grown to the stationary phase were stained with the fluorescent dye NileRed® specific for these compartments (see <xref rid="s0010" ref-type="sec">Materials and methods</xref>). Whereas the number and size of lipid particles in cells of the single deletion mutants <italic>lro1Δ</italic> and <italic>dga1Δ</italic> grown on glucose containing medium are similar to control, a higher number of small lipid particles is formed in the double deletion mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). In contrast, no significant differences in the formation of lipid particles are observed between the single deletion mutants <italic>lro1Δ</italic> and <italic>dga1Δ,</italic> the double deletion mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> and control when oleic acid serves as a carbon source (data not shown).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0060">
        <label>3.3</label>
        <title>The contribution of TAG synthases to TAG accumulation depends on the carbon source</title>
        <p>Cells of the single deletion mutants <italic>lro1Δ</italic> and <italic>dga1Δ,</italic> and the double deletion mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> were grown to the stationary phase either on glucose or oleic acid containing medium, lipids of total cells extracted and analyzed for the neutral lipid composition (see <xref rid="s0010" ref-type="sec">Materials and methods</xref>). The single deletion mutant <italic>lro1Δ</italic> accumulates TAG to approx. 75% of wild-type level independent whether glucose or oleic acid serves as a carbon source (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). In contrast, the amount of TAG is only significantly reduced in lipid extracts of <italic>dga1Δ</italic> cells grown on glucose containing medium (90% of control) but not when oleic acid serves as a carbon source. By growing cells of the double deletion mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> on glucose containing medium the TAG level decreases to 30% of control. In contrast, in cell extracts of the double deletion mutant grown on oleic acid medium the amount of TAG is reduced to 85% of wild-type level. Since TAG are still formed in the double deletion mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic>, <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> harbors at least one additional enzyme catalyzing the acylation of diacylglycerol<italic>.</italic></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0065">
        <label>3.4</label>
        <title>Lipid particle formation is restored upon heterologous expression of <italic>LRO1</italic> and <italic>DGA1</italic>, respectively, in a <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> mutant otherwise lacking these cell compartments</title>
        <p>Even though all results presented so far are pinpointing that Dga1p and Lro1p of the oleaginous yeast are indeed TAG synthases, it cannot be excluded that one of these proteins or both are involved in the regulation of TAG synthesis. Thus, heterologous expression experiments were performed.</p>
        <p>As already mentioned above, neutral lipids such as TAG and steryl esters do not fit into membrane structures and are sequestered in lipid particles. In the budding yeast <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> four enzymes catalyze the acylation of diacylglycerol yielding TAG, i.e., Lro1p, Dga1p, Are1p and Are2p <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. The preferential substrates of Are1p and Are2p, however, are sterols. Since Are1p and Are2p are the only steryl ester synthases in the budding yeast, the quadruple mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> lacks not only TAG but also steryl esters and consequently does not form lipid particles. To investigate the function of Dga1p and Lro1p of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> the respective genes were cloned into the vector pYES2 and heterologously expressed in the quadruple mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> (see <xref rid="s0010" ref-type="sec">Materials and methods</xref>). The <italic>GAL1</italic> promoter of the plasmid allows induction of gene expression by growing cells on galactose containing medium. Staining cells of both plasmid bearing <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> mutants with the lipophilic fluorescent dye NileRed® and microscopic inspection demonstrate the formation of lipid particles upon galactose induction (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>A, panels c and d). Whereas heterologous expression of <italic>LRO1</italic> in the quadruple deletion mutant background leads to the formation of lipid particles similar in size to the ones present in the corresponding <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> wild-type strain, the size of the particles is significantly increased in the quadruple mutant expressing <italic>DGA1</italic>. The number of lipid particles formed upon heterologous expression of either <italic>DGA1</italic> or <italic>LRO1</italic> in the <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> quadruple mutant is limited to 1 to 2. As a negative control, no lipid particles are formed in the quadruple mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> bearing the empty vector (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>A, panel b) or when transformants are grown on glucose containing minimal media (data not shown). Lipid analyses of total cells of the quadruple mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> expressing either <italic>DGA1</italic> or <italic>LRO1</italic> of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> demonstrate the presence of TAG (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>C). The prominent TAG band in the lipid extract of the transformant expressing <italic>DGA1</italic> (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>C, lane 5) parallels the bigger size of lipid particles observed by fluorescence microscopy (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>A, panel c). The absence of steryl esters in lipid extracts of strains heterologously expressing <italic>DGA1</italic> or <italic>LRO1</italic> demonstrates that sterols do not serve as substrate of Dga1p and Lro1p (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>B).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0070">
        <label>3.5</label>
        <title>Lro1p and Dga1p use different acyl-donors for TAG synthesis</title>
        <p>To elucidate the mechanism employed by Lro1p and Dga1p, respectively, for TAG formation enzyme assays specific for acyl-CoA dependent and acyl-CoA independent acylation of diacylglycerol were performed with transformants heterologously expressing <italic>DGA1</italic> or <italic>LRO1</italic> (see <xref rid="s0010" ref-type="sec">Materials and methods</xref>). In presence of oleoyl-CoA TAG synthase activity of homogenate of the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> quadruple mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> heterologously expressing <italic>DGA1</italic> is 45-fold increased compared to the respective corresponding wild-type of the quadruple mutant bearing the empty plasmid (<xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>A). However, in the assay specific for acyl-CoA dependent acylation some label is also incorporated into TAG when homogenate of <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> heterologously expressing <italic>LRO1</italic> serves as the enzyme source (60% of <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> wild-type level). Since oleic acid is the most abundant fatty acid occurring in TAG of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> (52.5%) <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, enzymatic measurements for acyl-CoA dependent TAG synthesis were performed with oleoyl-CoA as a substrate. The second major fatty acid bound to the glycerol backbone of TAG is palmitic acid (22.1%). Comparison of the specific activities of Dga1p measured either in the presence of oleoyl-CoA or palmitoyl-CoA revealed a clear preference for the former fatty acid (479 ± 46 nmol/mg ∗ min vs. 108 ± 13 nmol/mg ∗ min).</p>
        <p>By using phospholipids as acyl-donor microsomes of the quadruple mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> containing <italic>LRO1</italic> of the oleaginous yeast incorporate 1.4 times more radioactive label into TAG than microsomes of the corresponding <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> wild-type strain bearing the empty vector (<xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>B). Whereas substantial amounts of labeled TAG were formed in the presence of the phospholipid mixture used for the acyl-CoA independent assay (see <xref rid="s0010" ref-type="sec">Materials and methods</xref>), only traces of labeled TAG were formed when individual phospholipids (phosphatidylcholine, phosphatidylethanolamine, phosphatidylinositol, phophatidylserine) were used as acyl-donor. Especially phosphatidylcholine turned out to be a very poor substrate (data not shown). In the phospholipid:diacylglycerol acyltransferase specific assay microsomes were used as the enzyme source, because only traces of label were incorporated into TAG when homogenates of the respective strains were used as an enzyme source.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0075">
        <label>3.6</label>
        <title>In vitro activities of acyl-CoA dependent and acyl-CoA independent TAG synthases in <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> depend on the carbon source used for cell growth</title>
        <p>Results of heterologous expression experiments revealed that Dga1p catalyzes TAG synthesis via the acyl-CoA dependent pathway, whereas Lro1p prefers phospholipids as acyl-donor. To study TAG synthesis in <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> in more detail homogenates of the single deletion strains <italic>lro1Δ</italic>, <italic>dga1Δ,</italic> the double deletion mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> and the corresponding wild-type strain were used as an enzyme source in assays specific for either acyl-CoA dependent or acyl-CoA independent acylation of diacylglycerol (see <xref rid="s0010" ref-type="sec">Materials and methods</xref>). By using homogenate of the single deletion mutant <italic>lro1Δ</italic> (i.e., Dga1p is present) grown on glucose containing medium as the enzyme source TAG are only formed in the presence of oleoyl-CoA (<xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>A), but not when phospholipids serve as acyl-donor. In contrast, homogenate of <italic>dga1Δ</italic> cells (i.e., Lro1p is present) grown in the presence of glucose uses phospholipids as the preferred substrate for TAG synthesis. However, this enzyme source incorporates also a small but significant amount of radioactive label into TAG in the acyl-CoA dependent assay. The finding that under the same conditions homogenate of <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> cells grown on glucose containing medium lacks TAG synthase activity indicates that Lro1p of <italic>dga1Δ</italic> catalyzes the incorporation of the labeled fatty acid into TAG. This is in line with the observation that upon heterologous expression of <italic>LRO1</italic> in the <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> homogenate of these cells forms TAG in the presence of acyl-CoA. Even though TAG are present in <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> cells of the oleaginous yeast grown on glucose containing medium (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>), in vitro homogenate of the respective mutant cells lacks also TAG synthase activity when phospholipids are provided as acyl-donor (<xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>A). In the budding yeast <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> it has been shown that the contribution of Lro1p and Dga1p to TAG synthesis depends on the growth stage of the cells <xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Whereas Lro1p is the major TAG synthase in cells of the exponential phase, TAG synthase activity of Dga1p is higher in cells entering the stationary phase. To test whether the same is true for Lro1p and Dga1p of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic>, homogenate of wild-type cells of the exponential growth phase (OD<sub>600</sub> ~ 1.2) and the stationary phase (OD<sub>600</sub> ~ 5.4) were used as an enzyme source in the respective TAG synthase assays. Indeed, acyl-CoA independent TAG synthase (Lro1p) activity decreased by ~ 25% (A<sub>spec</sub> = 1.4 ± 0.06 pg/mg ∗ min vs. A<sub>spec</sub> = 1.1 ± 0.05 pg/mg ∗ min) and that of Dga1p increased by ~ 20% (A<sub>spec</sub> = 8.3 ± 0.6 pmol/mg ∗ min vs. A<sub>spec</sub> = 10 ± 1.8 pmol/mg ∗ min).</p>
        <p>In analogy to the enzyme assays performed with homogenates of cells grown on glucose containing media, homogenates of cells grown on oleic acid containing media were tested for TAG synthase activities via both mechanisms (<xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>B). In the Lro1p-specific assay enzymatic activity of homogenate of <italic>dga1Δ</italic> cells (i.e., Lro1p is present) grown in the presence of oleic acid is 1.7-fold increased compared to wild-type. In contrast to homogenate of <italic>lro1Δ</italic> cells grown on glucose containing medium which lacks phospholipid:diacylglycerol acyltransferase activity (<xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>A), a small amount of label is incorporated into TAG via this pathway when the respective enzyme source of cells grown in the presence of oleic acid is used. However, under the same conditions homogenate of the double deletion mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> is inactive. In the acyl-CoA dependent TAG synthase assay homogenates of both single deletion mutants and the double deletion mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> form TAG, however, with lower efficiency than control. Noteworthy, in contrast to homogenate of <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> cells grown on glucose containing medium which do not incorporate the provided acyl-CoA group into TAG (<xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>A), homogenate of the respective mutant cells grown on oleic acid containing medium exhibit TAG synthase activity via the acyl-CoA dependent pathway. Since homogenates of both <italic>dga1Δ</italic> cells as well as <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> cells contain 35% of acyl-CoA dependent TAG-synthase activity compared to control (<xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>B), the observed acylation activity cannot be ascribed to Lro1p. Thus, in <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> cells grown on oleic acid containing medium at least one additional acyl-CoA dependent enzyme contributes to TAG synthesis.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0080">
      <label>4</label>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Here evidence is provided that the open reading frames YALI0E32769g and YALI0E16797g named hereafter <italic>DGA1</italic> and <italic>LRO1</italic>, respectively, encode major TAG synthases of the oleaginous yeast <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic>. Moreover, it is shown that growth on oleic acid containing medium induces acyl-CoA dependent TAG synthase activity catalyzed by an additional enzyme. This is concluded from data obtained by a combined biochemical, cell biological and molecular biological approach including lipid profiling of mutants deleted of <italic>DGA1</italic> and/or <italic>LRO1</italic>, measurements of enzymatic activity in vitro and heterologous expression experiments.</p>
      <p>Recently, Ghosal et al. <xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> demonstrated for Lro1p of the budding yeast <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> that a transmembrane domain at the N-terminus is responsible for its localization to the endoplasmic reticulum (ER). Even though homology of phospholipid:diacylglycerol synthases of different yeast species is rather low at the N-terminal end, computational analysis predicts also for Lro1p of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> the presence of a transmembrane domain in this region (see <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>C). The observation that heterologous expression of <italic>LRO1</italic> in a mutant of the budding yeast lacking TAG synthase activity not only restores TAG synthesis via the phospholipid:diacylglycerol acyltransferase mechanism but furthermore that the respective enzymatic activity is enriched in microsomes (ER) indicates that structural features rather than the N-terminal sequence are responsible for localization to the ER. Localization studies of Dga1p of the budding yeast revealed its presence in lipid particles and the ER <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. A similar dual localization of Dga1p of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> is anticipated, because this polypeptide has formerly been identified as an unassigned lipid particle protein <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> and furthermore, acyl-CoA dependent TAG synthase activity is enriched in microsomes of a <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> wild-type strain grown on glucose but absent in the respective enzyme source of <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> cells (K. Athenstaedt, unpublished result).</p>
      <p>In <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> TAG are a major component of so-called lipid particles, spherical structures sequestering neutral lipids from the cytosolic environment in a hydrophobic core <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Thus, the possibility of differences in lipid particle formation in cells defective in TAG synthesis has been considered. Microscopic inspection reveals that indeed in cells of the double deletion mutant grown on glucose containing medium the number and size of lipid particles are affected (see <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). These differences in lipid particle formation in <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> cells grown in the presence of glucose are paralleled by the lowest accumulation of TAG compared to the other strains tested (see <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Since TAG serve as an energy source and/or a source of building blocks for membrane formation when nutrients are no longer provided by the environment, a smaller amount of TAG might lead to reduced long term viability and/or a prolonged lag phase after transferring the cells to fresh medium. However, neither any difference during the onset of growth nor in the long term viability (K. Athenstaedt, unpublished result) between <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> and wild-type has been observed, indicating that even the reduced amount of TAG in the double deletion mutant is sufficient for balanced growth.</p>
      <p>In the budding yeast <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic> four enzymes contribute to TAG synthesis, namely Lro1p, Dga1p, Are1p and Are2p <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. The quadruple mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> is viable, lacks TAG as well as lipid particles, and has thus been chosen as a tool for studying the function of the polypeptides encoded by <italic>DGA1</italic> and <italic>LRO1</italic> of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic>. Results of the heterologous expression experiments unambiguously identified Lro1p and Dga1p of the oleaginous yeast as TAG synthases. Moreover, these experiments revealed that whereas Dga1p requires acyl-CoA as a substrate for TAG synthesis, Lro1p uses phospholipids as acyl-donor. At the first sight the latter enzyme appears to accept at least to some extent acyl-CoA as a substrate as well, because in the TAG synthase assay specific for acyl-CoA dependent acylation significant amounts of TAG have been formed with homogenate of <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> cells heterologously expressing <italic>LRO1</italic> of the oleaginous yeast (see <xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). However, in an additional experiment where the assay mixture contained radioactively labeled diacylglycerol as a substrate but no phospholipid substantial amounts of TAG were synthesized. This shows that phospholipids of the bilayer membrane containing Lro1p were efficiently used for TAG formation by this enzyme. Furthermore, acyl-CoAs are rapidly incorporated into phospholipids by a remodeling process. Thus, it is most likely that in the respective assays the labeled acyl-CoA group ended up in TAG by an alternative route involving incorporation of the labeled fatty acid into phospholipids and subsequent transfer of the respective acyl-chain from those phospholipids surrounding Lro1p to TAG.</p>
      <p>By using homogenate of the double deletion mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> grown on glucose containing medium as an enzyme source no TAG is formed independent whether acyl-CoA or phospholipids is/are added as the respective acyl-donor (see <xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>A), thus indicating that Lro1p and Dga1p are the only TAG synthases of the oleaginous yeast. Lipid analysis (see <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>) and fluorescence microscopic inspection (see <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>), however, clearly demonstrate that the double deletion mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> still forms TAG which are sequestered in lipid particles. Thus, <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> harbors at least one additional enzyme besides Lro1p and Dga1p which catalyzes TAG formation. The fact that both types of in vitro assays do not yield TAG when homogenate of <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> cells grown on glucose containing medium serves as an enzyme source suggests that the potential additional TAG synthase catalyzes TAG formation by a different mechanism, probably by converting two diacylglycerol molecules to TAG and monoacylglycerol (see <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). However, since isoenzymes do not necessarily require the same conditions for revealing enzymatic activity and/or may be active at different growth phases, the additional TAG synthase(s) may nevertheless form TAG by a mechanism similar to Dga1p and Lro1p.</p>
      <p>The scenario of TAG synthesis in <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> cells significantly changes when oleic acid serves as the carbon source (see <xref rid="f0020 f0035" ref-type="fig">Figs. 4 and 7</xref>B). In <italic>lro1Δ</italic> cells TAG accumulate to approximately 75% of wild-type level independent whether glucose or oleic acid serves as the carbon source. In contrast, the ratio of TAG accumulation in mutants defective in <italic>DGA1</italic> to wild-type increases in favor of the mutant when oleic acid serves as a carbon source. Whereas the increased ratio of TAG accumulation in <italic>dga1Δ</italic> cells can be explained by a higher TAG synthase activity via the phospholipid:diacylglycerol acyltransferase specific pathway, another reason has to be relevant for the higher ratio of TAG accumulation in <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> cells. Results of in vitro experiments clearly demonstrate that in <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> cells growing on oleic acid medium at least one additional acyl-CoA dependent enzyme contributes to TAG synthesis. Since this additional TAG synthase reveals its enzymatic activity especially in cells lacking both Lro1p and Dga1p it is hypothesized that the respective enzyme may function as a kind of security system preventing the accumulation of toxic amounts of fatty acids. A toxic effect of higher amounts of free fatty acids is anticipated, since mutant cells of the fission yeast <italic>S. pombe</italic> lacking TAG synthesis undergo apoptosis upon reaching the stationary phase which is paralleled by accumulation of free fatty acids and diacylglycerols <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Similarly, cell viability is strongly decreased in the quadruple mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> of the budding yeast <italic>S. cerevisiae</italic>, likewise defective in TAG formation, when oleic acid serves as a carbon source <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The future task for understanding the complex process of TAG synthesis in the oleaginous yeast <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> will be the identification and characterization of additional polypeptides governing TAG synthesis. Especially the identification of the additional acyl-CoA dependent TAG synthase specifically induced upon growth on oleic acid containing medium will be a major step forward to understand the complexity of TAG metabolism in the oleaginous yeast. Since the ability of <italic>Y. lipolytica</italic> to accumulate huge amounts of TAG in the presence of fatty acids resembles adipocytes of higher eukaryotes, the knowledge about TAG metabolism in this yeast may provide useful information for similar studies in higher eukaryotes where defects in lipid turnover are related to several severe diseases such as obesity, arteriosclerosis and diabetes.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bb0005">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Oelkers</surname>
              <given-names>P.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sturley</surname>
              <given-names>S.L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Mechanisms and mediators of neutral lipid biosynthesis in eukaryotic cells</chapter-title>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Daum</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <series>Lipid Metabolism and Membrane Biogenesis</series>
          <volume>vol. 6</volume>
          <year>2004</year>
          <publisher-name>Springer Verlag</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Berlin-Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
          <fpage>289</fpage>
          <lpage>311</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0010">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Athenstaedt</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daum</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The life cycle of neutral lipids: synthesis, storage and degradation</article-title>
          <source>Cell. Mol. Life Sci.</source>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>1355</fpage>
          <lpage>1369</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16649142</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0015">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Oelkers</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tinkelenberg</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Erdeniz</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cromley</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Billheimer</surname>
              <given-names>J.T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sturley</surname>
              <given-names>S.L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A lecithin cholesterol acyltransferase-like gene mediates diacylglycerol esterification in yeast</article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <volume>275</volume>
          <year>2000</year>
          <fpage>15609</fpage>
          <lpage>15612</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10747858</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0020">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dahlqvist</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ståhl</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lenman</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Banaś</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sandager</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ronne</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stymne</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Phospholipid:diacylglycerol acyltransferase: an enzyme that catalyzes the acyl-CoA-independent formation of triacylglycerol in yeast and plants</article-title>
          <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <year>2000</year>
          <fpage>6487</fpage>
          <lpage>6492</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10829075</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0025">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Oelkers</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cromley</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Padamsee</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Billheimer</surname>
              <given-names>J.T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sturley</surname>
              <given-names>S.L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The <italic>DGA1</italic> gene determines a second triglyceride synthetic pathway in yeast</article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <volume>277</volume>
          <year>2002</year>
          <fpage>8877</fpage>
          <lpage>8881</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11751875</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0030">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sandager</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gustavsson</surname>
              <given-names>M.H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ståhl</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dahlqvist</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wiberg</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Banaś</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lenman</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ronne</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stymne</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Storage lipid synthesis is non-essential in yeast</article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <volume>277</volume>
          <year>2002</year>
          <fpage>6478</fpage>
          <lpage>6482</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11741946</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0035">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sorger</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daum</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Synthesis of triacylglycerols by the acyl-coenzyme A:diacyl-glycerol acyltransferase Dga1p in lipid particles of the yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <volume>184</volume>
          <year>2002</year>
          <fpage>519</fpage>
          <lpage>524</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0040">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sorger</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Athenstaedt</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hrastnik</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daum</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A yeast strain lacking lipid particles bears a defect in ergosterol formation</article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <volume>279</volume>
          <year>2004</year>
          <fpage>31190</fpage>
          <lpage>31196</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15155725</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0045">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lung</surname>
              <given-names>S.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weselake</surname>
              <given-names>R.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diacylglycerol acyltransferase: a key mediator of plant triacylglycerol synthesis</article-title>
          <source>Lipids</source>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>1073</fpage>
          <lpage>1088</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17269553</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0050">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Buhman</surname>
              <given-names>K.K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>S.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stone</surname>
              <given-names>S.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Repa</surname>
              <given-names>J.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>J.S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Knapp</surname>
              <given-names>F.F.</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burri</surname>
              <given-names>B.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hamilton</surname>
              <given-names>R.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abumrad</surname>
              <given-names>N.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farese</surname>
              <given-names>R.V.</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>DGAT1 is not essential for intestinal triacylglycerol absorption or chylomicron synthesis</article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <volume>277</volume>
          <year>2002</year>
          <fpage>25474</fpage>
          <lpage>25479</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11959864</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0055">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Q.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chieu</surname>
              <given-names>H.K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Low</surname>
              <given-names>C.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heng</surname>
              <given-names>C.K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> cells deficient in triacylglycerol synthesis undergo apoptosis upon entry into the stationary phase</article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <volume>278</volume>
          <year>2003</year>
          <fpage>47145</fpage>
          <lpage>47155</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12963726</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0060">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Athenstaedt</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jolivet</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boulard</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zivy</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Negroni</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicaud</surname>
              <given-names>J.-M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chardot</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lipid particle composition of the yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> depends on the carbon source</article-title>
          <source>Proteomics</source>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>1450</fpage>
          <lpage>1459</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16470660</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0065">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zweytick</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Athenstaedt</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daum</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intracellular lipid particles of eukaryotic cells</article-title>
          <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source>
          <volume>1469</volume>
          <year>2000</year>
          <fpage>101</fpage>
          <lpage>120</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10998572</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0070">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Papanikolaou</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aggelis</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lipid production by <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> growing on industrial glycerol in a single-stage continuous culture</article-title>
          <source>Bioresour. Technol.</source>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <year>2002</year>
          <fpage>43</fpage>
          <lpage>49</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11848376</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0075">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mlíčková</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roux</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Athenstaedt</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>d'Andrea</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daum</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chardot</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicaud</surname>
              <given-names>J.-M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lipid accumulation, lipid body formation, and acyl coenzyme A oxidases of the yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic></article-title>
          <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
          <volume>70</volume>
          <year>2004</year>
          <fpage>3918</fpage>
          <lpage>3924</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15240264</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0080">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zinser</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sperka-Gottlieb</surname>
              <given-names>C.D.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fasch</surname>
              <given-names>E.-V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kohlwein</surname>
              <given-names>S.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paltauf</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daum</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Phospholipid synthesis and lipid composition of subcellular membranes in the unicellular eukaryote <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title>
          <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
          <volume>173</volume>
          <year>1991</year>
          <fpage>2026</fpage>
          <lpage>2034</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2002005</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0085">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Daum</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Böhni</surname>
              <given-names>P.C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schatz</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Import of proteins into mitochondria. Cytochrome b<sub>2</sub> and cytochrome c peroxidase are located in the intermembrane space of yeast mitochondria</article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <volume>257</volume>
          <year>1982</year>
          <fpage>13028</fpage>
          <lpage>13033</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6290489</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0090">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lowry</surname>
              <given-names>O.H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosebrough</surname>
              <given-names>N.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farr</surname>
              <given-names>A.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Randall</surname>
              <given-names>R.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Protein measurement with the Folin phenol reagent</article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <volume>193</volume>
          <year>1951</year>
          <fpage>265</fpage>
          <lpage>275</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14907713</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0095">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Folch</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lees</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sloane-Stanley</surname>
              <given-names>G.H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A simple method for the isolation and purification of total lipides from animal tissues</article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <volume>226</volume>
          <year>1957</year>
          <fpage>497</fpage>
          <lpage>509</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13428781</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0100">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Athenstaedt</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zweytick</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jandrositz</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kohlwein</surname>
              <given-names>S.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daum</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identification and characterization of major lipid particle proteins of the yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title>
          <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
          <volume>181</volume>
          <year>1999</year>
          <fpage>6441</fpage>
          <lpage>6448</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10515935</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0105">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ghosal</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Banaś</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ståhl</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dahlqvist</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lindqvist</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stymne</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> phospholipid:diacylglycerol acyl transferase (PDAT) devoid of its membrane anchor region is a soluble and active enzyme retaining its substrate specificities</article-title>
          <source>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</source>
          <volume>1771</volume>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>1457</fpage>
          <lpage>1463</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18037386</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0110">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Connerth</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Czabany</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wagner</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zellnig</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leitner</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Steyrer</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daum</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Oleate inhibits steryl ester synthesis and causes liposensitivity in yeast</article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <volume>285</volume>
          <year>2010</year>
          <fpage>26832</fpage>
          <lpage>26841</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20571028</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <ref-list>
      <title>Further reading</title>
      <p>Program used for multiple alignments <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ch.embnet.org/">http://www.ch.embnet.org/</ext-link>.</p>
      <p>Program used for Kyte Doolittle blots <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://fasta.bioch.virginia.edu/">http://fasta.bioch.virginia.edu/</ext-link>.</p>
    </ref-list>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgement</title>
      <p>I thank T. Chardot and J.-M. Nicaud (INRA, France) for providing strains, and A. Hermetter (Graz University of Technology) for providing the Axiovert 35 microscope (FWF instrument).</p>
      <p>This work was financially supported by the Austrian Science Fund, FWF, project P21251 to K.A..</p>
    </ack>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="f0005">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Mechanisms of triacylglycerol synthesis. Triacylglycerols (TAG) are either formed via an acyl-CoA dependent (light gray) or acyl-CoA independent (dark gray) mechanism. Abbreviations: DAG: diacylglycerol; MAG: monoacylglycerol; PL: phospholipid.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0010">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Sequence alignments and hydropathy plots of triacylglycerol synthases. Multiple alignments of acyl-CoA:diacylglycerol acyltransferases (A) and the lecithin:cholesterol acyltransferase (LCAT) related proteins (B) of the budding yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> (SeqA), the fission yeast <italic>Schizosaccharomyces pombe</italic> (SeqB) and the oleaginous yeast <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> (SeqC). “<bold>*</bold>”: identical amino acid in all proteins; “<bold>:</bold>” identical amino acid in two polypeptides; “<bold>.</bold>” homologous amino acid. Program: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ch.embnet.org/">http://www.ch.embnet.org/</ext-link>. Hydropathy plots of Dga1p and Lro1p of <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> are shown in <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">panel</xref> C. Dga1p contains an insert of 113 (155) amino acids (marked by the black line) after the N-terminal transmembrane domain which is not present in the respective counterparts of the budding yeast and the fission yeast. Program: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://fasta.bioch.virginia.edu/">http://fasta.bioch.virginia.edu/</ext-link>.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr2a"/>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr2b"/>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr2c"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0015">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Lipid particle formation in <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> mutants defective in triacylglycerol synthesis. Fluorescence microscopic inspection of wild-type cells (A), the single deletion mutants <italic>lro1Δ</italic> (Β), <italic>dga1Δ</italic> (C) and the double deletion mutant <italic>dga1Δlro1Δ</italic> (D) grown to the stationary phase (24 h) on glucose containing media. Cells were stained with the fluorescent lipophilic dye NileRed®. Size bar: 5 μm.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0020">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Triacylglycerol accumulation in strains defective in triacylglycerol synthesizing enzymes. Accumulation of triacylglycerols (TAG) in the single deletion mutants <italic>lro1Δ</italic> , <italic>dga1Δ</italic> and the double deletion mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic> grown on glucose containing media (white bars) and on oleic acid containing media (gray bars). The value for wild-type (glucose: 0.71 ± 0.07% TAG/CDW; oleic acid: 17.9 ± 2.1% TAG/CDW) was set to 100%. Values are mean values of three independent experiments. *: P &lt; 0.05; **: P &lt; &lt; 0.0005; (Student's-<italic>t</italic>-test).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr4"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0025">
      <label>Fig. 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Heterologous expression of <italic>DGA1</italic> and <italic>LRO1</italic>, respectively, restores the formation of triacylglycerols. (A) Fluorescence microscopic inspection reveals that lipid particles are formed upon heterologous expression of <italic>DGA1</italic> (c) and <italic>LRO1</italic> (d) in the quadruple mutant <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> of the budding yeast <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> otherwise lacking lipid particles (b). Panel a shows lipid particle formation in the corresponding wild-type strain of the quadruple mutant bearing the empty vector. Size bar: 5 μm. (C) Analysis of the lipid pattern of the quadruple mutant heterologously expressing either <italic>LRO1</italic> (lane 4) or <italic>DGA1</italic> (lane 5) and the quadruple mutant bearing the empty vector (lane 3). Lane 1: standard containing ergosterol (E), ergosteryl oleate (STE) and triolein (TAG); Lane 2: lipid extract of total cells of the corresponding wild-type strain bearing the empty vector. Solvent system: petroleum ether-diethyl ether-acetic acid 70:30:2 (per vol.). (B) To verify the absence of steryl esters in strains with quadruple mutant background lipids were additionally separated with a solvent system allowing the separation of squalene (S) and STE. Solvent systems: petroleum ether-diethyl ether-acetic acid (25:25:1; per vol.; development of the TLC plate to 1/3 of the distance) and petroleum ether-diethyl ether (49:1; vol./vol.; development to the full distance). Post-chromatographic staining was performed as described in <xref rid="s0010" ref-type="sec">Materials and methods</xref>. Note: The amounts of lipids separated by thin-layer chromatography were extracted from equal amounts of homogenates based on the protein content.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr5"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0030">
      <label>Fig. 6</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Mechanism of triacylglycerol synthesis. Homogenates (A) or microsomes (B) of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> wild-type cells bearing the empty vector (WT + pYES2) and the quadruple mutants <italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> heterologously expressing <italic>DGA1</italic> (QM + <italic>DGA1</italic>) and <italic>LRO1</italic> (QM + <italic>LRO1</italic>), respectively, were used as enzyme sources in TAG synthase assays containing either oleoyl-CoA (A) or phospholipids (B) as a substrate. Activity of wild-type fractions was set to 1 (A<sub>spec</sub> “WT + pYES2” with oleoyl-CoA as substrate (A): 10.2 ± 0.3 pmol/mg ∗ min; A<sub>spec</sub> “WT + pYES2” with phospholipids as substrate (B): 11.8 ± 2.4 pg/mg ∗ min). Enrichment data were obtained from measurements of three independent data-sets. Note: In contrast to acyl-CoA independent TAG synthase activity (B), acyl-CoA dependent TAG synthase activity (A) is not restricted to microsomes (see <xref rid="s0080" ref-type="sec">Discussion</xref>). Thus, homogenates instead of microsomes were chosen as enzyme source in (A). No enzymatic activity was detected with the respective fractions of the quadruple mutant bearing the empty plasmid in the acyl-CoA dependent and acyl-CoA independent assay, which is in line with the lack of neutral lipids and lipid particles (see <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr6"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0035">
      <label>Fig. 7</label>
      <caption>
        <p>In vitro triacylglycerol synthase activities of homogenates of cells defective in <italic>DGA1</italic> and/or <italic>LRO1</italic>. Homogenates of <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic> cells grown either on glucose (A) or oleic acid (B) containing media were used as an enzyme source in triacylglycerol synthase assays specific for acyl-CoA independent (black bars) and acyl-CoA dependent (white bars) acylation of diacylglycerol (see <xref rid="s0010" ref-type="sec">Materials and Methods</xref>). The specific activity of wild-type samples was set to 100% (A<sub>spec</sub> “wt” with oleoyl-CoA as substrate (white bars): 10.3 ± 1.8 pmol/mg ∗ min (glucose; A); 29.7 ± 1.5 pmol/mg min (oleic acid; B); A<sub>spec</sub> “wt” with phospholipids as substrate (black bars): 1.1 ± 0.05 pg/mg min (glucose; A); 0.74 ± 0.1 pg/mg ∗ min (oleic acid; B); mean values of at least 3 independent experiments).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr7"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="t0005" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Strains and plasmids used in this study.</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Strain</th>
            <th align="left">Genotype</th>
            <th align="left">Reference</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="3" align="left">
              <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">JMY330 (wild-type)</td>
            <td align="left"><italic>MATA leu</italic>2-270 <italic>xpr</italic>2-322</td>
            <td align="left">Kindly provided by J.-M. Nicaud</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">JMY1201 (<italic>lro1Δ</italic>)</td>
            <td align="left"><italic>JMY330; lro1Δ</italic>::<italic>URA3</italic></td>
            <td align="left">Kindly provided by J.-M. Nicaud</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">JMY1204 (<italic>dga1Δ</italic>)</td>
            <td align="left"><italic>JMY330; dga1Δ</italic>::<italic>URA3</italic></td>
            <td align="left">Kindly provided by J.-M. Nicaud</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">JMY1281 (<italic>lro1Δdga1Δ</italic>)</td>
            <td align="left">
              <italic>JMY330; lro1Δ::URA3; dga1Δ</italic>
            </td>
            <td align="left">Kindly provided by J.-M. Nicaud</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="3" align="left">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="3" align="left">
              <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">BY4741 + pYES2 (wild-type control)</td>
            <td align="left"><italic>Mat</italic><bold>a</bold><italic>; his3Δ1; leu2Δ0; met15Δ0; ura3Δ0;</italic> + pYES2</td>
            <td align="left">This study</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"><italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> + pYES2</td>
            <td align="left">BY4741<italic>; Mat</italic><bold>a</bold><italic>; lro1Δ</italic>::<italic>KanMX4; dga1Δ</italic>::<italic>KanMX4; are1Δ</italic>::<italic>KanMX4; are2Δ</italic>::<italic>KanMX4</italic> + pYES2</td>
            <td align="left">This study</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"><italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> + pYES2-<italic>LRO1</italic><sup><italic>Yl</italic></sup></td>
            <td align="left">BY4741<italic>; Mat</italic><bold>a</bold><italic>; lro1Δ</italic>::<italic>KanMX4; dga1Δ</italic>::<italic>KanMX4; are1Δ</italic>::<italic>KanMX4; are2Δ</italic>::<italic>KanMX4</italic> + pYES2-<italic>LRO1</italic><sup><italic>Yl</italic></sup></td>
            <td align="left">This study</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"><italic>lro1Δdga1Δare1Δare2Δ</italic> + pYES2-<italic>DGA1</italic><sup><italic>Yl</italic></sup></td>
            <td align="left">BY4741<italic>; Mat</italic><bold>a</bold><italic>; lro1Δ::KanMX4; dga1Δ</italic>::<italic>KanMX4; are1Δ</italic>::<italic>KanMX4; are2Δ</italic>::<italic>KanMX4</italic> + pYES2-<italic>DGA1</italic><sup><italic>Yl</italic></sup></td>
            <td align="left">This study</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="3" align="left">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Plasmids</td>
            <td align="left">Description</td>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="3">
              <hr/>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">pYES2</td>
            <td/>
            <td align="left">Invitrogen</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">pYES2-<italic>LRO1</italic><sup><italic>Yl</italic></sup></td>
            <td align="left">pYES2 containing <italic>LRO1</italic> of <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic></td>
            <td align="left">This study</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">pYES2-<italic>DGA1</italic><sup><italic>Yl</italic></sup></td>
            <td align="left">pYES2 containing <italic>DGA1</italic> of <italic>Yarrowia lipolytica</italic></td>
            <td align="left">This study</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap id="t0010" position="float">
      <label>Table 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Primers used for plasmid construction.</p>
        <p>Underlined sequences are homologous to the respective ORF or the downstream uncoding region.</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Primer</th>
            <th align="left">Sequence 5′→ 3′</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"><italic>LRO1</italic><sup><italic>Yl</italic></sup> (fw)</td>
            <td align="left">CTAGCAGCTGTAATACGACTCACTATAGGGAATATTAAGCTTGGTACCGAGCTCGGATCCACTATGG<underline>CACAACCTGTGAATCGGA</underline></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"><italic>LRO1</italic><sup><italic>Yl</italic></sup> (rev)</td>
            <td align="left">ATGCGGCCCTCTAGATGCATGCTCGAGCGGCCGCCAGTGTGATGGATATCTGCAGAATTC<underline>CCCTTCTCCATCAGTGTG</underline></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"><italic>DGA1</italic><sup><italic>Yl</italic></sup> (fw)</td>
            <td align="left">CTAGCAGCTGTAATACGACTCACTATAGGGAATATTAAGCTTGGTACCGAGCTCGGATCCACTATGG<underline>CTATCGACTCACAATACT</underline></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"><italic>DGA1</italic><sup><italic>Yl</italic></sup> (rev)</td>
            <td align="left">ATGCGGCCCTCTAGATGCATGCTCGAGCGGCCGCCAGTGTGATGGATATCTGCAGAATTC<underline>ATACTCATTAGCTATTTGC</underline></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"><italic>GAL1</italic> (fw; control)</td>
            <td align="left">TGCATAACCACTTTAACT</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"><italic>LRO1</italic><sup><italic>Yl</italic></sup> (rev; control)</td>
            <td align="left">
              <underline>CCTTGCCCACAGCAAAAG</underline>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"><italic>DGA1</italic><sup><italic>Yl</italic></sup> (rev; control)</td>
            <td align="left">
              <underline>CGTTGATAGAAAGAGACCG</underline>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>