<article xmlns="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Conscious Cogn</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Consciousness and Cognition</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1053-8100</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1090-2376</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2842936</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20005133</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">YCCOG1172</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.concog.2009.11.002</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Effects of loss aversion on post-decision wagering: Implications for measures of
         awareness</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fleming</surname>
            <given-names>Stephen M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>s.fleming@fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk</email>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dolan</surname>
            <given-names>Raymond J.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>Wellcome Trust Centre for Neuroimaging, University College London, 12 Queen
               Square, London WC1N 3BG, United Kingdom</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. <email>s.fleming@fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>19</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>352</fpage>
      <lpage>363</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2009</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2010 Elsevier Inc.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2009</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Elsevier Inc.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/authorsview.authors/supplementalterms1.0">certain conditions</ext-link>.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wagering contingent on a previous decision, or post-decision wagering,
               has recently been proposed to measure conscious awareness. Whilst intuitively
               appealing, it remains unclear whether economic context interacts with subjective
               confidence and how such interactions might impact on the measurement of awareness.
               Here we propose a signal detection model which predicts that advantageous wagers
               placed on the identity of preceding stimuli are affected by loss aversion, despite
               stimulus visibility remaining constant. This pattern of predicted results was evident
               in a psychophysical task where we independently manipulated perceptual and economic
               factors. Changes in wagering behaviour induced by changes in wager size were largely
               driven by changes in criterion, consistent with the model. However, for
               near-threshold stimuli, a reduction in wagering efficiency was also evident,
               consistent with an apparent but potentially illusory decrease in awareness of the
               stimulus. These findings challenge an assertion that post-decision wagering provides
               a direct index of subjective awareness.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Post-decision wagering</kwd>
        <kwd>Perception</kwd>
        <kwd>Economics</kwd>
        <kwd>Signal detection theory</kwd>
        <kwd>Reward</kwd>
        <kwd>Awareness</kwd>
        <kwd>Metacognition</kwd>
        <kwd>Psychophysics</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Knowledge of one’s own uncertainty regarding an outcome plays a key role
               in determining decision strategy (<xref rid="bib14 bib17 bib25 bib26 bib48" ref-type="bibr">Foote &amp; Crystal, 2007; Hampton, 2001;
                  Kepecs, Uchida, Zariwala, &amp; Mainen, 2008; Kiani &amp; Shadlen, 2009; Smith,
                  Shields, &amp; Washburn, 2003</xref>), and may even be a central property
               of awareness (<xref rid="bib7 bib9 bib42 bib43" ref-type="bibr">Cleeremans, Timmermans,
                  &amp; Pasquali, 2007; Dienes, 2008; Rosenthal, 2000, 2002</xref>). For
               example, knowing in advance that you are unlikely to pass a test makes you reluctant
               to take the test in the first place (<xref rid="bib19 bib20 bib30 bib34" ref-type="bibr">Higham, 2007; Higham &amp; Gerrard, 2005; Koriat &amp; Goldsmith, 1996; Metcalfe
                  &amp; Finn, 2008</xref>), and may reflect awareness of your own (low)
               ability.</p>
      <p>Such insights motivated the use of wagering contingent on decision performance
               (post-decision wagering) as a direct and intuitive measure of conscious awareness
                  (<xref rid="bib28 bib37 bib38" ref-type="bibr">Koch &amp; Preuschoff, 2007; Persaud
                  &amp; McLeod, 2008; Persaud, McLeod, &amp; Cowey, 2007</xref>). In its
               simplest form, a participant is required to detect whether an arbitrary stimulus is
               present or not and then, in a second stage, gamble on whether his/her response was
               correct or not. Advantageous wagers are made when participants accurately assess the
               level of sensory evidence on each trial, linking objective performance to the
               subjectivity of stimulus information (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Persaud et al.,
                  2007</xref>). Furthermore, using wagers to measure awareness can
               potentially overcome problems of interpretation associated with a lack of control
               over subjective reports (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Eriksen, 1960</xref>)
               and the motivation of a subject (cf. <xref rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">Visser &amp;
                  Merikle, 1999</xref>). However, the interpretation of post-decision
               wagering data is potentially confounded by complex factors affecting how gains and
               losses affect performance (<xref rid="bib8 bib10 bib44" ref-type="bibr">Clifford,
                  Arabzadeh, &amp; Harris, 2008; Dienes &amp; Seth, 2009; Schurger &amp; Sher,
                  2008</xref>), and a full behavioural analysis of advantages, and
               disadvantages, in defining consciousness based on these economic terms is
               lacking.</p>
      <p>The processing stages underlying post-decision wagering can be logically
               decomposed using signal detection theory (SDT). In the first instance, it is assumed
               that objective features of the stimulus lead to a perceptual effect, modelled as a
               univariate random variable <italic>X</italic> (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.
                  1</xref>a), which we label “sensory
               evidence”. Discrimination errors at this stage are inevitable if the difference
               in sensory evidence between signal and noise (or other arbitrary category
               discriminations) is weak, leading to overlapping probability distributions
                  (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>a). It is thus assumed that
               participants make a decision by splicing up an evidence axis into two halves using a
               decision criterion (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Green &amp; Swets,
                  1966</xref>). In a post-decision wagering experiment, the participant is
               now required to make a high or low wager on whether they were correct. This requires
               knowledge both of how likely it was that the first decision was correct, and their
               expected return from the wager (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Clifford et al.,
                  2008</xref>). The former can be recovered from the sensory evidence on a
               given trial (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Galvin, Podd, Drga, &amp; Whitmore,
                  2003</xref>). The latter, however, is psychologically more complex given
               evidence that people are loss averse (<xref rid="bib23 bib52" ref-type="bibr">Kahneman
                  &amp; Tversky, 1979; Tversky &amp; Kahneman, 1991</xref>), manifesting in
               a propensity to weight losses greater than gains when making value-based decisions.
               Loss aversion has been suggested to impact on post-decision wagering performance by
               modulating a link between the assessment of sensory evidence and overt confidence
                  (<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Schurger &amp; Sher, 2008</xref>).</p>
      <p>To quantify how wagering on sensory evidence is influenced by economic factors,
               we first developed a simple computational model of post-decision wagering behaviour,
               building on previous work by Galvin and colleagues (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Galvin et al., 2003</xref>), but now extending this framework to
               encompass loss aversion. Using this model, we derive precise predictions about how
               sensory evidence translates into advantageous wagering responses. The accuracy of
               metacognitive assessments can be intuited as how transparent the initial decision
               process is to a putative “higher” level assessment. For example, if there
               is ambiguity in the decision process then the categorisation of one’s own
               performance as being correct, or incorrect, will be subject to error. This intuition
               can be captured within the logic of signal detection theory (SDT), which assesses how
               faithfully an organism separates signal from noise (<xref rid="bib16 bib33" ref-type="bibr">Green &amp; Swets, 1966; Macmillan &amp; Creelman,
                  2005</xref>). In standard applications of SDT (Type I), detection
               performance is assessed by a comparison of the proportion of “hits” and
               “false alarms” in a stimulus detection task. By applying the logic of SDT
               to post-decision wagering, we categorise a “hit” as a high wager after a
               correct decision and a “false alarm” as a high wager after an incorrect
               decision (see <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). This type of analysis is known as Type II SDT (<xref rid="bib6 bib8 bib15 bib31 bib33" ref-type="bibr">Clarke, Birdsall, &amp; Tanner, 1959; Clifford
                  et al., 2008; Galvin et al., 2003; Kunimoto, Miller, &amp; Pashler, 2001;
                  Macmillan &amp; Creelman, 2005</xref>). On the basis of these
               considerations, we derive a theoretical relationship linking Type I and Type II task
               performance by applying an ideal observer framework, enabling us to explore the
               relationship between post-decision wagering and changes in sensory evidence. Our
               specific prediction here was that post-decision wagering would be influenced by loss
               aversion, decoupling a link between perception and confident responding. To test our
               model, we examine data from a psychophysical experiment in which subjects made a high
               or low wager following a simple sensory judgement.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods" id="sec1">
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec>
        <label>2.1</label>
        <title>Signal detection model</title>
        <p>In signal detection theory (SDT), a Type I decision is based upon
                  overlapping Gaussian probability distributions over a random variable
                     <italic>X</italic>, conditional on the events signal
                     (<italic>S</italic>) and noise (<italic>N</italic>) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>a). Assuming an unbiased response criterion,
                     <italic>c</italic>, for the Type I detection decision (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Galvin et al., 2003</xref>), we can specify the
                  distribution over <italic>X</italic> for the probability of the Type I
                  response being correct or incorrect:<disp-formula id="fd1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="{"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>⩽</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="fd2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="{"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>⩽</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where
                     <italic>p</italic>(<italic>C</italic>) and
                     <italic>p</italic>(<italic>I</italic>) are the average
                  probabilities of making a correct or incorrect response on any given trial
                     (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Macmillan &amp; Creelman, 2005</xref>).
                  Full derivations of Eqs. <xref rid="fd1 fd2" ref-type="disp-formula">(1) and
                     (2)</xref> can be found in (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Galvin et al.,
                     2003</xref>); the (constant) prior terms from their more general
                  analysis are omitted here for clarity. The distributions specified by
                     <xref rid="fd1 fd2" ref-type="disp-formula">(1) and (2)</xref> are plotted
                  graphically in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>b. It is important
                  to note that these Type II distributions are conditional transformations based on
                  whether the first decision was correct or not. That is, the shape of the
                     <italic>f</italic>(<italic>x</italic>|<italic>C</italic>)
                  curve follows the signal distribution when <italic>x</italic> &gt; <italic>c</italic> (a Type I hit) and
                  the noise distribution when <italic>x</italic> &lt; <italic>c</italic> (a Type I correct rejection). Similarly,
                  the shape of the
                     <italic>f</italic>(<italic>x</italic>|<italic>I</italic>)
                  curve follows shape of the noise distribution when <italic>x</italic> &gt; <italic>c</italic> (a Type I false
                  alarm) and the signal distribution when <italic>x</italic> &lt; <italic>c</italic> (a Type I miss). The heights
                  of both
                  <italic>f</italic>(<italic>x</italic>|<italic>C</italic>) and
                     <italic>f</italic>(<italic>x</italic>|<italic>I</italic>) are
                  then scaled so that they sum to one.</p>
        <p>A correct Type II response is more likely towards the left or right-hand
                  extremes of <italic>X</italic> in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.
                     1</xref>b (high signal or high noise trials), whereas incorrect
                  responses predominate where there is maximal overlap between signal and noise. The
                  inherent assumption here is that the uncertainty associated with being sure of
                  seeing something is the same as the uncertainty associated with being sure of not
                  seeing something (the Type II distributions are symmetric around
                     <italic>X</italic> = 0), an
                  assumption we return to under Sections <xref rid="sec2 sec3" ref-type="sec">3 and
                     4</xref>.</p>
        <p>The log-likelihood of being correct on any given trial (likelihood ratio;
                     <italic>LR</italic>) is the log of the ratio of <xref rid="fd1 fd2" ref-type="disp-formula">(1) and
                           (2)</xref>:<disp-formula><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si3.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">LR</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">log</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
        <p>We assume that high wagers are made when the log-likelihood of being correct
                  on the Type I task reaches a given criterion,
                     <italic>β<sub>w</sub></italic>. As the likelihood ratio is
                  symmetric around <italic>c</italic>, there are thus two values of
                     <italic>x</italic> for each
                     <italic>β<sub>w</sub></italic>, one for when
                     <italic>x</italic> ⩽ <italic>c</italic> and one for when <italic>x</italic> &gt; <italic>c</italic>. This corresponds to
                  being sure that a signal was or was not present and wagering high.</p>
        <p>In standard applications of SDT, the optimal placement of the log-likelihood
                  ratio criterion can be calculated based on the relative utility of making a hit
                     (<italic>H</italic>), miss (<italic>M</italic>), correct rejection
                     (<italic>CR</italic>) or false alarm (<italic>FA</italic>)
                  (assuming equal priors), as follows (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Macmillan &amp;
                     Creelman, 2005</xref>):<disp-formula id="fd7"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si4.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">log</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CR</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">FA</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
        <p>In Type I SDT, it is likely that the “reward” (R) for a false
                  alarm or miss will be negative. Imagine taking part in a psychophysical task where
                  the penalty was £1 for a false alarm and 1p for a miss, with 10p earned for
                  correct responses. The optimal value of <italic>β</italic> would then
                  be (0.1 − (−1))/(0.1 − (−0.01)) = 10: the odds favouring stimulus <italic>B</italic> should be
                  10:1 or better in order to risk a “<italic>B</italic>” response
                  (that associated with the false alarm penalty). In our Type II analysis, we
                  similarly assume that subjects base their response criterion,
                        <italic>β<sub>w</sub></italic>, on the relative utility of
                  the four possible Type II wagering outcomes, which are mapped onto the four SDT
                  categories of Eq. <xref rid="fd7" ref-type="disp-formula">(4)</xref> using <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. This ratio is then adjusted by the prior
                  probability of the trial being correct or incorrect
                     (<italic>P</italic>(<italic>C</italic>) and
                     <italic>P</italic>(<italic>I</italic>)):<disp-formula id="fd9"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si5.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">log</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
        <p>In contrast to Eq. <xref rid="fd7" ref-type="disp-formula">(4)</xref> for Type I
                  SDT, in Eq. <xref rid="fd9" ref-type="disp-formula">(5)</xref> both hits and misses are
                  associated with positive outcomes (trials are labelled “misses” when
                  the Type I response was correct but only the low wager was used, leading to a
                  lower reward than could have been obtained, but still a reward; cf. <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Kunimoto et al., 2001</xref>). Thus, the terms in the
                  denominator of Eq. <xref rid="fd9" ref-type="disp-formula">(5)</xref> are the positive
                  utilities of each wager (<italic>R</italic>), whereas the outcomes in the
                  numerator are associated with the negative costs of losing each wager
                     (<italic>C</italic>) following incorrect responses.</p>
        <p>Crucially, we incorporate asymmetric utility curves when calculating the
                  values of <italic>R</italic> and <italic>C</italic>, as proposed
                  within Prospect Theory (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Kahneman &amp; Tversky,
                     1979</xref>). A schematic of such a curve is shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>c. Risk aversion for mixed (gain or loss)
                  gambles is explained through loss aversion, such that given the same absolute
                  value losses carry a greater impact than gains (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Tversky &amp; Kahneman, 1991</xref>). This nonlinear relationship
                  between gain (<italic>R</italic>) and loss (<italic>C</italic>) leads
                  to a value of <italic>β<sub>w</sub></italic> that is dependent on
                  the size of the high wager, assuming the low wager remains fixed for
                  simplicity.</p>
        <p>The positive and negative utility of each wager is specified as
                           follows:<disp-formula><label>(6)</label><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>R</italic> = <italic>V</italic><sup><italic>r</italic></sup>, <italic>V</italic> &gt; 0</textual-form><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si6.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula><label>(7)</label><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>C</italic> = <italic>s</italic>( - <italic>V</italic>)<sup><italic>t</italic></sup>, <italic>V</italic> &lt; 0</textual-form><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si7.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mtext>,</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula>where
                     <italic>V</italic> is the objective value of the wager,
                     <italic>r</italic> and <italic>t</italic> are power functions for
                  the gain and loss domain respectively, and <italic>s</italic> is the loss
                  aversion index. We restricted <italic>r</italic> and
                     <italic>t</italic> such that 0 &lt; <italic>r</italic> &lt; <italic>t</italic> &lt; 1,
                  resulting in utility being concave for gains, convex for losses and more linear in
                  losses than in gains (<xref rid="bib13 bib27" ref-type="bibr">Fennema &amp; Van Assen,
                     1999; Kobberling &amp; Wakker, 2005</xref>). We define
                     <italic>c</italic> ± <italic>m</italic> (as the likelihood ratio is symmetric about
                     <italic>c</italic>) as values of <italic>x</italic> such
                           that:<disp-formula><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si8.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">log</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
        <p>Using the signal detection categories of <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table
                     1</xref>, we then compute theoretical hit and false alarm rates for a
                  range of values of <italic>m</italic> by integrating over the Type II
                  probability distributions specified in <xref rid="fd1 fd2" ref-type="disp-formula">(1),
                     (2)</xref> and <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig.
                        1</xref>b:<disp-formula id="fd13"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si9.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dx</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dx</mml:mi></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="fd14"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si10.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">FA</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dx</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dx</mml:mi></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <label>2.2</label>
        <title>Psychophysics</title>
        <p>Thirteen participants (3 male, 10 female, mean age 27 ± 8.6 years) performed a lexical
                  decision task spread over two sessions on consecutive days, each contributing 1440
                  trials to the analysis. The task was to decide whether a heavily masked stimulus
                  was a word or a non-word, and then to gamble either “high” or
                  “low” depending on the correctness of their initial judgement
                     (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). One-hundred and seventy-two four-letter words were taken from the MRC
                  Psycholinguistic Database (<xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">Wilson,
                  1988</xref>), and matched for familiarity and written frequency of
                  occurrence. A related set of pronounceable non-words was created by a random vowel
                  change. To increase task difficulty, stimuli appeared randomly at any one of four
                  locations surrounding a central fixation point. Threshold detection performance
                  (79%) was assessed for each individual using a staircase procedure (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Levitt, 1971</xref>); on each trial stimulus duration was
                  100%, 80% or 50% of this threshold. The low wager remained constant across blocks
                  at 50p; the value of the high wager varied across blocks (£1, £2,
                  £5 or £10). Responses were made using the left-hand
                     (“<italic>z</italic>” or
                  “<italic>x</italic>” keys) to indicate the word/non-word, and
                  the right-hand (“up” or “down” arrow keys) to indicate a
                  high or low gamble.</p>
        <p>Stimulus duration was randomised within blocks, giving a 3 × 4 factorial design crossing high wager size
                  (£1, £2, £5 or £10) with stimulus visibility (100%, 80% or
                  50% of threshold duration). This design allowed us to recover an estimate of
                  advantageous wagering (proportion of high wagers following correct responses;
                  “hits” in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) for each
                  cell in our design.</p>
        <p>Participants were informed that the wager they were making was a true mixed
                  gamble: they would win the money they wagered if their initial word/non-word
                  decision was correct, and would have this amount deducted from their running total
                  if they were incorrect. They were also informed that only one trial from each
                  block was to be evaluated at random, allowing us to use relatively larger amounts
                  of money while still encouraging participants to treat each trial as a meaningful
                  gamble.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <label>2.3</label>
        <title>Analysis</title>
        <p>To quantify a match between the psychophysical data and the model, we
                  computed the likelihood of each subject’s wagers under the model (from the
                  integrals in Eqs. <xref rid="fd13 fd14" ref-type="disp-formula">(9) and (10)</xref>),
                  optimised over free parameters of the utility function. We compared two
                  parameterisations of the utility function: one with, and one without, a loss
                  aversion constant (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Tversky &amp; Kahneman,
                     1991</xref>). We took the parameters <italic>r</italic>,
                     <italic>t</italic> and <italic>s</italic> to be free in Model 1
                  (loss averse + power), and
                     <italic>r</italic> and <italic>t</italic> to be free in Model 2
                  (power). The testable model space was constrained by requiring the loss and gain
                  domains of the utility function to be asymmetric, as symmetric functions do not
                  predict any effect of wager size on the Type II response criterion (see
                     <xref rid="app1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Material</xref> for a more
                  detailed discussion of empirical forms of the utility curve).</p>
        <p>Type I sensitivity was set for each level of stimulus visibility using
                  empirically estimated <italic>d</italic>′ values from each subject.
                  For each model, we fit the free parameters to each participant’s choice data
                  by maximising the likelihood of the observed choices, using a nonlinear
                  optimisation algorithm (<italic>fminsearch</italic> in the Matlab
                  Optimisation toolbox). We report negative log-likelihoods (smaller values indicate
                  better fit), penalised for model complexity using the Bayesian information
                  criterion (BIC) (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Schwarz, 1978</xref>). To
                  compare models at the group level we summed each subject’s BIC, resulting in
                  a log group Bayes factor (<xref rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">Stephan, Weiskopf, Drysdale,
                     Robinson, &amp; Friston, 2007</xref>).</p>
        <p>For signal detection analysis, Type I “word” responses were
                  classified as hits or false alarms; “non-word” responses were
                  classified as correct rejections or misses. For both the model and the data we
                  computed Type II hit and false alarm rates using the classification scheme of
                     <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. To allow comparison with
                  previous datasets employing post-decision wagering (<xref rid="bib37 bib38" ref-type="bibr">Persaud &amp; McLeod, 2008; Persaud et al.,
                     2007</xref>), advantageous wagers were defined as Type II hit rates
                  (proportion of high gambles made after correct decisions). A repeated-measures
                  analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to analyse these proportions, following an
                  arcsine transformation of the data to correct for heterogeneity of variance. In
                  addition Type I SDT measures of the initial perceptual discrimination
                     (<italic>d</italic>′ and <italic>c</italic>) and Type II
                  sensitivity (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" altimg="si11.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>)
                  and criterion (<italic>c<sub>w</sub></italic>) for the wagering
                  response were calculated as follows (where <italic>z</italic> is the inverse
                  of the cumulative normal distribution
                           function):<disp-formula><label>(11)</label><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>d</italic><sup>′</sup> = <italic>z</italic>(<italic>H</italic>) - <italic>z</italic>(<italic>F</italic>)</textual-form><mml:math id="M12" altimg="si12.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula><label>(12)</label><mml:math id="M13" altimg="si13.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula><label>(13)</label><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>c</italic> =  - 0.5[<italic>z</italic>(<italic>H</italic>) + <italic>z</italic>(<italic>F</italic>)]</textual-form><mml:math id="M14" altimg="si14.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula><label>(14)</label><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup"><italic>c</italic><sub><italic>w</italic></sub> =  - 0.5[<italic>z</italic>(<italic>H</italic><sub><italic>w</italic></sub>) + <italic>z</italic>(<italic>F</italic><sub><italic>w</italic></sub>)]</textual-form><mml:math id="M15" altimg="si15.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="[" close="]"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula>0.5
                  was added to all cells in calculation of both Type I and Type II SDT measures to
                  avoid extreme proportions of <italic>H</italic> or <italic>F</italic>
                     (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Hautus, 1995</xref>). SDT measures
                  calculated for each wager and sensitivity condition were analysed using
                  repeated-measures ANOVAs.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2">
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec>
        <label>3.1</label>
        <title>Model comparison</title>
        <p>As an initial examination of the validity of our model, we computed
                  estimates of advantageous wagering (the proportion of high wagers following
                  correct responses) from both the model output and psychophysical data
                     (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>a and b). Perceptual sensitivity levels in the model were set to match mean
                     <italic>d</italic>′ values across subjects in the psychophysical
                  experiment. It is clear that advantageous wagering is predicted not only to
                  increase as a function of perceptual sensitivity, but also to decrease as a
                  function of wager size. The latter decrease is a direct consequence of the
                  loss-averse utility function implemented in the model.</p>
        <p>We next tested the model predictions against psychophysical data.
                  Advantageous wagering decreased with both decreasing stimulus visibility (effect
                  of visibility; <italic>F</italic><sub>(2,24)</sub> = 99.87, <italic>p</italic> &lt; .0001) and with increasing wager size (effect of
                  wager; <italic>F</italic><sub>(3,36)</sub> = 10.71, <italic>p </italic>&lt; .0001; Fig. 3b), closely matching the predictions of the model
                     (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>a). Even when the stimulus was
                  most visible, the size of the wager significantly modulated a tendency to gamble
                  high following correct responses (paired <italic>t</italic>-test between
                  £1 and £10 wagers;
                     <italic>t</italic><sub>(12)</sub> = 3.90, <italic>p </italic>= .002). Indeed, for the range of stimulus durations we tested here, the effect of
                  wager size did not interact with stimulus visibility
                     (<italic>F</italic><sub>(6,72)</sub> &lt; 1, <italic>p </italic>&gt; .5).</p>
        <p>In assessing the match between the psychophysical results and the model, we
                  compared two parameterisations of the utility function: one with a loss aversion
                  constant (<xref rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">Tversky &amp; Kahneman, 1991</xref>)
                  and one without. The model with the loss aversion constant was strongly preferred,
                  despite the Bayesian information criterion (BIC) measure including a penalty for
                  additional complexity (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>c; BIC
                  difference of 73.2, corresponding to an
                     <italic>e</italic><sup>73.2</sup> difference in Bayes factor). This
                  suggests the transformation of perceptual sensitivity into confident wagering was
                  indeed significantly affected by the loss aversion parameter of the model. The
                  average utility function adopted by participants is shown in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>d. Across subjects, the loss aversion
                  parameter <italic>s</italic> ranged from 1.94 to 4.53, with a mean of
                     2.74 ± 0.92. Such a parameter range
                  is comparable with previous findings in the literature (<xref rid="bib51 bib52" ref-type="bibr">Tom, Fox, Trepel, &amp; Poldrack, 2007; Tversky &amp;
                     Kahneman, 1991</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <label>3.2</label>
        <title>Type I signal detection analysis</title>
        <p>As expected, longer stimulus durations were associated with higher Type I
                     <italic>d</italic>′
                     (<italic>F</italic><sub>(2,24)</sub> = 123.47, <italic>p </italic>&lt; .0001). Importantly, however, Type I perceptual sensitivity remained
                  constant across changes in wager size (interaction of wager size and visibility:
                     <italic>F</italic><sub>(6,72)</sub> = 1.07, <italic>p </italic>&gt; .3; <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a). As outlined in Section <xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">2</xref>, an explicit assumption of our model is that Type I response
                  criteria are unbiased. To evaluate this assumption we calculated Type I criterion
                  for the word/non-word discrimination as a function of both stimulus visibility and
                  wager size (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>b). A consistent bias
                  towards responding “word” for the higher visibility trials was
                  observed, leading to a significant effect of visibility on response criterion
                     (<italic>F</italic><sub>(2,24)</sub> = 23.48, <italic>p </italic>&lt; .0001). However, as for <italic>d</italic>′, this bias
                  was expressed consistently across changes in wager size (no interaction with wager
                  size; <italic>F</italic><sub>(6,72)</sub> = 1.31, <italic>p </italic>&gt; .2), suggesting that these criterion shifts are not sufficient to
                  explain biases in post-decision wagering induced by loss aversion.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <label>3.3</label>
        <title>Type II signal detection analysis</title>
        <p>The results described under Model Comparison above show that a typical
                  post-decision wagering measure – Type II hit rate – is subject to a
                  bias that can be explained by loss aversion, despite the underlying Type I
                  sensitivity to the stimulus remaining constant. However, participants’
                  wagering efficiency (ability to discriminate between correct and incorrect trials)
                  might still be independent of their overall propensity to wager high
                     (<xref rid="bib19 bib31" ref-type="bibr">Higham, 2007; Kunimoto et al.,
                     2001</xref>; but see <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Evans &amp;
                     Azzopardi, 2007</xref>). In other words, despite using the £10
                  wager less than the £1 wager for a given level of sensitivity (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>b), does this usage still discriminate well
                  between correct and incorrect decisions?</p>
        <p>To answer this question we computed Type II measures of wagering efficiency,
                     <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" altimg="si16.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>,
                  and wagering criterion, <italic>c<sub>w</sub></italic> (see Section
                     <xref rid="sec1" ref-type="sec">2</xref>) from both model and psychophysics
                  data, as a function of stimulus visibility and wager size (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>a and b). The
                  model predicts that wager size should primarily affect
                        <italic>c<sub>w</sub></italic> (due to loss aversion), without
                  affecting <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" altimg="si17.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>,
                  which is a function of Type I <italic>d</italic>′ (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>a; left-hand panel). The data indeed showed a
                  strong main effect of wager size on <italic>c<sub>w</sub></italic>
                     (<italic>F</italic><sub>(2,24)</sub> = 45.87, <italic>p </italic>&lt; .0001), which did not interact with stimulus visibility
                     (<italic>F</italic><sub>(6,72)</sub> = 0.56, <italic>p </italic>&gt; .7), in agreement with the model (right-hand panel of <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>b). The model also predicts a main effect of
                  stimulus visibility on <italic>c<sub>w</sub></italic>, in that
                  wagering is generally more conservative when the task is more difficult
                     (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>a, right-hand panel), an
                  effect borne out in the data
                     (<italic>F</italic><sub>(3,36)</sub> = 8.93, <italic>p </italic>&lt; .005).</p>
        <p>The match between the model and the data on <inline-formula><mml:math id="M18" altimg="si18.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
                  was less consistent. As predicted, we found a main effect of stimulus visibility
                     (<italic>F</italic><sub>(2,24)</sub> = 7.78, <italic>p </italic>&lt; .005; <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>a), which did
                  not show any significant interactions with wager size
                     (<italic>F</italic><sub>(6,72)</sub> = 1.78, <italic>p </italic>&gt; .1). However, for the lowest visibility, we noted a downward trend
                  in <inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" altimg="si19.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
                  as wager size increased, reflected in a linear effect of wager size that
                  interacted with visibility level
                     (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,12)</sub> = 8.66, <italic>p </italic>= .012). Indeed, when comparing participants’ sensitivity to their own
                  correctness in low-visibility judgements for £1 and £10 wager blocks,
                     <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20" altimg="si20.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
                  dropped by almost half (from 0.91 to 0.50). To ensure that these effects were not
                  stimulus-specific (cf. <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Higham, Perfect, &amp; Bruno,
                     2009</xref>; Experiment 3), we reanalysed the low-visibility condition
                  as a function of whether the stimulus was a word or non-word (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). A main
                  effect of wager size on <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21" altimg="si21.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
                  was confirmed (<italic>F</italic><sub>(3,36)</sub> = 3.95, <italic>p </italic>= .016) which did not interact with stimulus type
                     (<italic>F</italic><sub>(3,36)</sub> &lt; 1). A main effect of stimulus type was also found
                     (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,12)</sub> = 34.4, <italic>p </italic>&lt; .001), replicating <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Higham et al.’s
                     (2009)</xref> findings that monitoring is worse for distractors
                  (non-words in our task) than targets (words). Overall, our results show that the
                  size of the wager largely affects the criterion for using the high-wager response,
                  but for near-threshold stimuli, also affects metacognitive performance.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <label>3.4</label>
        <title>Test of model assumptions</title>
        <p>An inherent assumption of our model is that the wagering criterion
                     (<italic>m</italic> in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>b)
                  is symmetric about <italic>c</italic>. In other words, it is assumed that
                  the same degree of loss aversion leads to similar wagering behaviour following
                  reports of both signal and noise trials. It is possible that these criteria
                        (<italic>c </italic>+ <italic>m</italic> and <italic>c</italic> − <italic>m</italic>) are independently
                  specified; for example, it may be easier to be sure of seeing something than to be
                  sure of not seeing something. To examine such effects, we split <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" altimg="si22.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
                  and <italic>c<sub>w</sub></italic> by whether the first response had
                  been “word” or “non-word” (equivalent to calculating
                  separate hit and false alarm rates for the left- and right-hand sides of the
                  distributions in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>b). These were
                  entered into a 2 (Type I response) × 3
                     (visibility) × 4 (wager size) ANOVA.
                  A robust main effect of Type I response on
                     <italic>C<sub>w</sub></italic> was found
                     (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,12)</sub> = 37.3, <italic>p </italic>&lt; .0001), which was driven by a more conservative criterion for
                  wagering following non-word (mean <italic>c<sub>w</sub> </italic>= 0.60) compared to word responses (mean
                        <italic>c<sub>w</sub> </italic>= −0.16). Importantly, however, this dependence of
                        <italic>c<sub>w</sub></italic> on the initial decision was
                  highly consistent across both wager size (interaction with wager size;
                     <italic>F</italic><sub>(2,24)</sub> &lt; 1, <italic>p </italic>&gt; .9) and changes in stimulus visibility
                     (<italic>F</italic><sub>(3,36)</sub> &lt; 1, <italic>p </italic>&gt; .6), indicative of a stable baseline shift that does not affect the experimental
                  manipulations of interest. In addition, we confirmed that the effects of wager
                  size on <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" altimg="si23.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
                  and <italic>c<sub>w</sub></italic> (reported in Section 3.3) were not
                  qualified by interactions with stimulus or Type I response (word/non-word; all
                     <italic>F</italic> &lt; 1).</p>
        <p>Finally, we note that the results presented in <xref rid="fig5 fig6" ref-type="fig">Figs. 5b and 6</xref> are derived from point
                  estimates of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" altimg="si24.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
                  and <italic>c<sub>w</sub></italic>, which in turn rely on the
                  assumption of equal variance Gaussian confidence distributions,
                     <italic>f</italic>(<italic>x</italic>|<italic>C</italic>) and
                     <italic>f</italic>(<italic>x</italic>|<italic>I</italic>)
                     (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Green &amp; Swets, 1966</xref>). In fact,
                  the Type II probability distributions used in the model are known to deviate from
                  these assumptions (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>b;
                     <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Galvin et al., 2003</xref>). Such
                  deviations produce interactions between Type II <italic>d</italic>′
                  and shifts in criterion (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Evans &amp; Azzopardi,
                     2007</xref>). However, we consider it unlikely that our observation of
                  decreasing <inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" altimg="si25.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
                  with wager size is an artefact of a criterion shift, for two reasons. First, the
                  prediction based on the Type II ROC curve is that for higher wagers, more
                  conservative criteria would actually result in slight increases in <inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" altimg="si26.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
                     (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>a, left-hand panel; see also
                     <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Evans &amp; Azzopardi, 2007</xref>). The
                  opposite is seen in the data for low-visibility stimuli (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>b, left-hand panel and <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). Second, the same effects hold when an
                  overall measure of the wagering “error” rate is calculated (overall
                  proportion of false alarms and misses in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table
                     1</xref>). Collapsing over stimulus visibility, greater errors were
                  seen in the usage of a £10 wager (45 ± 5%) than in the usage of a £1 wager (34 ± 3%).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec3">
      <label>4</label>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Measuring conscious awareness is fraught with controversy (<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">Seth, Dienes, Cleeremans, Overgaard, &amp; Pessoa,
                  2008</xref>) where even the simplest of methods, asking for subjective
               reports, is dogged by the conundrum of response bias (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Eriksen, 1960</xref>). Recently, wagering contingent on decision
               performance (post-decision wagering) has been proposed as a direct and intuitive
               measure of conscious awareness (<xref rid="bib28 bib38 bib37" ref-type="bibr">Koch &amp;
                  Preuschoff, 2007; Persaud et al., 2007; Persaud &amp; McLeod,
               2008</xref>). In the present study, we examine how economic factors affect
               wagers placed on perceptual decisions, and consider the theoretical implications our
               results have for post-decision wagering as a measure of subjective
               awareness.</p>
      <p>Our signal detection model, derived from equations developed by <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Galvin et al. (2003)</xref>, defines the transformations of
               noisy sensory evidence into confidence distributions on which wagering responses are
               based. Due to inherent loss aversion (<xref rid="bib23 bib44" ref-type="bibr">Kahneman
                  &amp; Tversky, 1979; Schurger &amp; Sher, 2008</xref>), this model
               predicts that advantageous wagering (Type II hits) on a perceptual event depends on
               the size of the gamble, despite sensory evidence remaining constant. Our
               psychophysics data confirm this pattern of predicted results. Our findings suggest
               that loss aversion is a key modulator of the linkage between perceptual sensitivity
               and confident wagering. This effect was true even for the highest stimulus
               visibility, demonstrating a labile linkage between perception and
               behaviour.</p>
      <p>It is clear from these results that the typical post-decision wagering measure
               – advantageous wagering, or Type II hit rate – is subject to a bias
               induced by loss aversion, despite underlying Type I sensitivity as measured by
               responses to the stimulus remaining constant. Data from a related task requiring
               uncertainty monitoring (a scholastic aptitude test where omission of responses was
               allowed), revealed an analogous reduction in test score when the penalty for
               incorrect answers was increased (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Higham,
                  2007</xref>). Higham went on to show that this reduction was due to more
               conservative Type II response criteria in the high-penalty condition. Similarly, our
               model predicts that the effect of loss aversion on advantageous wagering is largely
               due to a criterion (<italic>c<sub>w</sub></italic>) shift, reducing the
               propensity of the subject to opt for the high wager regardless of whether her first
               response was correct or not. In contrast, Type II wagering efficiency (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M27" altimg="si27.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>;
               the difference between good and bad wagers in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table
                  1</xref>) should remain relatively constant in the face of changing wager
               size. In our psychophysical task, we find predictable effects of the wager size on
               Type II response criteria, but also observe decreases in <inline-formula><mml:math id="M28" altimg="si28.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
               as a function of wager size for near-threshold stimuli. In other words, for the same
               underlying task performance, participants become worse at discriminating between
               their own correct and incorrect responses as wager size increases.</p>
      <p>Previous work has shown that Type II sensitivity and criterion are not in fact
               independent when derived from contingency tables such as <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Evans &amp; Azzopardi,
                  2007</xref>), assuming equal variance Type I distributions (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Galvin et al., 2003</xref>). Indeed, similar (but more
               subtle) increases in sensitivity as a function of wager size were predicted by our
               model (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>a, left panel). However, the
               empirical effect we observe is a <italic>decrease</italic> in <inline-formula><mml:math id="M29" altimg="si29.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
               for near-threshold stimuli as wager size increases (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig.
                  5</xref>b, left panel and <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig.
               6</xref>). What might cause this decrease in wagering efficiency on
               high-wager blocks? It is possible that the prospect of high wagers interferes with
               participants’ performance monitoring on low-visibility (difficult) trials.
               However, this account might also predict decreases in Type I task performance, which
               are not seen in our data. We note that recent evidence suggests that the prospect of
               large rewards (comparable to those used in the present study) causes paradoxical
               performance decrements (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Mobbs et al.,
               2009</xref>; see also <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Baumeister,
                  1984</xref>). Whether such influences of large rewards on behaviour could
               also lead to a reduction in performance monitoring, consistent with the present data,
               is a question that requires further study.</p>
      <sec>
        <label>4.1</label>
        <title>Generation of confidence</title>
        <p>Two inherent assumptions of our model deserve attention in order to
                  illustrate the current limitations of a purely signal detection-based theory of
                  confidence. A first assumption is that the initial sensory judgement is unbiased.
                  Empirically, however, there was a consistent bias towards responding
                  “word” for the medium and high stimulus visibility conditions. As this
                  bias was consistent across wager size, it is unlikely to affect our conclusions
                  regarding the effects of wager size on behaviour. However, it does affect how we
                  characterise the link between underlying stimulus distributions and confidence, an
                  issue we consider below. A second assumption of the model is that the criteria for
                  wagering are symmetrical (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>b). This
                  corresponds to equating the confidence required to wager high for words and
                  non-words. In our behavioural data, we see a more conservative criterion for
                  wagering high following non-word decisions. However, this shift was expressed
                  consistently across conditions, leaving unaffected the main conclusions we infer
                  regarding changes in <italic>c<sub>w</sub></italic> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M30" altimg="si30.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
                  as a function of wager size. In our model, wagering criteria are symmetric because
                  the same utility function is applied to symmetric signal and noise distributions.
                  Within this framework, a baseline difference in wagering criteria may be caused by
                  the variance of the signal (word) distribution being greater than the noise
                  (non-word) distribution, leading to a more prominent
                     <italic>f</italic>(<italic>I</italic>|<italic>x</italic>)
                  distribution following non-word responses and requiring more conservative criteria
                  to maintain a given level of wagering performance. Interestingly, greater signal
                  variance when compared to noise in empirical ROCs has been documented in the
                  memory literature (<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Ratcliff, Sheu, &amp; Gronlund,
                     1992</xref>). However, it is unclear from the present data whether
                  distributional or response factors are the main drivers of the observed asymmetry
                  in wagering criteria.</p>
        <p>These behavioural deviations from the model hint at a deeper issue regarding
                  the relationship between Type I task performance and metacognitive confidence
                     (<xref rid="bib2 bib5 bib21" ref-type="bibr">Baranski &amp; Petrusic, 2001; Busey,
                     Tunnicliff, Loftus, &amp; Loftus, 2000; Higham et al., 2009</xref>).
                  In our signal detection model, probability distributions over the stimulus are
                  assumed to deterministically give rise to Type II confidence distributions,
                  without invoking the notion of intermediate processing stages. <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Higham et al. (2009)</xref> identify this generation of
                  confidence from stimulus distributions as the “direct translation
                  hypothesis”. They empirically tested this hypothesis by varying Type I
                  response criteria in a memory paradigm, noting that Type II sensitivity should be
                  systematically affected if Type I distributions are indeed directly translated
                  into Type II distributions, a conclusion supported by their data (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Higham et al., 2009</xref>; Experiment 3). However,
                  recent human psychophysical data reveal dissociations between objective
                  performance and subjective confidence, suggesting a more complex relationship
                  between Type I and Type II distributions (<xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">Wilimzig,
                     Tsuchiya, Fahle, Einhauser, &amp; Koch, 2008</xref>; see also
                     <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Busey &amp; Arici, 2009</xref>). In
                  addition, reaction time measures suggest that confidence is at least partly
                  determined by additional processing following the decision itself (<xref rid="bib1 bib2" ref-type="bibr">Baranski &amp; Petrusic, 1998, 2001</xref>). In the
                  present study, word–non-word discrimination may be a suboptimal testbed for
                  the direct translation hypothesis, given that the evidence dimension is unlikely
                  to be unitary. For example, some words may be easier to process than others,
                  engendering higher fluency and thus influencing metacognitive assessment
                     (<xref rid="bib24 bib29" ref-type="bibr">Kelley &amp; Lindsay, 1993; Koriat,
                     1993</xref>; <xref rid="bib55a" ref-type="bibr">Winkielman, Halberstadt,
                     Fazendeiro, &amp; Catty, 2006</xref>). Future work is needed examine
                  the empirical form of Type I and Type II distributions under simpler
                  psychophysical conditions.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <label>4.2</label>
        <title>Post-decision wagering and awareness</title>
        <p>What do the present results say about post-decision wagering as a measure of
                  awareness? On a psychological level, the use of advantageous wagering counts (Type
                  II hit rate) is confounded by factors (presumably) external to stimulus awareness
                  (see also <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Dienes &amp; Seth, 2009</xref>). For
                  example, blindsight subject GY was seen to wager high 48% of the time after
                  correct responses to stimuli in his blind hemifield (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Persaud et al., 2007</xref>; p. 257). Persaud and colleagues argue
                  that as this proportion is no better than chance (50%), it is evidence for a lack
                  of awareness. However, it is clear from the model and data we present here that
                  simply altering the size of the wager can manipulate this proportion to be
                  consistent with higher or lower awareness. Application of Type II SDT measures to
                  GYs response counts might be a more convincing demonstration of a lack of
                  awareness (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Persaud et al. (2007)</xref>, their
                     <xref rid="app1" ref-type="sec">Supplementary Table 6</xref>; but see
                     <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Clifford et al. (2008)</xref>). Again,
                  however, this measure is not perfect: we find changes in wager size produced
                  unpredictable effects on <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" altimg="si31.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
                  for the types of near-threshold stimuli often used in consciousness research, and
                  particular forms of the payoff matrix can produce values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" altimg="si32.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
                  consistent with a lack of awareness (<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Clifford et al.,
                     2008</xref>). Further problems arise when making comparisons across
                  subjects, or when comparing patients with controls: in our model fit, loss
                  aversion varied considerably between subjects (and may vary in an even more
                  unpredictable fashion within different patient populations), leading to the
                  interpretation of wagering responses being confounded by individual differences in
                  the subjective utility of the gamble (<xref rid="bib10 bib44" ref-type="bibr">Dienes
                     &amp; Seth, 2009; Schurger &amp; Sher, 2008</xref>). There are obvious
                  instances where the ease of use and nonverbal nature of wagering may outweigh such
                  drawbacks, for instance when measuring awareness in non-human animals and
                  children. In these cases, care should be taken to address potentially illusory
                  changes in awareness caused by economic factors.</p>
        <p>On a philosophical level, even if it is possible to control for the
                  confounding effects of loss aversion, it is unclear whether awareness can be
                  inferred from successful wagering (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Seth,
                     2008</xref>). Recent data demonstrates that adaptive, value-based
                  responses can be made in response to stimuli that are below an objective threshold
                  of awareness (<xref rid="bib40 bib39" ref-type="bibr">Pessiglione et al., 2007,
                     2008</xref>). Indeed, from an economist’s perspective, a
                  post-decision wager is a gamble in which the sensory uncertainty determines the
                  probabilities of winning and losing. Graded changes in either the stimulus or
                  outcome utilities will produce probabilistic changes in wagering behaviour, which
                  may not have obvious mappings to particular states of consciousness. In contrast,
                  explicitly taking into account this graded nature of processing using, for
                  example, direct confidence rating scales may offer more robust means of assessing
                  both objective sensitivity and subjective meta-sensitivity (<xref rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">Szczepanowski &amp; Pessoa, 2007</xref>). In this regard
                  our results emphasise the importance of considering both stimulus and response
                  variables when assessing conscious awareness (<xref rid="bib8 bib12 bib22" ref-type="bibr">Clifford et al., 2008; Evans &amp; Azzopardi, 2007;
                     Hulme, Friston, &amp; Zeki, 2009</xref>).</p>
        <p>In summary, using a combination of signal detection theory and psychophysics
                  we show that the translation of perceptual sensitivity into a post-decision
                  wagering response is systematically affected by economic variables, in this
                  instance by loss aversion. Type II signal detection measures reveal that changes
                  in behaviour induced by changes in wager size are largely driven by changes in
                  criterion, consistent with our model. However, when stimulus visibility is low and
                  wagers are large, a reduction in wagering efficiency is also seen. Indeed, the
                  complex interaction between objective stimulus visibility, wager size and the
                  subsequent willingness to gamble casts doubt on an assertion (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Persaud et al., 2007</xref>) that post-decision wagering
                  is a direct index of subjective awareness, despite its intuitive nature. Such
                  interactions raise intriguing questions for future work into the relationship
                  between stimulus processing, subjective awareness and the generation of
                  metacognitive confidence.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baranski</surname>
              <given-names>J.V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petrusic</surname>
              <given-names>W.M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Probing the locus of confidence judgments: Experiments on the
                           time to determine confidence</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Psychology: Human Perception and
                                 Performance</source>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <year>1998</year>
          <fpage>929</fpage>
          <lpage>945</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9627426</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baranski</surname>
              <given-names>J.V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petrusic</surname>
              <given-names>W.M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Testing architectures of the decision–confidence
                           relation</article-title>
          <source>Canadian Journal of Experimental
                                 Psychology</source>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <year>2001</year>
          <fpage>195</fpage>
          <lpage>206</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11605555</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baumeister</surname>
              <given-names>R.F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Choking under pressure: Self-consciousness and paradoxical
                           effects of incentives on skillful performance</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Personality and Social
                                 Psychology</source>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <year>1984</year>
          <fpage>610</fpage>
          <lpage>620</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6707866</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Busey</surname>
              <given-names>T.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arici</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>On the role of individual items in recognition memory and
                           metacognition: Challenges for signal detection theory</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Psychology: Learning, Memory,
                                 and Cognition</source>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>1123</fpage>
          <lpage>1136</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Busey</surname>
              <given-names>T.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tunnicliff</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Loftus</surname>
              <given-names>G.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Loftus</surname>
              <given-names>E.F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Accounts of the confidence–accuracy relation in
                           recognition memory</article-title>
          <source>Psychonomic Bulletin and Review</source>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <year>2000</year>
          <fpage>26</fpage>
          <lpage>48</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10780019</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Clarke</surname>
              <given-names>F.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Birdsall</surname>
              <given-names>T.G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanner</surname>
              <given-names>W.P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Two types of ROC curves and definition of
                           parameters</article-title>
          <source>Journal of the Acoustical Society of
                                 America</source>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <year>1959</year>
          <fpage>629</fpage>
          <lpage>630</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cleeremans</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Timmermans</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pasquali</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Consciousness and metarepresentation: A computational
                           sketch</article-title>
          <source>Neural Networks</source>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>1032</fpage>
          <lpage>1039</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17904799</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Clifford</surname>
              <given-names>C.W.G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arabzadeh</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harris</surname>
              <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Getting technical about awareness</article-title>
          <source>Trends in Cognitive Sciences</source>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>54</fpage>
          <lpage>58</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18178511</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dienes</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Subjective measures of unconscious knowledge</article-title>
          <source>Progress in Brain Research</source>
          <volume>168</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>49</fpage>
          <lpage>64</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18166385</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dienes, Z., &amp; Seth, A. (2009). Gambling on the unconscious: A
                     comparison of wagering and confidence ratings as measures of awareness in an
                     artificial grammar task. <italic>Consciousness and Cognition</italic>,
                        <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.concog.2009.09.009">doi:10.1016/j.concog.2009.09.009</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eriksen</surname>
              <given-names>C.W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Discrimination and learning without awareness – A
                           methodological survey and evaluation</article-title>
          <source>Psychological Review</source>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <year>1960</year>
          <fpage>279</fpage>
          <lpage>300</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13697142</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Evans</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azzopardi</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of a ‘bias-free’ measure of
                           awareness</article-title>
          <source>Spatial Vision</source>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>61</fpage>
          <lpage>77</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17357716</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fennema</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Van Assen</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Measuring the utility of losses by means of the tradeoff
                           method</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Risk and Uncertainty</source>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <year>1999</year>
          <fpage>277</fpage>
          <lpage>295</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Foote</surname>
              <given-names>A.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Crystal</surname>
              <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Metacognition in the rat</article-title>
          <source>Current Biology</source>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>551</fpage>
          <lpage>555</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17346969</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Galvin</surname>
              <given-names>S.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Podd</surname>
              <given-names>J.V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Drga</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Whitmore</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Type 2 tasks in the theory of signal detectability:
                           Discrimination between correct and incorrect decisions</article-title>
          <source>Psychonomic Bulletin and Review</source>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <year>2003</year>
          <fpage>843</fpage>
          <lpage>876</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15000533</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Green</surname>
              <given-names>D.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Swets</surname>
              <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Signal detection theory and psychophysics</chapter-title>
          <year>1966</year>
          <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hampton</surname>
              <given-names>R.R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rhesus monkeys know when they remember</article-title>
          <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of
                                 Sciences</source>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <year>2001</year>
          <fpage>5359</fpage>
          <lpage>5362</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hautus</surname>
              <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Corrections for extreme proportions and their biasing effects
                           on estimated values of <italic>d</italic>’</article-title>
          <source>Behavior Research Methods Instruments &amp;
                                 Computers</source>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <year>1995</year>
          <fpage>46</fpage>
          <lpage>51</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Higham</surname>
              <given-names>P.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>No special K! A signal detection framework for the strategic
                           regulation of memory accuracy</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Psychology:
                                 General</source>
          <volume>136</volume>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>22</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17324082</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Higham</surname>
              <given-names>P.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gerrard</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Not all errors are created equal: Metacognition and changing
                           answers on multiple-choice tests</article-title>
          <source>Canadian Journal of Experimental
                                 Psychology</source>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <year>2005</year>
          <fpage>28</fpage>
          <lpage>34</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15832630</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Higham</surname>
              <given-names>P.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perfect</surname>
              <given-names>T.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bruno</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Investigating strength and frequency effects in recognition
                           memory using type-2 signal detection theory</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Experimental Psychology: Learning, Memory,
                                 and Cognition</source>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>57</fpage>
          <lpage>80</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib22">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hulme</surname>
              <given-names>O.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Friston</surname>
              <given-names>K.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zeki</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neural correlates of stimulus reportability</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Cognitive Neuroscience</source>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>1602</fpage>
          <lpage>1610</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18823251</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kahneman</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tversky</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prospect Theory – Analysis of decision under
                           risk</article-title>
          <source>Econometrica</source>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <year>1979</year>
          <fpage>263</fpage>
          <lpage>291</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kelley</surname>
              <given-names>C.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lindsay</surname>
              <given-names>D.S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Remembering mistaken for knowing: Ease of retrieval as a basis
                           for confidence in answers to general knowledge questions</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Memory and Language</source>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <year>1993</year>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>24</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib25">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kepecs</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Uchida</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zariwala</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mainen</surname>
              <given-names>Z.F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neural correlates, computation and behavioural impact of
                           decision confidence</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <volume>455</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>227</fpage>
          <lpage>231</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18690210</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib26">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kiani</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shadlen</surname>
              <given-names>M.N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Representation of confidence associated with a decision by
                           neurons in the parietal cortex</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>324</volume>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>759</fpage>
          <lpage>764</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19423820</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib27">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kobberling</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wakker</surname>
              <given-names>P.P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An index of loss aversion</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Economic Theory</source>
          <volume>122</volume>
          <year>2005</year>
          <fpage>119</fpage>
          <lpage>131</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib28">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koch</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Preuschoff</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Betting the house on consciousness</article-title>
          <source>Nature Neuroscience</source>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>140</fpage>
          <lpage>141</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib29">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koriat</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>How do we know what we know? The accessibility model of the
                           feeling of knowing</article-title>
          <source>Psychological Review</source>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <year>1993</year>
          <fpage>609</fpage>
          <lpage>639</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8255951</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib30">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koriat</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldsmith</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Monitoring and control processes in the strategic regulation
                           of memory accuracy</article-title>
          <source>Psychological Review</source>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <year>1996</year>
          <fpage>490</fpage>
          <lpage>517</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8759045</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib31">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kunimoto</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miller</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pashler</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Confidence and accuracy of near-threshold discrimination
                           responses</article-title>
          <source>Consciousness and Cognition</source>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <year>2001</year>
          <fpage>294</fpage>
          <lpage>340</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11697867</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib32">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Levitt</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transformed up–down methods in
                           psychoacoustics</article-title>
          <source>Journal of the Acoustical Society of
                                 America</source>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <year>1971</year>
          <fpage>467</fpage>
          <lpage>477</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5541744</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib33">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Macmillan</surname>
              <given-names>N.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Creelman</surname>
              <given-names>C.D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Detection theory: A user’s guide</chapter-title>
          <year>2005</year>
          <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib34">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Metcalfe</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Finn</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evidence that judgements of learning are causally related to
                           study choice</article-title>
          <source>Psychonomic Bulletin and Review</source>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>174</fpage>
          <lpage>179</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18605499</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib35">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mobbs</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hassabis</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seymour</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marchant</surname>
              <given-names>J.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weiskopf</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dolan</surname>
              <given-names>R.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Choking on the money: Reward-based performance decrements are
                           associated with midbrain activity</article-title>
          <source>Psychological Science</source>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>955</fpage>
          <lpage>962</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19594859</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib36">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Penny</surname>
              <given-names>W.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stephan</surname>
              <given-names>K.E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mechelli</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Friston</surname>
              <given-names>K.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparing dynamic causal models</article-title>
          <source>NeuroImage</source>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <year>2004</year>
          <fpage>1157</fpage>
          <lpage>1172</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15219588</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib37">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Persaud</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McLeod</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Wagering demonstrates subconscious processing in a binary
                           exclusion task</article-title>
          <source>Consciousness and Cognition</source>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>565</fpage>
          <lpage>575</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17572108</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib38">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Persaud</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McLeod</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cowey</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Post-decision wagering objectively measures
                           awareness</article-title>
          <source>Nature Neuroscience</source>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>257</fpage>
          <lpage>261</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib39">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pessiglione</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petrovic</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daunizeau</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Palminteri</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dolan</surname>
              <given-names>R.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frith</surname>
              <given-names>C.D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Subliminal instrumental conditioning demonstrated in the human
                           brain</article-title>
          <source>Neuron</source>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>561</fpage>
          <lpage>567</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18760693</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib40">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pessiglione</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Draganski</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kalisch</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lau</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dolan</surname>
              <given-names>R.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>How the brain translates money into force. A neuroimaging
                           study of subliminal motivation</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>316</volume>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>904</fpage>
          <lpage>906</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17431137</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib41">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ratcliff</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sheu</surname>
              <given-names>C.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gronlund</surname>
              <given-names>S.D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Testing global memory models using ROC curves</article-title>
          <source>Psychological Review</source>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <year>1992</year>
          <fpage>518</fpage>
          <lpage>535</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1502275</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib42">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rosenthal</surname>
              <given-names>D.M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Consciousness, content, and metacognitive
                           judgments</article-title>
          <source>Consciousness and Cognition</source>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <year>2000</year>
          <fpage>203</fpage>
          <lpage>214</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10924239</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib43">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rosenthal</surname>
              <given-names>D.M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>How many kinds of consciousness?</article-title>
          <source>Consciousness and Cognition</source>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <year>2002</year>
          <fpage>653</fpage>
          <lpage>665</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12470629</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib44">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schurger</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sher</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Awareness, loss aversion, and post-decision
                           wagering</article-title>
          <source>Trends in Cognitive Sciences</source>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>209</fpage>
          <lpage>210</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18482859</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib45">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schwarz</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Estimating the dimension of a model</article-title>
          <source>Annals of Statistics</source>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <year>1978</year>
          <fpage>461</fpage>
          <lpage>464</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib46">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seth</surname>
              <given-names>A.K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Post-decision wagering measures metacognitive content, not
                           sensory consciousness</article-title>
          <source>Consciousness and Cognition</source>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>981</fpage>
          <lpage>983</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17588775</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib47">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seth</surname>
              <given-names>A.K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dienes</surname>
              <given-names>Z.n.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cleeremans</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Overgaard</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pessoa</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Measuring consciousness: Relating behavioural and
                           neurophysiological approaches</article-title>
          <source>Trends in Cognitive Sciences</source>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>314</fpage>
          <lpage>321</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18606562</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib48">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shields</surname>
              <given-names>W.E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Washburn</surname>
              <given-names>D.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The comparative psychology of uncertainty monitoring and
                           metacognition</article-title>
          <source>Behavioural and Brain Sciences</source>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <year>2003</year>
          <fpage>317</fpage>
          <lpage>339</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib49">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stephan</surname>
              <given-names>K.E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weiskopf</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Drysdale</surname>
              <given-names>P.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>P.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Friston</surname>
              <given-names>K.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparing hemodynamic models with DCM</article-title>
          <source>NeuroImage</source>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>387</fpage>
          <lpage>401</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17884583</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib50">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Szczepanowski</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pessoa</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fear perception: Can objective and subjective awareness
                           measures be dissociated?</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Vision</source>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>17</lpage>
          <comment>10</comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib51">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tom</surname>
              <given-names>S.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fox</surname>
              <given-names>C.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trepel</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Poldrack</surname>
              <given-names>R.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The neural basis of loss aversion in decision-making under
                           risk</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>315</volume>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>515</fpage>
          <lpage>518</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17255512</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib52">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tversky</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kahneman</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Loss aversion in riskless choice. A reference-dependent
                           model</article-title>
          <source>Quarterly Journal of Economics</source>
          <volume>106</volume>
          <year>1991</year>
          <fpage>1039</fpage>
          <lpage>1061</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib53">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Visser</surname>
              <given-names>T.A.W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Merikle</surname>
              <given-names>P.M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Conscious and unconscious processes: The effects of
                           motivation</article-title>
          <source>Consciousness and Cognition</source>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <year>1999</year>
          <fpage>94</fpage>
          <lpage>113</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10072695</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib54">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wilimzig</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsuchiya</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fahle</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Einhauser</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koch</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spatial attention increases performance but not subjective
                           confidence in a discrimination task</article-title>
          <source>Journal of Vision</source>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>10</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18842078</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib55">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wilson</surname>
              <given-names>M.D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The MRC psycholinguistic database: Machine readable
                           dictionary, version 2</article-title>
          <source>Behavioural Research Methods, Instruments and
                                 Computers</source>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <year>1988</year>
          <fpage>6</fpage>
          <lpage>11</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib55a">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Winkielman</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Halberstadt</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fazendeiro</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Catty</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prototypes are attractive because they are easy on the
                           mind</article-title>
          <source>Psychological Science</source>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>799</fpage>
          <lpage>806</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16984298</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <sec id="app1" sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <label>Appendix A</label>
      <title>Supplementary material</title>
      <p>
        <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="d30e2651">
          <caption>
            <title>Supplementary Material</title>
          </caption>
          <media xlink:href="mmc1.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"/>
        </supplementary-material>
      </p>
    </sec>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We are indebted to Paul Azzopardi for insightful comments on an earlier version of
            this manuscript. We additionally thank Chris Frith, Klaas Stephan and anonymous
            reviewers for helpful suggestions, and Brett Wilkinson for mathematical advice. This
            work was carried out under a Wellcome Trust Programme Grant to RJD and MRC funding
            within the UCL 4 Year PhD in Neuroscience to SMF.</p>
    </ack>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="fig1">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Computational model of post-decision wagering performance. (a)
               Theoretical distributions over a random variable <italic>X</italic>
               (corresponding to an arbitrary stimulus axis) for signal (<italic>S</italic>,
               solid line) and noise (<italic>N</italic>, broken line). (b) Probability
               distributions over different values of <italic>X</italic> for the probability
               of making a correct (solid line) and incorrect (broken line) categorisation. Shaded
               areas represent the integrals specified in Eqs. <xref rid="fd13" ref-type="disp-formula">(9)</xref> (<italic>H</italic><sub>w</sub>, grey) and
                  <xref rid="fd14" ref-type="disp-formula">(10)</xref>
                  (<italic>FA</italic><sub>w</sub>, black). (c) Schematic of the
               loss-averse utility function used in the model.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig2">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Psychophysical task design. Participants were required to detect whether
               a masked stimulus was a word or a non-word, and then place a high or low wager on
               whether their initial response was correct or not. To increase stimulus uncertainty,
               the target and mask could appear at any one of four locations around a central
               fixation cross (not shown).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig3">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Comparison of computational model with psychophysical data. (a)
               Predicted proportions of advantageous wagers (proportion of high wagers following
               correct initial responses) derived from the computational model illustrated in
                  <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, plotted as a function of
               stimulus visibility (low, medium and high) and high wager size. Stimulus visibility
               in the model was set to be equal to the empirically derived mean
                  <italic>d</italic>′ values from the psychophysical task. (b) Mean
               (±SEM) observed proportions of advantageous wagers from 13 subjects in the
               word/non-word detection task. (c) Negative log-likelihoods of the model fits to the
               psychophysical data summed over subjects, penalised for model complexity using
               Bayesian information criterion (BIC). More negative values indicate a better fit,
               with a difference of three indicating strong evidence for one model compared to the
               other (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Penny, Stephan, Mechelli, &amp; Friston,
                  2004</xref>). It can be seen that despite the penalty for an extra
               parameter, the model with the loss aversion constant <italic>s</italic>
               provides a better fit to the data. (d) Utility function created by averaging the
               best-fit parameters from the power + loss averse
               model over subjects.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig4">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Word/non-word task performance. Subjects’ performance
                  (<italic>d</italic>′) (a) and criterion (b) in the Type I detection
               task as a function of both visibility and wager size. Error bars reflect standard
               errors of the mean.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr4"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig5">
      <label>Fig. 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Type II signal detection analysis of wagering responses. (a) Predictions
               from the model output for the pattern of signal detection parameters (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" altimg="si33.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>,
               left-hand panel; <italic>c<sub>w</sub></italic>, right-hand panel)
               calculated using <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Wagering
               efficiency (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M34" altimg="si34.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>)
               is expected to change as a function of Type I <italic>d</italic>′, but
               only slightly as a function of wager size; the wagering criterion
                     (<italic>c<sub>w</sub></italic>) is expected to be affected by both
               wager size and Type I <italic>d</italic>′. (b) Type II signal detection
               parameters from the post-decision wagering task as a function of stimulus visibility
               and wager size. Error bars reflect standard errors of the mean.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr5"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig6">
      <label>Fig. 6</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Type II sensitivity (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M35" altimg="si35.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>)
               for near-threshold stimuli as a function of wager size and stimulus type
               (word/non-word). A significant effect of wager size on <inline-formula><mml:math id="M36" altimg="si36.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
               was found that did not interact with stimulus type. Monitoring of performance
               following responses to words (targets) was increased compared to monitoring of
               responses to non-words (distractors). Error bars reflect standard errors of the
               mean.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr6"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Categorisation of subjects’ wagering responses for a Type II
               signal detection analysis.</p>
      </caption>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>