<article xmlns="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biochim Biophys Acta</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0006-3002</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier Pub. Co</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3082049</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21074514</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">BBAMEM80419</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamem.2010.10.017</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Functional analysis of the conserved hydrophobic gate region of the magnesium transporter CorA</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Svidová</surname>
            <given-names>Soňa</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sponder</surname>
            <given-names>Gerhard</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schweyen</surname>
            <given-names>Rudolf J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
          <xref rid="fn0005" ref-type="fn">†</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Djinović-Carugo</surname>
            <given-names>Kristina</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>kristina.djinovic@univie.ac.at</email>
          <xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
          <xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
          <xref rid="cr0005" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="af0005"><label>a</label>Department of Microbiology, Immunobiology and Genetics, Max F. Perutz Laboratories, University of Vienna, Dr. Bohrgasse 9/4, A-1030 Vienna, Austria</aff>
      <aff id="af0010"><label>b</label>Department for Structural and Computational Biology, Max F. Perutz Laboratories, University of Vienna, Campus Vienna Biocenter 5, A-1030 Vienna, Austria</aff>
      <aff id="af0015"><label>c</label>Department of Biochemistry, Faculty of Chemistry and Chemical Technology, University of Ljubljana, Ljubljana, Slovenia</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cr0005"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. Campus Vienna Biocenter 5, A-1030 Vienna, Austria. Tel.: + 43 1 4277 52203/52201; fax: + 43 1 4277 9522. <email>kristina.djinovic@univie.ac.at</email></corresp>
        <fn id="fn0005">
          <label>†</label>
          <p>Deceased on 15th of February 2009.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>1808</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>1587</fpage>
      <lpage>1591</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2011 Elsevier B.V.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Elsevier B.V.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/authorsview.authors/supplementalterms1.0">certain conditions</ext-link>.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Leu294 residue in the cytoplasmic neck of <italic>Thermotoga maritima</italic> CorA is considered to be the main gate for Mg<sup>2+</sup> transport. We created three site-directed mutants at this position: in the Leu294Asp and Leu294Gly mutants we observed a defect in closing of the pore, while in the Leu294Arg mutant not only gating, but also the regulation of Mg<sup>2+</sup> uptake was affected. Our results confirmed the importance of the Leu294 for gating of Mg<sup>2+</sup> transport and in addition revealed the influence of the charge and structural features of the amino acid residues on the gating mechanism.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract abstract-type="graphical">
        <title>Research highlights</title>
        <p>► Mutational study of the ion gate of Mg<sup>2+</sup> transporter CorA. ► Effect of exchange of Leu294 with a positively charged residue on gating of CorA (Leu294Arg mutant). ► Effect of exchange of Leu294 with a negatively charged residue on gating of CorA (Leu294Asp mutant). ► Effect of removal of side chain at position 294 on gating of CorA (Leu294Gly mutant).</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>CorA</kwd>
        <kwd>Magnesium transport</kwd>
        <kwd>Hydrophobic gate</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Thermotoga maritima</italic>
        </kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Magnesium transporters of the CorA family are widely distributed amongst Eubacteria and Archaea. The CorA gene encodes a constitutively expressed integral membrane protein <xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Previous investigations showed that it is essential for bacterial growth <xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> but standard rich media provide sufficient magnesium concentrations for growth <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In the last years three crystal structures of <italic>Thermotoga maritima</italic> CorA have been published <xref rid="bb0020 bb0025 bb0030" ref-type="bibr">[4–6]</xref>. All showed that the transporter exists in a pentameric form, consisting of a cytosolic funnel shaped part, linked to the transmembrane region by long α7 helices (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>a, b). The pore is formed by the first trans-membrane helices and surrounded by the second trans-membrane helices, which anchor the complex in the membrane and end in a highly conserved positively charged motif (KKKKWL) called “basic sphincter”. In the cytoplasmic neck of the pore a hydrophobic ring is created by residues Leu294 and Met291, surrounded by the aforementioned basic sphincter (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>c). This concentration of positive charges and the significant conservation of the bulky hydrophobic residues at positions 291 and 294 in the CorA protein family is considered to be of high importance for gating of Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions. Opening and closing of the gate is most probably regulated by interaction of the Mg<sup>2+</sup> ion with a divalent cation sensing site (DCS), placed between Asp89 in the α3 helix in the N-terminal part of one monomer and Asp253 of the α7 helix of the adjacent monomer <xref rid="bb0020 bb0025 bb0030" ref-type="bibr">[4–6]</xref> (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>b). A second DCS site, involving residues Glu88 and Asp175, was identified by Eshaghi et al. <xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref> and Payandeh et al. <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>b).</p>
      <p>The exact gating mechanism of the TmCorA transporter could not been revealed yet. It has been proposed that binding of the Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions to the DCS sites evokes a structural rearrangement of the cytosolic domain causing positively charged residues of the basic sphincter to close the pore by drawing the negative charges away from the middle of the pore, and thereby preventing the positively charged Mg<sup>2+</sup> ion to pass. Removal of Mg<sup>2+</sup> from the DCS sites would cause a movement of the N-terminal domain, resulting in drawing the basic sphincter away from the neck of the pore and allowing the Mg<sup>2+</sup> ion to pass <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. According to the recently performed 110-ns molecular-dynamics simulations, based on the CorA structures published by Eshaghi et al. <xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref> and Payandeh et al. <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, the binding or unbinding of Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions to the DCS sites evokes structural rearrangements of the cytosolic domains and the α7 helices transmit these changes to the gate region causing closing or widening of the pore <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Leu294 in the hydrophobic ring is the critical residue for Mg<sup>2+</sup> gating. It creates a strong energetic barrier for ion permeation and probably controls the movement of Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions indirectly through the movement of water. According to Payandeh et al. <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, not only an energetic, but also a mechanic barrier can influence the uptake of Mg<sup>2+</sup> and “opening sensitivity” of the transporter. To investigate this hypothesis in more detail, this mutational study was focused on Leu294 which was mutated to 15 different amino acids using random PCR mutagenesis. After a preliminary screen, three of these mutants representing different types of amino acids: positively charged hydrophilic arginine, negatively charged hydrophilic aspartic acid and small neutral glycine, were chosen for closer investigations.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s0010">
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="s0015">
        <label>2.1</label>
        <title>Bacterial strains, growth media and genetic procedures</title>
        <p><italic>Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium</italic> strain LB5010 was used as wild-type reference.</p>
        <p><italic>Salmonella enterica serovar Typhimurium strain</italic> MM281 (DEL485 (leuBCD)mgtB::MudJ;mgtA21::MudJ;corA45::mudJ;zjh1628::Tn10(cam) Cam<sup>R</sup>, Kan<sup>R</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup> dependent) was kindly provided by M.E. Maguire. It lacks all major magnesium transport systems <italic>CorA</italic>, <italic>MgtA</italic> and <italic>MgtB</italic> and requires Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentrations in millimolar range for growth.</p>
        <p>Strains were grown in LB medium (10 g tryptone, 5 g yeast extract, 10 g NaCl per liter) with ampicillin (100 μg/ml). MM281 required addition of 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>.</p>
        <p>LB plates contained 2% Difco™ Agar Noble, minimizing possible Mg<sup>2+</sup> contamination.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0020">
        <label>2.2</label>
        <title>Plasmid constructs</title>
        <p>The <italic>Thermotoga maritima</italic> CorA coding sequence was kindly provided by S. Eshaghi and used as template for PCR. The sequence was amplified using the following primers: TmCorwoSfw 5′-CGCGGATCCGAGGAAAA-GAGGCTGTCTGC-3′ and TmCorrev 5′-TCCCCCGGGTCACAGCCACTTCTTT-TTCTTG-3′. The 1035 bp PCR product was cut with BamHI and SmaI restriction enzymes and cloned into the pQE80L vector with an IPTG-inducible promoter.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0025">
        <label>2.3</label>
        <title>Random PCR mutagenesis</title>
        <p>In order to introduce various amino acid substitutions in CorA, an overlap extension PCR according to Pogulis et al. <xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> was used.</p>
        <p>Random mutagenesis of the Leu294 amino acid with the mutagenic forward primer 5′-GCGGTCTTCTTGATGTGTA<underline>C</underline>CTTTCGAGTGTAAGTAACAAAACAAACGAAGTGATGAAGGTG<underline>NNN</underline>ACCATCATAGCG-3′ and the reverse primer 5′-CGCTATGATGGT<underline>NNN</underline>CACCTTCATCACTTCGTTTGTTTTGTTACTTACACTCGAAAG<underline>G</underline>TACACATCAAGAA-GACCGC-3′ was performed with mutagenic PCR according to standard protocols. PCR product was cut with BamHI and PstI restriction enzymes and cloned into a BamHI and PstI digested pQE CorA construct. Correctly ligated constructs were identified by deletion of the BsaBI restriction site in the CorA gene, resulting in a silent mutation from a thymine to a cytosine. No additional mutations were found by sequencing.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0030">
        <label>2.4</label>
        <title>Complementation assays on solid media</title>
        <p>The CorA, MgtA, MgtB deletion strain MM281 was transformed with pQE80L constructs harbouring TmCorA or mutated versions thereof. Single colonies were inoculated in LB medium containing 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and grown over night. The cultures were washed twice with 0.7% saline, adjusted to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.1, and diluted 1:10, 1:100 and 1:1000 and spotted on LB plates containing 100 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> or on standard LB plates, both supplemented with different IPTG concentrations (0; 0.01; 0.1 mM). The cultures were incubated for 24 h at 37 °C.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0035">
        <label>2.5</label>
        <title>Growth curves</title>
        <p>Overnight cultures of MM281 cells transformed with the aforementioned plasmid constructs were grown in LB medium with 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, washed twice with LB and inoculated to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.1 into liquid LB medium containing different concentrations of MgCl<sub>2</sub> and IPTG.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0040">
        <label>2.6</label>
        <title>Measurement of Mg<sup>2+</sup> uptake by spectrofluorometry</title>
        <p>For these measurements cells were grown in low-phosphate LB medium in order to minimize complexation of Mg<sup>2+</sup> by an excess of phosphate, which might cause variation in Mg<sup>2+</sup> concentration. The measurements have been performed as described previously <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0045">
        <label>2.7</label>
        <title>PAGE and western blotting</title>
        <p>Overnight cultures of MM281 cells transformed with the aforementioned plasmid constructs were washed twice with LB medium and diluted in fresh LB + Amp medium to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.1. Expression was induced by adding 0.05 mM IPTG for 3 h. Equivalents of 3 ml culture with an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.5 were taken. The cell pellet was resuspended in 20 μl SDS-Laemmli buffer and 20 μl 8 M Urea and sonicated for 5 s. After 15 min centrifugation at 13,000 rpm, equal volumes of supernatant were loaded on 10% SDS/polyacrylamide gels, blotted and labelled with an antiserum against the 6xHis tag (Qiagen).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0050">
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>There are several hydrophobic constrictions along the TmCorA ion conduction pathway. The narrowest one is formed by the highly conserved residues Leu294 and Met291 <xref rid="bb0020 bb0025 bb0030" ref-type="bibr">[4–6]</xref>. They are considered to be part of the potential “hydrophobic gate” <xref rid="bb0020 bb0040" ref-type="bibr">[4,8]</xref>. To verify this hypothesis our mutations targeted the Leu294, we analysed mutants containing three different residues: positively charged arginine, negatively charged aspartic acid and small glycine.</p>
      <sec id="s0055">
        <label>3.1</label>
        <title>Effect of positive charge at position 294 on gating of CorA: Leu294Arg mutant</title>
        <p>In the growth complementation assay the Leu294Arg mutant showed similar growth as the wild-type TmCorA on plates without MgCl<sub>2</sub> and with different IPTG concentrations, which means, that the change from hydrophobic leucine to the hydrophilic, positively charged arginine does not cause a dramatic change in the protein function (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). While on plates containing 100 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and 0.1 mM IPTG the wild-type TmCorA exhibited a growth defect, probably caused by Mg<sup>2+</sup> overdose, the Leu294Arg mutant was still able to grow indicating decreased transport efficiency of this mutant (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).</p>
        <p>Mg<sup>2+</sup> uptake measurements of the Leu294Arg mutant showed slower Mg<sup>2+</sup> influx and lower steady-state values (~ 80% of wild-type values) (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) suggesting that (i) the pore of the transporter is smaller than in wild-type TmCorA; (ii) the sensitivity of CorA to Mg<sup>2+</sup> or the regulation of opening and closing of the pore was affected.</p>
        <p>The growth curves of cells transformed with TmCorA Leu294Arg mutant (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a, b, c) support these hypotheses. In liquid medium supplemented with 0.05 mM IPTG the cells grew much slower than those with wild-type TmCorA (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>b), while the shapes of the curves remained similar, pointing to a lower Mg<sup>2+</sup> transport capacity of this mutant. The same was true for cells growing in medium with 0.05 mM IPTG and 3 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>c). We did not observe any indications of Mg<sup>2+</sup> overdose, not even after 11 hour incubation (results not shown), suggesting that closing of the transporter remained tightly regulated. In medium without MgCl<sub>2</sub> the cells with Leu294Arg mutant were unable to grow, exactly like those with wild-type TmCorA (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0060">
        <label>3.2</label>
        <title>Effect of negative charge at position 294 on gating of CorA: Leu294Asp mutant</title>
        <p>Cells transformed with TmCorA Leu294Asp mutant showed a growth defect on medium containing 0.1 mM IPTG as well as on media containing 0.1 mM IPTG and 100 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> in the growth complementation assay (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). This suggests either a higher Mg<sup>2+</sup> transport capacity, which might be caused by a defect in the regulation process of the opening and closing of the channel or in the closing itself, leading to Mg<sup>2+</sup> overdose during the 24 hour incubation and consequently to a toxic effect of this protein at high expression levels.</p>
        <p>Mg<sup>2+</sup> uptake of Leu294Asp mutant increased slowly and did not reach a steady-state level within a time period of 600 s (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>), suggesting that the pore is neither completely open nor can it close properly, causing slow, constant Mg<sup>2+</sup> uptake, leading finally to a Mg<sup>2+</sup> overdose. This mutation apparently causes a defect in the regulation of opening and closing or/and in the closing process itself, which was corroborated by the growth curves (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a, b, c): neither cells transformed with the TmCorA nor cells transformed with the Leu294Asp mutant were able to grow in medium without MgCl<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a). In medium containing 0.05 mM IPTG we observed rapid growth but after 4 h a steady-state phase was reached, probably due to a Mg<sup>2+</sup> overdose (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>b). In medium containing 0.05 mM IPTG and 3 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> the shape of the Leu294Asp mutant growth curve differed from that of the wild-type TmCorA: the mutant cells grew significantly slower, reaching only an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.6 (~ 50% of the wild-type CorA) (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>c), which indicates a Mg<sup>2+</sup> overdose caused by the constant Mg<sup>2+</sup> uptake depicted in <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0065">
        <label>3.3</label>
        <title>Effect of removal of side chain at position 294 on gating of CorA: Leu294Gly mutant</title>
        <p>As expected, the Leu294Gly mutant was even more Mg<sup>2+</sup> sensitive than the Leu294Asp variant. The cells did not grow on plates containing 0.1 mM IPTG suggesting a defect in the closing and/or in the regulation of the transporter and the growth on plates containing 0.01 mM IPTG points to a higher Mg<sup>2+</sup> uptake capacity compared to the wild-type TmCorA (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). In case of the Leu294Gly mutant the cells also grew on plates without additional MgCl<sub>2</sub> or IPTG (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>) which might be due to not tight enough regulation of the used plasmid, leading to leaky expression of the CorA gene in the absence of IPTG. This was tested by determination of expressed CorA levels using western blots (<xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). The low expression level of the wild-type TmCorA protein was not sufficient to provide cells with enough Mg<sup>2+</sup> in a low Mg<sup>2+</sup> medium, but in the case of the Leu294Gly mutant cells are able to take up enough Mg<sup>2+</sup> to survive. This observation supports the suggested increased Mg<sup>2+</sup> transport ability of the Leu294Gly mutant, which was also observed in Mg<sup>2+</sup> uptake measurements (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). The Mg<sup>2+</sup> influx was as fast as in cells transformed with wild-type TmCorA, but it did not reach a steady-state, which indicates a defect in the closing of the transporter.</p>
        <p>In liquid medium containing 0.05 mM IPTG we observed fast growth of the Leu294Gly cells, followed by a steady-state after 4 h (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>b). In medium supplemented with 0.05 mM IPTG and 3 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> the cells stopped to grow already after 3 h, reaching only ~ 40% of the wild-type level, and contrary to the wild-type cells, they began to die (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>c). This effect can be related not only to an increased Mg<sup>2+</sup> transport ability but also to a closing defect of the transporter. Increased Mg<sup>2+</sup> transport ability of the Leu294Gly mutant (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) allowed growth of the cells also in medium without any supplements (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a), suggesting eminent structural changes caused by this mutation.</p>
        <p>In order to confirm that the higher Mg<sup>2+</sup> uptake capacity of this mutant is due to the Leu294Gly mutation, we used Co(III)hexamine, a known blocker of the CorA transporter <xref rid="bb0040 bb0055 bb0060" ref-type="bibr">[8,11,12]</xref>. We compared the wild-type <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> strain LB5010, which has all major Mg<sup>2+</sup> uptake systems (CorA, MgtA, MgtB) with strain MM281 deficient for these genes, transformed with wild-type TmCorA and with TmCorA Leu294Gly mutant. In liquid LB medium (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>) strain LB5010 grew fast, whereas strain MM281 containing the Leu294Gly mutation showed reduced growth, and strain MM281 with wild-type TmCorA did not grow at all. After addition of 3 mM Co(III)hexamine, growth of LB5010 cells and MM281 cells containing wild-type TmCorA remained unchanged, whereas growth of MM281 cells with the Leu294Gly mutation was completely inhibited proving that growth of cells under low Mg<sup>2+</sup> conditions is the result of this mutation.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0070">
      <label>4</label>
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Gating of the TmCorA magnesium transporter is a complex process, involving several events resulting in structural rearrangements of the pentamer: binding of Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions to the regulatory DCS site(s) with consequent rearrangements of α-helices in the N-terminal domain, the pore-forming α7 helices and the basic sphincter are considered to lead collectively to conformational changes in the gating region. Leu294 lies in the 15 Å long region termed MM stretch (spanning residues Met291 to Met301) proposed to play a central role in controlling the ionic conduction profile by representing both a steric as well as an electrostatic bottleneck for Mg<sup>2+</sup> translocation <xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. This region involves a series of hydrophobic residues among which Leu at position 294 plays a critical role in the gating process. The effects of the Leu294 mutation to Asp and Gly may be mechanistically and structurally explained by local structural and electrostatic changes due to introduction of a negatively charged or a small amino acid residue with no side chain.</p>
      <p>In case of glycine, the absence of the side chain could on one hand cause a wider opening of the pore and on the other impair its complete closing. This is in agreement with results of Payandeh et al. <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, who showed that exchange of Leu294 to a hydrophobic amino acid with a smaller side chain (Ile, Val or Ala) results in an increased ability of cells to grow on media supplemented with low MgCl<sub>2</sub> concentrations.</p>
      <p>In case of introduction of an aspartic acid at position 294, the negatively charged side chains coming from five protomers repulse each other and thereby maximise the distance between them, leading to the incapacity of the transporter to properly close and to maintain a stable magnesium concentration in the cell. Furthermore, slow magnesium uptake of this mutant indicates that Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions are probably trapped in the ring of negative charges.</p>
      <p>The effects observed with the Leu294Arg mutant cannot only be explained by local changes. Concentration of positively charged arginine residues in this region might have two opposite effects: repulsion of the positively charged residues causing a local structural distortion, and/or repulsion of the Mg<sup>2+</sup> ion and hindering its passing through the pore. Both effects can explain the slow-down of Mg<sup>2+</sup> transport, but not the low steady-state values observed in Mg<sup>2+</sup> uptake measurements, which indicate a change in the regulation of Mg<sup>2+</sup> influx. According to Payandeh et al. a valine mutation at position 294 can alter Mg<sup>2+</sup>-binding properties of the transporter <xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Due to the distance of ~ 65 Å between the Leu294 and the DCS sites a direct interaction seems impossible. Since the loss of Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions from DCS sites can induce conformational rearrangements of the magnesium-binding domains, transmitted to the gate region by the α7 helices and leading to changes allowing ions to pass through <xref rid="bb0035 bb0040" ref-type="bibr">[7,8]</xref>, also a reverse process might be possible. Certain mutations in the gate region may evoke structural rearrangements of the α7 helices leading to conformational changes in the DCS sites, resulting in their changed affinity to Mg<sup>2+</sup> ions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0075">
      <label>5</label>
      <title>Concluding remarks</title>
      <p>In summary, we confirmed the importance of the Leu294 as a mechanical barrier to Mg<sup>2+</sup> permeation. We furthermore propose an additional function of this residue in the regulation of Mg<sup>2+</sup> uptake. Since Mg<sup>2+</sup> transport involves multiple coordinated structural movements, further structural and functional analyses will be required to fully understand the molecular basis of this process.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bb0005">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>R.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Banks</surname>
              <given-names>J.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Snavely</surname>
              <given-names>M.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maguire</surname>
              <given-names>M.E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sequence and topology of the CorA magnesium transport systems of <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>. Identification of a new class of transport protein</article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <volume>268</volume>
          <year>1993</year>
          <fpage>14071</fpage>
          <lpage>14080</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8314774</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0010">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Webb</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The utilization of magnesium by certain Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria</article-title>
          <source>J. Gen. Microbiol.</source>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <year>1966</year>
          <fpage>401</fpage>
          <lpage>409</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4960404</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0015">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>R.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maguire</surname>
              <given-names>M.E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Microbial magnesium transport: unusual transporters searching for identity</article-title>
          <source>Mol. Microbiol.</source>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <year>1998</year>
          <fpage>217</fpage>
          <lpage>226</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9622348</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0020">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lunin</surname>
              <given-names>V.V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dobrovetsky</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khutoreskaya</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Joachimiak</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Doyle</surname>
              <given-names>D.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bochkarev</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maguire</surname>
              <given-names>M.E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Edwards</surname>
              <given-names>A.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koth</surname>
              <given-names>C.M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Crystal structure of the CorA Mg2+ transporter</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <volume>440</volume>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>833</fpage>
          <lpage>837</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16598263</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0025">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eshaghi</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Niegowski</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kohl</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martinez Molina</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lesley</surname>
              <given-names>S.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nordlund</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Crystal structure of a divalent metal ion transporter CorA at 2.9 angstrom resolution</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>313</volume>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>354</fpage>
          <lpage>357</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16857941</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0030">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Payandeh</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pai</surname>
              <given-names>E.F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A structural basis for Mg2+ homeostasis and the CorA translocation cycle</article-title>
          <source>EMBO J.</source>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>3762</fpage>
          <lpage>3773</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16902408</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0035">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chakrabarti</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neale</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Payandeh</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pai</surname>
              <given-names>E.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pomes</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An iris-like mechanism of pore dilation in the CorA magnesium transport system</article-title>
          <source>Biophys. J.</source>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <year>2010</year>
          <fpage>784</fpage>
          <lpage>792</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20197031</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0040">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Payandeh</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramjeesingh</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Poduch</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bear</surname>
              <given-names>C.E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pai</surname>
              <given-names>E.F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Probing structure–function relationships and gating mechanisms in the CorA Mg2+ transport system</article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <volume>283</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>11721</fpage>
          <lpage>11733</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18276588</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0045">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pogulis</surname>
              <given-names>R.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vallejo</surname>
              <given-names>A.N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pease</surname>
              <given-names>L.R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>In vitro recombination and mutagenesis by overlap extension PCR</article-title>
          <source>Meth. Mol. Biol.</source>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <year>1996</year>
          <fpage>167</fpage>
          <lpage>176</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0050">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Froschauer</surname>
              <given-names>E.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kolisek</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dieterich</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schweigel</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schweyen</surname>
              <given-names>R.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fluorescence measurements of free [Mg2+] by use of mag-fura 2 in <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic></article-title>
          <source>FEMS Microbiol. Lett.</source>
          <volume>237</volume>
          <year>2004</year>
          <fpage>49</fpage>
          <lpage>55</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15268937</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0055">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kucharski</surname>
              <given-names>L.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lubbe</surname>
              <given-names>W.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maguire</surname>
              <given-names>M.E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cation hexaammines are selective and potent inhibitors of the CorA magnesium transport system</article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <volume>275</volume>
          <year>2000</year>
          <fpage>16767</fpage>
          <lpage>16773</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10748031</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bb0060">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kolisek</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zsurka</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Samaj</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weghuber</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schweyen</surname>
              <given-names>R.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schweigel</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mrs2p is an essential component of the major electrophoretic Mg2+ influx system in mitochondria</article-title>
          <source>EMBO J.</source>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <year>2003</year>
          <fpage>1235</fpage>
          <lpage>1244</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12628916</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We thank Michael Maguire (Case Western Reserve University) for providing the <italic>Salmonella typhimurium</italic> strains MM281 and LB5010 and Said Eshaghi (Karolinska Institute, Sweden) for providing the TmCorA coding sequence. We also thank Elisabeth Froschauer, Muhammad Bashir Khan and Oliviero Carugo (Univ. of Pavia, Italy and Max F. Perutz Laboratories, Austria) for fruitful discussions.</p>
      <p>This work was supported by WWTF (LS05021) and FWF (P20141).</p>
    </ack>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="f0005">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Structure of the TmCorA Mg<sup>2+</sup> transporter. (a) Single monomer: green — transmembrane domains TM1 and TM2, blue — α7 helix, red — N-terminal domain. (b) Side view of the homopentamer: cyan — DCS sites 1 and 2. (c) View from the top: blue — basic sphincter, yellow — aromatic ring, green — the gate forming residues Leu294 and Met291.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0010">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Growth complementation assay of the gating mutants. <italic>S. typhimurium</italic> strain MM281 which lacks all three known magnesium transport systems was transformed with plasmids indicated. The pQE TmCorA and pQE80L empty constructs served as positive and negative control.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0015">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Representative recordings of Mg<sup>2+</sup> uptake. <italic>S. typhimurium</italic> strain MM281 which lacks all three known magnesium transport systems was transformed with plasmids indicated. The representative recordings show changes in fluorescence intensity of Mag-Fura-2 monitored over 10 min time after adding 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>. The pQE TmCorA and pQE80L empty constructs served as positive and negative control.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0020">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Effect of gating mutations in different liquid medium. Growth curves of the <italic>S. typhimurium</italic> strain MM281 which lacks all three known magnesium transport systems, transformed with plasmids indicated. Cells were grown over night in LB amp medium containing 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>. Cultures were diluted to an OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.1 and grown over 5 h. The data were averaged from three independent experiments.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr4"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0025">
      <label>Fig. 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Effect of Co(III)hexamine, inhibitor of the CorA-mediated magnesium transport. Growth curves of the <italic>S. typhimurium</italic> strains LB5010 (wild-type strain) transformed with pQE80L parental vector and MM281 (<italic>corAΔ</italic>, <italic>mgtAΔ</italic>, <italic>mgtBΔ</italic>) transformed with pQE80 TmCorA and pQE80 TmCorA L294G in the presence or absence of cobalt hexamine. The data were averaged from three independent experiments.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr5"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0030">
      <label>Fig. 6</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Western blot analysis of whole cell samples. <italic>S. typhimurium</italic> strain MM281 which lacks all three known magnesium transport systems was transformed with plasmids indicated. The synthesis of CorA protein and variants thereof was induced by addition 0.05 mM IPTG for 3 h.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr6"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>