<article xmlns="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Vacuum</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Vacuum</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0042-207X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1879-2715</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Pergamon Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3252239</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22241935</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">VAC5215</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vacuum.2010.11.014</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Adsorption and desorption of CO on Ni decorated stepped Rh(553)</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Singnurkar</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schennach</surname>
            <given-names>R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>robert.schennach@tugraz.at</email>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>Institute of Solid State Physics, Graz University of Technology, Petersgasse 16/2, A-8010 GRAZ, Austria</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label>Corresponding author. Tel.: +43 316 873 8462; fax: +43 316 873 8466. <email>robert.schennach@tugraz.at</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>85</volume>
      <issue>7-4</issue>
      <fpage>761</fpage>
      <lpage>767</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2011 Elsevier Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/authorsview.authors/supplementalterms1.0">certain conditions</ext-link>.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vicinal surfaces are important in surface science, as they show interesting electronic structures and reactivities due to the steps. In this paper the adsorption and desorption of carbon monoxide on the stepped Rh(553) surface decorated with Ni is reported. With 0.1 to 0.3 monolayer Ni on Rh(553) one and two atoms broad Ni wires along the Rh steps are formed. The adsorption and desorption of carbon monoxide on these surfaces is investigated using thermal desorption spectroscopy (TDS) and reflection absorption infra red spectroscopy (RAIRS). TDS shows a marked change from just one broad TDS peak on pure Rh(553) to 4 distinct peaks with increasing Ni decoration. RAIRS shows that already at 0.1 monolayer Ni the CO adsorption states on bridge sites on the Rh step atoms are completely quenched. In addition it is shown that with Ni films up to 3 monolayer the on top adsorption sites for CO on Ni are preferred over the bridge and hollow adsorption sites in contrast to what is known from the Ni(111) surface.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract abstract-type="graphical">
        <title>Research highlights</title>
        <p>► CO adsorption on a Ni decorated stepped Rh(553) surface is investigated by TPD and RAIRS. ► The Ni decoration quenches the CO bridge position on the Rh steps. ► Ni decoration of the steps leads to 4 TPD peaks as compared to just one peak in clean Rh(553). ► Increasing the Ni coverage does not lead to a CO adsorption that is comparable to a stepped Ni surface.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>RAIRS</kwd>
        <kwd>TDS</kwd>
        <kwd>Rh(553)</kwd>
        <kwd>Ni</kwd>
        <kwd>Bimetallic surface</kwd>
        <kwd>Stepped surface</kwd>
        <kwd>Carbon monoxide</kwd>
        <kwd>CO</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec1">
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>In recent years the surface science community started to investigate stepped surfaces again, as a way to bridge the so called materials gap. As a real heterogeneous catalyst consists of small metal particles on an oxide support, the metal particles will have quite a lot of steps and kinks, as the particles usually assume an island geometry. Therefore, investigations of stepped surfaces are a way to understand the influence of steps on the adsorption and reaction of simple molecules on still well characterized surfaces. Pioneering work on vicinal surfaces was done earlier (e.g. <xref rid="bib1 bib2" ref-type="bibr">[1,2]</xref>).</p>
      <p>In order to understand the changes due to the steps one first has to understand the system on the flat surface. Secondly a sound structural characterisation of the stepped surface is necessary to make sure that the surface actually looks the same as expected from the cutting angle used. This has been done for the Rh(553) surface using STM (Scanning Tunneling Microscopy) in previous work <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. There it was shown that the surface consists of monoatomic (111) steps and 4 atom rows wide (111) terraces. The steps are stable within the temperature range used in this paper for the thermal desorption spectroscopy.</p>
      <p>Bimetallic surfaces have also been studied extensively over the years due to the importance of bimetallic catalysts used in industry. However, for surface science studies a well ordered bimetallic surface is important and often not very easily prepared. Nevertheless, it was reported that metal atoms decorating steps change the step potential barriers <xref rid="bib4 bib5" ref-type="bibr">[4,5]</xref>. In the case of Ni evaporation onto the stepped Rh(553) surface STM experiments showed that the Ni first decorates the steps leading to one to two atoms broad Ni wires along the steps <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. An increased reactivity of the Ni rows on the steps was reported, too <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. The electronic structure of the Ni nanowires on Rh(553) has been investigated recently <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Increasing the Ni content leads to a layer like growth up to about 1 ML Ni. With increasing amount of Ni the second Ni layer starts to grow before the first layer is completely closed <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Unfortunately no further data of Ni growth in Rh(553) is available.</p>
      <p>In this paper we will present the results of CO adsorption on the Ni decorated Rh(553) surface and its evolution with increasing amount of Ni on the stepped surface. The data will be discussed with respect to what is known about the structure of the surfaces and with respect to what is known about CO adsorption on the corresponding flat Rh(111) and Ni(111) surfaces as well as stepped Rh and Ni surfaces.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec2">
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Experimental</title>
      <p>The experiments were done in a ultrahigh vacuum (UHV) apparatus described in detail previously <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. In difference to the previous experiments the molecular beam apparatus was replaced by a capillary array detector. Briefly, the UHV chamber is equipped with an Auger Electron Spectrometer (AES), an X-ray photoelectron spectrometer (XPS) and a quadrupole mass spectrometer. Thermal desorption experiments were done with a heating rate of 4 ks<sup>−1</sup> while the desorbing molecules were detected with the quadrupole mass spectrometer.</p>
      <p>RAIRS (Reflection absorption infra red spectroscopy) measurements were done in the same UHV chamber using a Bruker IFS 66v/S FTIR spectrometer and an external liquid N<sub>2</sub> cooled MCT detector. A grazing incidence of about 83° and a scan time of 15 min were used with a resolution of 4 cm<sup>−1</sup> and a mirror velocity of 10 kHz. The details of the RAIRS setup were described in an earlier publication <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The Rh (553) crystal was cleaned by repeated cycles of Ar ion sputtering at 300 K, oxygen treatment at 870 K in a 6.6 × 10<sup>−8</sup> mbar O<sub>2</sub> atmosphere and annealing at 1150 K. The cleanliness of the surface was checked by AES, XPS and production of TPD spectra of carbon monoxide and oxygen in good agreement with previously done experiments <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Carbon monoxide was brought into the chamber via a leak valve. The cleanliness of the gas was checked by the quadrupole mass spectrometer. The exposures at pressures between 10<sup>−8</sup> and 10<sup>−7</sup> mbar were monitored by recording the total pressure in the system (using a Leybold Ionivac IM520) and the corresponding QMS signal. The exposures are given in Langmuir (L) with 1L corresponding to 1 torrs.</p>
      <p>The Ni was evaporated onto the stepped Rh(553) surface at room temperature using an electron beam evaporator and the deposited amount of Ni was controlled using a quartz micro balance. The Ni coverages are given in monolayers (ML) with respect to the amount of Rh atoms in the top most atomic layer.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec3">
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Results and discussion</title>
      <p>In the following first the TPD results will be discussed followed by the RAIRS results. Finally the results will be discussed in light of previous studies and by comparison of RAIRS and TPD results.</p>
      <sec id="sec3.1">
        <label>3.1</label>
        <title>Thermal desorption spectroscopy (TPD)</title>
        <p>The adsorption of carbon monoxide on the stepped Rh(553) surface has been studied before <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> and it was shown that the thermal desorption spectra of CO from this surface are practically identical to the carbon monoxide desorption from Rh(111) <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. From <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A it is clear that already a Ni coverage of 0.1 ML completely changes the thermal desorption behaviour of CO. For comparison with the 0.1 ML Ni decorated surface the TPD data from clean Rh(553) are shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> B. While on clean Rh(553) only one desorption peak around 480 K with a shoulder at high coverage around 350 K is seen <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, with Ni decoration of the steps one can see up to 4 different TPD peaks as a function of the CO coverage (see <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> A). With a CO exposure of 0.25 L (curve a in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> A) one can see a large peak at about 500 K, a broad smaller peak with the maximum around 250 K and a small feature with a maximum around 125 K. With a CO exposure of 0.5 L (curve b in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> A) these three peaks increase in intensity and the two high temperature peaks shift slightly to lower temperatures. At an exposure of 1 L (curve c in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> A) a shoulder develops around 375 K, while the other three peaks increase in intensity with the two higher temperature peaks again shifting slightly to lower temperatures. With 2 L of CO exposure (curve d in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> A) the shoulder at 375 K developed into a clear peak at about 350 K. So at an exposure of 2 L CO all 4 peaks have developed, however they all overlap with each other except for the peak at 125 K. With a CO exposure of 4 L (curve e in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> A) a marked change occurs in the TPD spectra. The broad small feature at around 125 K changes into a sharp peak at 125 K, which further increases in intensity and shifts to slightly higher temperatures with increasing CO coverage on the surface. In addition there seems to be a shoulder around 170–175 K, that is visible up to the highest CO exposures. With further increasing CO exposure (curves f and g in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> A) only the peak below 250 K gets more pronounced and shifts down to about 210 K. The other three peaks stay the same and also no further shift in the peak positions occur. Therefore, the peak corresponding to an exposure of 10 L (curve g in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> A) corresponds to a full layer of CO on the 0.1 ML Ni decorated Rh(553) surface.</p>
        <p>Increasing the amount of Ni on the Rh(553) surface to 0.3 ML one finds a change in the TPD spectra (see <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). At low CO exposures (curve a and b in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>) still three peaks are observed at 490, 250 and 125 K. The low temperature peak at 125 K increases with CO coverage, but the peak maximum stays at the same temperature. The high temperature peak at 490 K shifts with increasing CO coverage down to about 475 K. With a CO exposure of 2 L (curve d in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>) again the shoulder around 375 K develops, however no clear peak is found even at the highest CO exposure in contrast to the 0.1 ML Ni case (see <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). The TPD peak around 250 K shifts down in temperature to about 215 K up to a CO exposure of 2 L (curve d in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). With higher CO exposures this peak is replaced by a peak around 270 K, which stays at a constant temperature up to the highest exposure (curves e−g in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).</p>
        <p>From comparison with the literature one can assign the different CO TPD peaks with 0.1 and 0.3 ML Ni to the following adsorption sites. It is known from STM measurements that the Ni does decorate the steps at these low coverages <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Therefore one can assume that the main CO desorption peak around 490 K stems from CO bound in on top sites on the Rh(553) terraces and the shoulder around 375 K is most likely due to desorption from bridge and hollow sites of the Rh terraces. As these two desorption features are very similar to the CO desorption from the Ni free Rh(553) surface <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> this assignment of the CO adsorption sites is quite likely.</p>
        <p>The TPD peaks below about 350 K have not been observed on the Ni free Rh(553) surface <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Therefore they must be associated with the Ni decoration of the steps. The adsorption of CO on the Ni decorated steps has been investigated before using HR-XPS (High resolution x-ray photoelectron spectroscopy) and DFT (Density functional theory) <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. In this paper it was shown that CO adsorbs at exposures below 1 L at on top sites of the terraces and with higher exposures bridge and hollow sites of the steps are occupied. Therefore one can assign the two low temperature peaks in our TPD to bridge and hollow sites on the steps. Taking into account that DFT shows the lowest adsorption energy for CO adsorbed in the on top position of the Ni on the step and the fact that only very few such sites will be occupied making them invisible in the HR-XPS one can tentatively assign the TPD peak at the lowest temperature (125 K) to CO adsorption in the on top site of the step and the peak around 250 K to CO adsorbed in the bridge and hollow sites of the steps. The shoulder seen around 170–175 K in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> might be due to repulsive interactions between the CO molecules in the bridge and hollow sites at higher CO coverages.</p>
        <p>Increasing the Ni coverage on the Rh(553) surface to 0.5 ML shows a similar picture with 4 peaks in the TPD (see <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). However, the thermal desorption features at high temperatures are actually quite different. The main peak starts around 500 K at a CO exposure of 0.25 L (curve a in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). With increasing CO coverage on the surface this peak again shifts to lower temperatures. A shoulder on the leading edge of this peak is already visible at 1 L CO exposure (curve c in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). It is at a temperature of about 440 K, which is approximately 50 K higher than the high temperature shoulder with less Ni on the surface. With further increasing CO exposure the shoulder develops into a peak and the maximum shifts down to about 410 K. At the highest CO exposure (curve g in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>) this peak has almost the same height as the peak at 480 K. The two low temperature peaks evolve very similar to the 0.3 ML Ni case. The change in the high temperature desorption peaks could be attributed to on top or bridge/hollow adsorption sites on the now available Ni terrace. The main desorption peak from a stepped Ni(111) surface is at about 450 K <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, which would fit to the peak around 410 K in the 0.5 ML Ni case on Rh(553). However, one has to bear in mind that on Ni(111) the hollow and bridge sites are occupied at low CO coverage and the on top site only gets populated at higher CO coverage <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. This will be further discussed in the RAIRS section below.</p>
        <p>The picture changes again when 1 ML of Ni is deposited on the Rh(553) surface. As can be seen in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> there are only three main TPD peaks at 490, 425 and 250 K left. With the lowest CO exposure still one peak at 490 K and one around 250 K is seen, however, the peak around 125 K has almost disappeared (curve a in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). With increasing coverage these two peaks increase and shift to lower temperatures, with a significant larger shift of the peak at lower temperature. With a CO exposure of 1 L (curve c in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>) a clear third peak is found at 440 K, which is at this exposure already higher than the peak at 490 K. The peak at 220 K has a shoulder around 250 K at this exposure. With increasing CO exposure the peak at 220 K disappears and the shoulder develops into a peak at about 250 K. At high CO coverage also a shoulder at about 150 K is visible. In addition a peak (shoulder) around 180 K develops. At the highest CO exposure of 10 L (curve e in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>) the peak at 440 K is the highest peak with only a shoulder at 490 K, which was the highest peak at lower Ni coverages.</p>
        <p>A comparison of the TPD with 1 ML Ni on Rh(553) with a stepped Ni(111) surface shows that the low temperature shoulder and the two peaks at lower temperature are similar to CO desorption from a stepped Ni(111) surface. However, the shoulder at 490 K does not exist on the Ni surface. Therefore this shoulder must be due to the Rh substrate.</p>
        <p>A tentative correlation of different CO adsorption sites to the TPD peaks could be as follows. The highest temperature TPD peak could probably be due to on top adsorption sites of CO on the terraces, which are covered with Ni in this case. The second peak around 440 K could be due to CO adsorbed in the bridge and hollow sites of the terraces and the low temperature peak around 250 K would be due to hollow and bridge sites on the steps and on top sites on the steps are represented by the shoulder around 150 K. The peak (shoulder) around 180 K might again be due to repulsive lateral interactions between the bridge and hollow sites on the steps at higher CO coverages.</p>
        <p>A further increase of the amount of Ni on the Rh(553) surface to 2 ML does not change the overall shape of the TPD. Only the peak at around 440 K increases in intensity as compared to the peak around 490 K. Also the onset of the peak at 440 K already occurs in form of a shoulder at a CO exposure of 0.5 L.</p>
        <p>However, at a Ni coverage of 3 ML there is another marked change in the thermal desorption of CO. As can be seen from <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> in this case only one peak is found around 340 K with two shoulders on the leading and on the trailing edge. Again a small peak at 150 K is seen in the desorption spectra. For a layer by layer growth of Ni on Rh(553) one would expect that the TPD of 3 ML Ni on Rh(553) would resemble the TPD of a stepped Ni(111) surface more than that of a flat Ni(111) surface. However, if one makes these comparisons none of the two are very similar to the TPD seen in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>. Therefore the surface morphology of the 3 ML Ni on Rh(553) is probably more complicated with some Ni island formation. Such a rough surface could lead to the smeared out TPD in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> as compared to lower Ni coverages. In addition one has to bear in mind that the lattice mismatch between Ni and Rh is quite high with 8%. This will lead to a significant strain in the surface layers, which in turn will affect the CO adsorption.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="sec3.2">
        <label>3.2</label>
        <title>Reflection absorption infra red spectroscopy (RAIRS)</title>
        <p>In <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> a and b the on top region and the bridge and hollow region of the C–O stretching frequency as a function of CO exposure on 0.1 ML Ni decorated Rh(553) is shown. The RAIR spectra were recorded just before the corresponding thermal desorption experiments. With a CO exposure of 0.25 L one can see a peak in the on top region at about 2032 cm<sup>−1</sup>. This vibrational frequency corresponds very well to the on top vibration on the terrace according to <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. The vibration at 2018 cm<sup>−1</sup> found on the Ni free Rh(553) <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> is not found here, showing that the Ni decoration of the steps quenches these adsorption sites. At this low CO coverage no vibrations in the bridge and hollow region are found. This is also in contrast to the Ni free Rh(553), because there a vibration at around 1900 cm<sup>−1</sup> was found originating from CO bonded in a bridge site on the step. Also this site is apparently quenched by the Ni decoration of the steps.</p>
        <p>With increasing CO exposure the on top vibration shifts up to 2048 cm<sup>−1</sup> (see <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>). This shift of the CO on top frequency is well known for CO adsorbed on a Rh surface and it is due to dipole–dipole interactions <xref rid="bib12 bib16" ref-type="bibr">[12,16]</xref>. These interactions are the reason for the repulsive interaction that leads to the shift of the CO TPD peak maxima to lower temperatures <xref rid="bib12 bib16" ref-type="bibr">[12,16]</xref>. Both IR peaks with 0.25 and 0.5 L CO also have a small peak at higher wavenumbers (2065 and 2072 cm<sup>−1</sup>), which was attributed to a metastable densely packed CO structure before <xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>.</p>
        <p>With an exposure of 1 L the on top peak shifts up to 2070 cm<sup>−1</sup> and it shows a shoulder around 2080 cm<sup>−1</sup>. The shoulder most likely still corresponds to the high density CO structure mentioned above. With further increasing CO exposure the on top frequency shifts to 2088 cm<sup>−1</sup> and stays more or less constant. However, the peaks have a fairly large full width at half maximum (FWHM), which might indicate a disordered CO layer, as ordered CO structures usually have a rather small FWHM <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>.</p>
        <p>Only at an exposure of 4 L also a RAIRS peak is found in the bridge and hollow region. This vibration around 1875 cm<sup>−1</sup> has been attributed to bridge and hollow sites of the terraces of Rh(553) <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Apparently there is no feature visible in the IR that could be attributed to CO adsorbed on Ni or on sites close to Ni at this low Ni coverage. However, this might simply be due to the limited sensitivity of about 0.1 ML of CO of the RAIRS.</p>
        <p>With a Ni coverage of 0.3 ML on the Rh(553) surface the RAIR spectra are different (see <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> a, b). At low CO exposures (0.25 and 0.5 L) only CO adsorbed in on top positions is observed starting at about 2025 cm<sup>−1</sup> and increasing up to 2050 cm<sup>−1</sup> with a CO exposure of 1 L (see <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> a). This vibration can again be attributed to CO adsorbed on Rh terrace atoms in an on top configuration. At 1 L also a vibrational feature around 1865 cm<sup>−1</sup> is found (see <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> b), which can be attributed to bridge or hollow sites on the terrace. With increasing CO exposure this feature shifts to higher wavenumbers ending up at about 1875 cm<sup>−1</sup> with 10 L CO.</p>
        <p>The on top vibration changes to a broad peak with two maxima at about 2075 and 2090 cm<sup>−1</sup> with an exposure of 2 L (see <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> a). Both peaks move to higher wavenumbers with increasing CO exposure and the peak at lower wavenumbers decreases in intensity, while the peak at higher wavenumbers increases. The origin of these two on top peaks could be due to CO adsorbed on Rh and on Ni sites. As will be shown later with 3 ML Ni only one on top CO vibration at 2100 cm<sup>−1</sup> is found supporting this interpretation. However, the on top vibration of CO on Ni(111) is found at around 2060 cm<sup>−1</sup> <xref rid="bib17 bib18" ref-type="bibr">[17,18]</xref>. The shift to higher wavenumbers found with the Ni decorated surface could be due to the underlying Rh atoms and/or the rather large strain of the Ni atoms due to the lattice mismatch.</p>
        <p>With half a monolayer of Ni on the surface the RAIR spectra are quite similar. In the on top CO adsorption region (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>a) again one clear peak is found up to an exposure of 1 L. With 2 L and more CO two overlapping peaks around 2080 and 2100 cm<sup>−1</sup> are found. In the bridge and hollow region (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> b) the picture is slightly different. At 2 L CO exposure a small peak around 1860 cm<sup>−1</sup> is found similar to the case with 0.3 ML Ni. With further increasing CO exposure, however, a peak around 1800 cm<sup>−1</sup> is found (see <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> b). The peak around 1860 cm<sup>−1</sup> would correspond to CO adrorbed in bridge or hollow Rh sites. The vibration at 1800 cm<sup>−1</sup> could be from Ni bridge sites, as these sites are occupied first on a clean Ni(111) surface. However, one would also expect an influence of the Rh substrate on this species. Therefore, a clear assignment of the vibrational features is not possible from the available data.</p>
        <p>With one full monolayer of Ni on the surface there is a change in the CO adsorption as seen with RAIRS (see <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> a, b). With low CO exposures (0.25 and 0.5 L) again only a vibration in the on top region is found that corresponds to on top sites on the terrace. With 1 L of CO this peak not only shifts to higher wavenumbers (2052 cm<sup>−1</sup>), it also becomes asymmetric with a shoulder at lower wavenumbers (see <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> a). With 2 L CO the peak shifts up to 2100 cm<sup>−1</sup> with a shoulder around 2080 cm<sup>−1</sup>. With increasing CO exposure no further changes are seen. As the surface is nominally completely covered by Ni in this case one can assume that the vibration at 2100 cm<sup>−1</sup> stems from CO bound in an on top site on Ni.</p>
        <p>In the bridge and hollow site region (see <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> b) no peak can be seen with a CO exposure of 1 L. Only with higher exposures a broad peak around 1910 cm<sup>−1</sup> is found. This peak would fit to the bridge adsorption site on Ni(111) at high coverage <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. However, also bridge sites on the Rh steps have a vibration at this frequency <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Due to the fact that 1 ML Ni grows in a closed layer one can most likely attribute this peak to the Ni bridge site. The strong influence of the Rh substrate can be seen by the fact that on Ni(111) the bridge sites get occupied before the on top site, in contrast to the results shown here.</p>
        <p>With 2 ML Ni on Rh(553) the asymmetry in the RAIRS peaks at low CO exposures is already visible at 0.25 L CO (see <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>a). Otherwise the overall shape and evolution of the RAIRS data with increasing CO exposure are quite similar to the 1 ML Ni case. However, at an exposure of 2 L one has not only the peak at 2100 cm<sup>−1</sup> and the shoulder around 2080 cm<sup>−1</sup>, there is also an additional small peak at about 2055 cm<sup>−1</sup>. This suggests that under these conditions three different CO molecules in an on top geometry exist on the surface. This might be due to some Ni island formation on the surface, giving rise to Ni on top sites with a Rh directly underneath, with a Ni directly underneath and then the Rh and with two Ni layers underneath. When one compares <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref> a and <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> a one can see that the peak around 2055 cm<sup>−1</sup> seen with 2 ML Ni is already visible as a very small shoulder around 2050 cm<sup>−1</sup> with 1 ML Ni. This suggests that partial Ni island formation already occurs with 1 ML Ni.</p>
        <p>The RAIR spectra in the hollow and bridge adsorption site region are shown in <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref> b. Again, adsorption in this region is only found with CO exposures higher than 1 L, in contrast to what one would expect from Ni(111). A peak around 1930 cm<sup>−1</sup> is found with 2 L CO, which increases in intensity with an exposure of 10 L (see <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref> b). In comparison with the 1 ML Ni case (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> b) the peaks are smaller and at slightly higher wavenumbers. This might be due to a reduced amount of Ni terraces, where such bridge sites are possible.</p>
        <p>Finally the RAIRS measurements were also done with a coverage of 3 ML Ni on the Rh(553) surface. In this case the TPD shows only one asymmetric peak suggesting not too many differences between the available adsorption sites. This is also reflected in the IR data as can be seen in <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11</xref>. There the on top region is shown. With a CO exposure of 0.5 L the RAIR spectrum already looks like the spectra found with high exposures on the surface with 2 ML Ni. The main peak is at 2080 cm<sup>−1</sup> and a broad shoulder around 2060 cm<sup>−1</sup> is also found with 3 ML Ni (see <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11</xref>). This means that the shape is similar to the case with 2 ML Ni, but the peak is found at lower wavenumbers, which is in accordance with the fact that the CO stretching frequency in the on top configuration shifts to higher wavenumbers with increasing CO coverage.</p>
        <p>On the surface with 3 ML Ni and higher CO exposures (2 and 10 L) only one clear peak at 2100 cm<sup>−1</sup> is found. The increased intensity suggests a more ordered CO structure as compared with the smaller CO exposure. A clear change to lower intensity with an order disorder transition in the CO stretching frequency has been found before <xref rid="bib12 bib16" ref-type="bibr">[12,16]</xref>.</p>
        <p>With three monolayers of Ni on Rh(553) one would expect that the CO adsorption is quite similar to a clean Ni surface. However, again the on top sites are filled first in contrast to what is known for pure Ni <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Actually, in the case of 3 ML Ni no vibrations corresponding to CO in bridge or hollow sites have been found. Either these states are screened by the on top states <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, or the Ni terraces are too small to accommodate enough bridge sites to make them detectable in IR due to Ni island formation.</p>
        <p>To distinguish between these two options a detailed STM characterisation of the Ni growth on Rh(553) would be necessary.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec4">
      <label>4</label>
      <title>Conclusions</title>
      <p>The adsorption of carbon monoxide on Ni decorated stepped Rh(553) is markedly different than on the Ni free Rh(553) surface. Already 0.1 ML Ni completely quench the bride site on the steps found on Ni free Rh(553). At the same time the thermal desorption spectra change under these conditions from just one broad desorption peak on Ni free Rh(553) to 4 different desorption features that overlap with each other. A tentative assignment of these peaks based on IR data and comparison to Ni free Rh(553) and stepped Ni surfaces has been made. With increasing amount of Ni on the surface the TPD spectra slowly gain a similarity to TPD spectra obtained from Ni(111) and stepped Ni surfaces. The RAIRS results clearly show that up to 3 ML Ni on Rh(553) first the on top adsorption sites are occupied by CO and only at higher CO coverage also the hollow and bridge sites are occupied. This is in contrast to the Ni(111) surface where the bridge and hollow sites get occupied first. This difference could be due to the electronic influence of the Rh substrate and/or to the strain in the Ni overlayer due to the lattice mismatch between Ni and Rh.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lang</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Joyner</surname>
              <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Somorjai</surname>
              <given-names>G.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Surf Sci</source>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <year>1972</year>
          <fpage>454</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Somorjai</surname>
              <given-names>G.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Introduction to surface chemistry and catalysis</chapter-title>
          <year>1994</year>
          <publisher-name>J. Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Parteder</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Allegretti</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wagner</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramsey</surname>
              <given-names>M.G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Surnev</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Netzer</surname>
              <given-names>F.P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>J Phys Chem C</source>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <issue>49</issue>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>19272</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shiraki</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fujisawa</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nantoh</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kawai</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Phys Rev Lett</source>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <year>2004</year>
          <fpage>096102</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15089491</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shiraki</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fujisawa</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nantoh</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kawai</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>J Phys Soc Jpn</source>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <year>2005</year>
          <fpage>2033</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schoiswohl</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mittendorfer</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Surnev</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramsey</surname>
              <given-names>M.G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andersen</surname>
              <given-names>J.N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Netzer</surname>
              <given-names>F.P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Surf Sci</source>
          <volume>600</volume>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>L274</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schoiswohl</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mittendorfer</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Surnev</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramsey</surname>
              <given-names>M.G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andersen</surname>
              <given-names>J.N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Netzer</surname>
              <given-names>F.P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Phys Rev Lett</source>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>126102</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17025981</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wagner</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stroppa</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mittendorfer</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramsey</surname>
              <given-names>M.G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Surnev</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Netzer</surname>
              <given-names>F.P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Surf Sci</source>
          <volume>604</volume>
          <year>2010</year>
          <fpage>1406</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <label>9</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Surnev S. Private communications.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Krenn</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schennach</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>J Chem Phys</source>
          <volume>120</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2004</year>
          <fpage>5729</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15267451</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Krenn</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koch</surname>
              <given-names>H.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schennach</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Vacuum</source>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <issue>1–3</issue>
          <year>2005</year>
          <fpage>40</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koch</surname>
              <given-names>H.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singnurkar</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schennach</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stroppa</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mittendorfer</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>J Phys Chem C</source>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>806</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stroppa</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mittendorfer</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andersen</surname>
              <given-names>J.N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parteder</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Allegretti</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Surnev</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>J Phys Chem C</source>
          <volume>113</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>942</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Benndorf</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meyer</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>J Vac Sci Technol</source>
          <volume>A8</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>1990</year>
          <fpage>2677</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Surnev</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yates</surname>
              <given-names>J.T.</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Surf Sci</source>
          <volume>201</volume>
          <year>1988</year>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Krenn</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bako</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schennach</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>J Chem Phys</source>
          <volume>124</volume>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>144703</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16626227</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Katano</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bandara</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kubota</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Onda</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wada</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Domen</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Surf Sci</source>
          <volume>427–428</volume>
          <year>1999</year>
          <fpage>337</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koel</surname>
              <given-names>B.E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Surf Sci</source>
          <volume>327</volume>
          <year>1995</year>
          <fpage>38</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>This work was supported by the Austrian Science Fund (FWF).</p>
    </ack>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="fig1">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>(A) Thermal desorption of CO from Rh(553) decorated with 0.1 ML Ni as a function of CO coverage. The heating rate was 4 ks<sup>−1</sup>. The CO exposure was a) 0.25 L, b) 0.5 L, c) 1 L, d) 2 L, e) 4 L, f) 8 L and g) 10 L (B) CO desorption from clean Rh(553).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig2">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Thermal desorption of CO from Rh(553) decorated with 0.3 ML Ni as a function of CO coverage. The heating rate was 4 ks<sup>−1</sup>. The CO exposure was a) 0.25 L, b) 0.5 L, c) 1 L, d) 2 L, e) 4 L, f) 8 L and g) 10 L.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig3">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Thermal desorption of CO from Rh(553) decorated with 0.5 ML Ni as a function of CO coverage. The heating rate was 4 ks<sup>−1</sup>. The CO exposure was a) 0.25 L, b) 0.5 L, c) 1 L, d) 2 L, e) 4 L, f) 8 L and g) 10 L.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig4">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Thermal desorption of CO from Rh(553) decorated with 1 ML Ni as a function of CO coverage. The heating rate was 4 ks<sup>−1</sup>. The CO exposure was a) 0.25 L, b) 0.5 L, c) 1 L, d) 2 L, e) 10 L.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr4"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig5">
      <label>Fig. 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Thermal desorption of CO from Rh(553) decorated with 3 ML Ni as a function of CO coverage. The heating rate was 4 ks<sup>−1</sup>. The CO exposure was a) 0. 5 L, b) 2 L, c) 10 L.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr5"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig6">
      <label>Fig. 6</label>
      <caption>
        <p>RAIR spectra of CO adsorbed on 0.1 ML Ni on Rh(553). a) On top region and b) bridge and hollow region. The CO exposures are given in the figures.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr6"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig7">
      <label>Fig. 7</label>
      <caption>
        <p>RAIR spectra of CO adsorbed on 0.3 ML Ni on Rh(553). a) On top region and b) bridge and hollow region. The CO exposures are given in the figures.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr7"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig8">
      <label>Fig. 8</label>
      <caption>
        <p>RAIR spectra of CO adsorbed on 0.5 ML Ni on Rh(553). a) On top region and b) bridge and hollow region. The CO exposures are given in the figures.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr8"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig9">
      <label>Fig. 9</label>
      <caption>
        <p>RAIR spectra of CO adsorbed on 1.0 ML Ni on Rh(553). a) On top region and b) bridge and hollow region. The CO exposures are given in the figures.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr9"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig10">
      <label>Fig. 10</label>
      <caption>
        <p>RAIR spectra of CO adsorbed on 2.0 ML Ni on Rh(553). a) On top region and b) bridge and hollow region. The CO exposures are given in the figures.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr10"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig11">
      <label>Fig. 11</label>
      <caption>
        <p>RAIR spectra of CO adsorbed on 3.0 ML Ni on Rh(553), on top region. The CO exposures are given in the figure.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr11"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>