<article xmlns="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="brief-report">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Magn Reson</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Journal of Magnetic Resonance</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1090-7807</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1096-0856</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3000495</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20850362</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">YJMRE4510</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmr.2010.08.016</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Communication</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Observation of NMR noise from solid samples</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Schlagnitweit</surname>
            <given-names>Judith</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dumez</surname>
            <given-names>Jean-Nicolas</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nausner</surname>
            <given-names>Martin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jerschow</surname>
            <given-names>Alexej</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Elena-Herrmann</surname>
            <given-names>Bénédicte</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Müller</surname>
            <given-names>Norbert</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>norbert.mueller@jku.at</email>
          <email>norbert.mueller@jk.uni-linz.ac.at</email>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Johannes Kepler University in Linz, Institute of Organic Chemistry, Altenbergerstraße 69, 4040 Linz, Austria</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Université de Lyon, Centre de RMN à très hauts champs, CNRS/ENS Lyon/UCBL, 5 rue de la Doua, 69100 Villeurbanne, France</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Chemistry Department, New York University, New York, NY 10003, USA</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. Fax: +43 732 2468 8747. <email>norbert.mueller@jku.at</email><email>norbert.mueller@jk.uni-linz.ac.at</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>207-206</volume>
      <issue>1-6</issue>
      <fpage>168</fpage>
      <lpage>172</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>2</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2010 Elsevier Inc.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Elsevier Inc.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/authorsview.authors/supplementalterms1.0">certain conditions</ext-link>.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>We demonstrate that proton NMR noise signals, i.e. NMR spectra without excitation by radio frequency, can be obtained from solid samples. Experimental results are shown for static and magic-angle spinning conditions. In addition, a tuning procedure based on the probes’ NMR noise characteristics and similar to the one described previously for liquids probes can also be used to optimize signal-to-noise ratios in <sup>1</sup>H-MAS experiments.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>NMR noise</kwd>
        <kwd>Spin-noise</kwd>
        <kwd>Tuning</kwd>
        <kwd>Matching</kwd>
        <kwd>Signal-to-noise ratio</kwd>
        <kwd>Sensitivity</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Even at equilibrium an ensemble of spins gives rise to a small fluctuating signal. This phenomenon was predicted by Bloch <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref> in 1946, and was later detected under a variety of conditions for liquid <sup>1</sup>H samples <xref rid="b0010 b0015 b0020 b0025 b0030" ref-type="bibr">[2–6]</xref> . For hyperpolarized solutions, Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) noise has been reported for both <sup>69</sup>Xe <xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> and, more recently <sup>1</sup>H <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. NMR noise can also be used as an alternative tuning indicator, leading to the so called spin-noise tuning optimum (SNTO) <xref rid="b0030 b0045 b0050" ref-type="bibr">[6,9,10]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In this report, we demonstrate examples of the detection of NMR noise in solid state NMR under both static and MAS conditions.</p>
      <p>In previous communications <xref rid="b0025 b0030" ref-type="bibr">[5,6]</xref> we referred to this noise by the term <italic>spin-noise</italic> only. In view of recent results <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> we prefer to use the term <italic>NMR noise</italic>, which encompasses the proper spin-noise (i.e. residual fluctuations from statistically incomplete cancellation) <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref> and the conceptually distinct, but often accompanying effect of absorbed circuit noise (ACN) <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0010">
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Experimental</title>
      <p>NMR noise spectra of static powders were acquired on a Bruker 500 MHz DRX instrument equipped with a liquids-type high-resolution cryogenically cooled (TXI) triple resonance probe. The solid samples were finely ground powders of hexamethylbenzene (Aldrich) and adamantane (VWR chemicals) filled into standard 5 mm NMR sample tubes.</p>
      <p>Magic-angle spinning (MAS) NMR noise data were collected on a Bruker 500 MHz Avance III system using a standard 4 mm triple resonance MAS probe in combination with two different dedicated solids high-power preamplifiers and a low-power, low noise preamplifier. The latter designed for high-resolution liquid state NMR was used, since the higher intrinsic noise levels in the broadband receiving chain of a typical solids spectrometer make detection of NMR noise very demanding. To differentiate between probe and preamplifier effects additional experiments were performed using a 4 mm double resonance MAS probe.</p>
      <p>To minimize the pickup from external rf-sources, the <sup>1</sup>H-pulse cable coming from the power amplifier was disconnected from the preamplifier and a 50 Ω terminator was attached to the preamplifier instead. The <sup>1</sup>H pulse amplifier’s mains supply was switched off. The X/Y-channels rf-connectors of the probe were also terminated with 50 Ω.</p>
      <p>Data were collected (using a pseudo 2D acquisition sequence (containing no pulse) storing one noise block per row) and processed as detailed in Ref. <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>.</p>
      <p>For the static wide line experiments 16 K (for adamantane) and 20 K (for hexamethylbenzene) data blocks were collected with 160 ppm spectral width and 256 points in the direct dimension of acquisition, for a total experimental time of approximately 15 min.</p>
      <p>In order to find the initial noise signal in the MAS experiments and to optimize tuning and matching conditions until a symmetrical dip line shape for the noise signal was observed (this condition is henceforth referred to as spin-noise tuning optimum – SNTO), the rotor was first filled with H<sub>2</sub>O and noise measurements were carried out at 3 kHz MAS frequency with 10 ppm spectral width. The experiments on adamantane were performed under similar conditions, albeit using a spectral width of 50 ppm, 8 kHz MAS frequency, and 32–256 K data blocks to obtain sufficient noise signal for total experimental times of approximately 140 min to 18 h.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0015">
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Results and discussion</title>
      <sec id="s0020">
        <label>3.1</label>
        <title>Static samples</title>
        <p>The static solid samples used, adamantane and hexamethylbenzene, are not considered “typical” solids, since high internal mobility in these plastic solids narrows the spectra <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. However, due to the spectral width limitations imposed by the hardware of a liquid state spectrometer, these samples were chosen to demonstrate the feasibility of noise NMR on static solids. In <xref rid="f0005 f0010" ref-type="fig">Figs. 1 and 2</xref> we compare conventional NMR spectra (called <italic>pulse spectra</italic> in the following) to noise NMR spectra for the two plastic solids. The short transverse relaxation times in solids allow for very short noise block acquisition times and therefore permit highly efficient collection of NMR data as compared to pulse spectra, as longitudinal relaxation is irrelevant in the absence of excitation. In spite of the large number of acquired data blocks the total duration of acquisition (excluding buffer transfer times and internal spectrometer delays) for the spectra shown in <xref rid="f0005 f0010" ref-type="fig">Figs. 1b and 2</xref>b was only several seconds for each. These remarkably short pure acquisition times for noise spectra of static solids highlight an application potential of NMR noise detection for specialized applications to very slowly relaxing nuclei, such as, for example, found in nano-diamond powder <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>.</p>
        <p>To compensate for the non-uniform rf-background noise of the narrow-band spectrometer system used, baseline corrections were required for wide line spectra. For this purpose a noise power spectrum obtained with an empty NMR tube under identical conditions was subtracted from the initial noise power spectra of each sample.</p>
        <p>In the <sup>1</sup>H noise spectrum of adamantane (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>b) obtained in this way one can see a spike near zero frequency arising from incomplete cancellation of coherent artifacts near the carrier frequency. While such artifacts are usually negligible in noise spectra of liquid samples <xref rid="b0030 b0045" ref-type="bibr">[6,9]</xref>, they can be prominent in wide line noise NMR spectra, because the energy spectral density of the wide line solid signal is much weaker than a corresponding high resolution NMR noise signal. Since the decoherence times of these electronic artifacts is much longer than the solid samples’ <sup>1</sup>H transverse relaxation time, which determines the line shapes of NMR noise signals under conditions, where radiation damping can be neglected <xref rid="b0030 b0040 b0065" ref-type="bibr">[6,8,13]</xref>, there is a simple remedy: the coherent electronic signals are efficiently suppressed by pair-wise subtraction of subsequent noise data blocks before Fourier transform. This is demonstrated in the noise spectrum of solid hexamethylbenzene shown in <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>b, which was otherwise processed like the spectrum in <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>b. Due to the random nature of the NMR noise signal this subtraction procedure results in a signal loss by a factor (√2)<sup>–1</sup>.</p>
        <p>Comparing the pulse spectra to the noise spectra in <xref rid="f0005 f0010" ref-type="fig">Figs. 1 and 2</xref> one can see that the line shapes are well reproduced. It is noteworthy here that, if the temperature ratio <italic>T</italic><sub>sample</sub>/<italic>T</italic><sub>coil</sub> &gt; 2, these wide line noise spectra are always positive (i.e. the <sup>1</sup>H noise is always adding to the thermal noise) irrespective of the tuning offset, since <italic>T</italic><sub>2 </sub>≪ <italic>T</italic><sub>rd</sub>, as can be rationalized from Eqs. (2) to (4) in Ref. <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0025">
        <label>3.2</label>
        <title>Magic-angle spinning experiments</title>
        <p>Using MAS NMR we observed <sup>1</sup>H NMR noise spectra for liquid H<sub>2</sub>O and adamantane powder using both a triple and a double resonance probe in combination with three different preamplifiers.</p>
        <p>According to the description of the line shape of the spin-noise signal by McCoy and Ernst <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, a pure Lorentzian absorption signal (“dip”) should occur, if the resonance frequency of the rf-circuit coincides with the Larmor frequency. As described for liquid state NMR noise experiments <xref rid="b0030 b0045" ref-type="bibr">[6,9]</xref> the tuning required to obtain this dip line shape may deviate from the conventional tuning optimum (CTO). This offset also does not generally coincide with the optimum determined by minimizing reflected power through an external reflection bridge. This was also the case for the triple and double resonance probes in combination with two preamplifiers, where the noise power signal exhibits a dispersive line shape at the CTO.</p>
        <p><xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> shows noise spectra of H<sub>2</sub>O at different tuning offsets obtained using the triple resonance probe connected to a high-power <sup>1</sup>H/<sup>19</sup>F preamplifier. Note that both the observed line shape and the average (thermal) noise level are tuning-dependent. De-tuning of the other channels had no influence on the <sup>1</sup>H noise signal. The SNTO <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, where a pure “dip” power line shape (i.e. a noise level lower than average thermal noise) was seen, was at a tuning offset of 365 kHz from the resonance frequency. This offset varies between different probes and preamplifiers as shown in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p>
        <p>Using a (<sup>1</sup>H/<sup>13</sup>C) double resonance MAS probe instead, surprisingly, only positive noise signals could be found within the entire tuning and matching range. We concluded that the SNTO for this probe/amplifier connection lay outside the range accessible by the tuning capacitors.</p>
        <p>Using a high-power (solids) low noise preamplifier, the dip tuning offset was zero. This was the case for this preamplifier with all probes used.</p>
        <p>In combination with a low-power preamplifier the shape of the tuning curve was significantly different. The pure dip signal was not found with the normal routine within the tuning ranges of both probes. De-matching had a significant influence on both the noise line shape and the average thermal noise level. In the case of the triple resonance probe, slight de-matching, in case of the double resonance probe (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>), significant de-matching (a new minimum occurred in the tuning curve) together with de-tuning allowed us to find settings that gave rise to a dip line shape of the noise signal, in a trial-and-error approach. A more systematic approach is under investigation in our laboratories.</p>
        <p>Apparently there can be more than one combination of tuning and matching adjustments that yield an NMR noise dip signal, at least on some probes.</p>
        <p>The MAS tuning and matching conditions found for the H<sub>2</sub>O sample were also used for adamantane. In this case, where a dip was found by de-tuning only, the probe was tuned to the same SNTO frequency as found for H<sub>2</sub>O. If de-tuning and de-matching were necessary to find the dip, the controls were adjusted until the conventional tuning curve resembled as closely as possible the one found with H<sub>2</sub>O.</p>
        <p>In <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> pulse and noise spectra of adamantane obtained under conventional tuning (CTO) and SNTO conditions are compared. In the pulse spectra one can see that a substantial signal gain is achieved for both probes at the SNTO compared to the CTO: about 30% and 20% (for the triple and double resonance probes, respectively). As reported for liquid state spectra <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> and as a consequence of the tuning offsets and sub-optimal matching for pulse conditions the pulse durations increase concomitantly. The thermal noise also depends on the tuning and matching. The noise level is somewhat bigger at SNTO-conditions for the probes tested (<xref rid="t0010 t0015" ref-type="table">Tables 2 and 3</xref>).</p>
        <p>Comparing the wide line noise spectra and the MAS noise spectra, a most noteworthy difference is that a dip noise signal is found for the MAS case only. This behavior can be understood well within the modified Nyquist treatment by considering the difference of scale between <italic>T</italic><sub>2</sub> and <italic>T</italic><sub>rd</sub> in line with Eqs. (2)–(4) in Ref. <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0030">
      <label>4</label>
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>The properties of NMR noise signals with respect to line shape, thermal noise level and tuning dependence resemble those observed for liquid state NMR <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. The static solids investigated on a high-resolution cryogenically cooled liquids probe showed a positive (bump) NMR noise response, which indicates prevailing of pure spin-noise as opposed to absorbed circuit noise <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. The short transverse relaxation times in static solids efficiently quench radiation damping, allowing straightforward observation of pure spin-noise.</p>
      <p>The line shape of the NMR noise signal from MAS probes does not only depend on tuning but is also significantly influenced by the matching adjustment and the preamplifier used. In some cases, only significant de-matching allowed to arrive at the spin-noise tuning optimum (SNTO).</p>
      <p>The SNTO offsets are not influenced significantly by the sample properties. For example, it is nearly the same for liquid H<sub>2</sub>O and solid adamantane. For this reason, it suffices to determine the spin-noise tuning offset only once for a particular probe/preamplifier pair.</p>
      <p>At SNTO conditions with large offsets from the Larmor frequency the signal of MAS pulse spectra can be enhanced by up to 20–30% as compared to the conventional tuning conditions. Similarly, large tuning offsets have been reported recently by Rossini et al. <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref> for optimized NQR spectra of <sup>75</sup>As and <sup>35</sup>Cl.</p>
      <p>With respect to NMR probe circuits, we propose that a probe design, which makes the conventional tuning and noise optima coincide, can help to obtain probes performing better under both pulse and receiving conditions, thus ultimately making special tuning protocols such as finding the SNTO <xref rid="b0030 b0045" ref-type="bibr">[6,9]</xref> obsolete.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="b0005">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bloch</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nuclear induction</article-title>
          <source>Phys. Rev.</source>
          <volume>70</volume>
          <year>1946</year>
          <fpage>460</fpage>
          <lpage>475</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b0010">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sleator</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hahn</surname>
              <given-names>E.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hilbert</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clarke</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nuclear-spin noise</article-title>
          <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <year>1985</year>
          <fpage>1742</fpage>
          <lpage>1746</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10031911</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b0015">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sleator</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hahn</surname>
              <given-names>E.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hilbert</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Clarke</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nuclear-spin noise and spontaneous emission</article-title>
          <source>Phys. Rev. B</source>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <year>1987</year>
          <fpage>1969</fpage>
          <lpage>1981</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b0020">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guéron</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leroy</surname>
              <given-names>J.L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>NMR of water protons. The detection of their nuclear-spin noise, and a simple determination of absolute probe sensitivity based on radiation damping</article-title>
          <source>J. Magn. Reson.</source>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <year>1989</year>
          <fpage>209</fpage>
          <lpage>215</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b0025">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Müller</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jerschow</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nuclear spin noise imaging</article-title>
          <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>6790</fpage>
          <lpage>6792</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16636281</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b0030">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nausner</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schlagnitweit</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smrecki</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jerschow</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Müller</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Non-linearity and frequency shifts of nuclear magnetic spin-noise</article-title>
          <source>J. Magn. Reson.</source>
          <volume>198</volume>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>73</fpage>
          <lpage>79</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19232505</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b0035">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Desvaux</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marion</surname>
              <given-names>D.J.Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huber</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berthault</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nuclear spin-noise spectra of hyperpolarized systems</article-title>
          <source>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</source>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>4341</fpage>
          <lpage>4343</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b0040">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Giraudeau</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Müller</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jerschow</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frydman</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><sup>1</sup>H NMR noise measurements in hyperpolarized liquid samples</article-title>
          <source>Chem. Phys. Lett.</source>
          <volume>489</volume>
          <year>2010</year>
          <fpage>107</fpage>
          <lpage>112</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b0045">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marion</surname>
              <given-names>D.J.-Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Desvaux</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An alternative tuning approach to enhance NMR signals</article-title>
          <source>J. Magn. Reson.</source>
          <volume>193</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>153</fpage>
          <lpage>157</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18462967</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b0050">
        <label>10</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">M. Nausner, M. Goger, E. Bendet-Taicher, J. Schlagnitweit, A. Jerschow, N. Müller, Signal enhancement in protein NMR using the spin noise tuning optimum, J. Biomol. NMR, <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s10858-010-9446-4">doi:10.1007/s10858-010-9446-4</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b0055">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Slichter</surname>
              <given-names>W.P.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nuclear magnetic relaxation in organic crystals</article-title>
          <source>Mol. Cryst. Liq. Cryst.</source>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <year>1969</year>
          <fpage>81</fpage>
          <lpage>99</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b0060">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Levin</surname>
              <given-names>E.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fang</surname>
              <given-names>X.W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bud’ko</surname>
              <given-names>S.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Straszheim</surname>
              <given-names>W.E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McCallum</surname>
              <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt-Rohr</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Magnetization and <sup>13</sup>C NMR spin-lattice relaxation of nanodiamond powder</article-title>
          <source>Phys. Rev. B</source>
          <volume>77</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>054418</fpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b0065">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McCoy</surname>
              <given-names>M.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ernst</surname>
              <given-names>R.R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nuclear spin noise at room temperature</article-title>
          <source>Chem. Phys. Lett.</source>
          <volume>159</volume>
          <year>1989</year>
          <fpage>587</fpage>
          <lpage>593</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="b0070">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rossini</surname>
              <given-names>A.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hamaed</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schurko</surname>
              <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The application of frequency swept pulses for the acquisition of nuclear quadrupole resonance spectra</article-title>
          <source>J. Magn. Reson.</source>
          <volume>207</volume>
          <year>2010</year>
          <fpage>32</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20576454</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>These results were first presented in part at the joint EUROMAR 2010 and 17th ISMAR Conference (July 4–9, 2010, Florence Italy) supported by the European Science Foundation (ESF) as part of the EMAR project. The research was supported by the FWF (Austrian Science Funds) Project No. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:P19635">P19635</ext-link>-N17 and by the European Union FP7 Project EAST-NMR (Contract No. 228461). Additional financial support by the Access to Research Infrastructures activity in the 6th Framework Programme of the EC (Contract No. RII3-026145, EU-NMR) for conducting the research is gratefully acknowledged.</p>
    </ack>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="f0005">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p><sup>1</sup>H single pulse (a) and noise (b) spectra of adamantane powder acquired at 500 MHz with a cryogenically cooled triple resonance probe. Acquisition parameters are given in Section <xref rid="s0010" ref-type="sec">2</xref>.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0010">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p><sup>1</sup>H single pulse (a) and noise (b) spectra of hexamethylbenzene powder. Acquisition parameters are given in Section <xref rid="s0010" ref-type="sec">2</xref>.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr2"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0015">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Tuning dependence of the line shape of the H<sub>2</sub>O <sup>1</sup>H noise signal for a triple resonance MAS probe in combination with a high-power <sup>1</sup>H/<sup>19</sup>F preamplifier. Data were acquired using the general parameters, given in Section <xref rid="s0010" ref-type="sec">2</xref>. The line shape at the CTO (a) has a dispersive character (shown in blue colour, marked with “CTO”). The “dip” line shape (e) was found by de-tuning the probe by 365 kHz. Spectra (b), (c) and (d) illustrate the line shape changes while de-tuning. In addition the conventional tuning curve (sweep width 50 MHz) is shown as a screen shot in the inset frame, which exhibits a notably different shape compared to those in <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr3"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0020">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Tuning and matching dependence of the <sup>1</sup>H<sub>2</sub>O noise signal for the double resonance MAS probe connected via a low-power, low noise liquids preamplifier. The left part of the figure shows that de-tuning does not change the line shape of the signal much, while the (thermal) noise level increases, starting from the CTO (a), gradually de-tuning more and more (b), (c) and (d) up to almost −8 MHz offset (e). Significant de-matching starting from point (b) resulted in the line shape (f). De-matching of the probe lead to a new global minimum in the conventional tuning curve (tuning offsets under “de-matched conditions” are marked by asterisks). The dip-type noise signal (h) was found by trial and error adjustments of the tuning and matching capacitors from situation (f). Data were acquired using the parameters, given in Section <xref rid="s0010" ref-type="sec">2</xref>. The line shape at the CTO has a pure positive character (“bump”, shown in blue, marked with “CTO”). Conventional tuning curves (sweep width 50 MHz) (i, j, k) correspond to the spectra (a, e, h), respectively. Light blue lines mark the centre frequencies (500.16 MHz), the dark blue line in (j) shows the position of the maximum tuning offset (e) accessible by the tuning capacitor and the red line in (h) designates the SNTO.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr4"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0025">
      <label>Fig. 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Comparison of noise spectra (b and c) and pulse spectra (a) of adamantane, obtained using the triple resonance probe connected to a low-power, low noise liquids preamplifier, at SNTO (red) and CTO (blue) conditions.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr5"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="t0005" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Tuning frequency at the NMR noise dip (found with H<sub>2</sub>O) for different probe – preamplifier – combinations (using the preamplifiers’ manufacturer’s shorthand designations).</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Probe</th>
            <th>Preamplifier</th>
            <th>Tuning offset (kHz)</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Triple</td>
            <td>LP LNA <sup>1</sup>H</td>
            <td>1365<xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td/>
            <td>HP LNA <sup>1</sup>H</td>
            <td>0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td/>
            <td>HPHP <sup>1</sup>H/<sup>19</sup>F</td>
            <td>365</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="3">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Double</td>
            <td>LP LNA <sup>1</sup>H</td>
            <td>7165<xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn">b</xref></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td/>
            <td>HP LNA <sup>1</sup>H</td>
            <td>0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td/>
            <td>HPHP <sup>1</sup>H/<sup>19</sup>F</td>
            <td>Dip not found within tuning range</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn id="tblfn1">
          <label>a</label>
          <p>The probe had to be slightly dematched to arrive at the “dip”.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn id="tblfn2">
          <label>b</label>
          <p>Significant de-matching of the probe lead to a “dip”. In that case the tuning frequency is the frequency of a secondary very broad global minimum, which occured after de-matching.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap id="t0010" position="float">
      <label>Table 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Tuning dependence of the pulsed <sup>1</sup>H-NMR signal of solid adamantane, rms-noise, derived <italic>S</italic>/<italic>N</italic>, and 90° pulse length (p90) obtained on a triple resonance probe in combination with a low-power low noise preamplifier under CTO and SNTO conditions. Because of the long 90° pulse lengths and to allow us to use a higher receiver gain (RG set to 80.6, sufficient to avoid digitization noise problems on this spectrometer system) the spectra were acquired at 1/40 of the 90° pulse lengths. Note the small difference in the SNTO-frequencies obtained for adamantane (shown here) and for water (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Triple</th>
            <th>Tuning-offset (kHz)</th>
            <th>Signal amplitude</th>
            <th>Noise</th>
            <th><italic>S</italic>/<italic>N</italic></th>
            <th>p90 (μs)0 dB</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>CTO</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td>0.851 × 10<sup>6</sup></td>
            <td>330.841</td>
            <td>1285.7</td>
            <td align="char">6.0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>SNTO</td>
            <td align="char">1329</td>
            <td>1.104 × 10<sup>6</sup></td>
            <td>456.842</td>
            <td>1208.1</td>
            <td align="char">10.0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Difference</td>
            <td align="char">1329</td>
            <td>+29.7%</td>
            <td>+38.1%</td>
            <td>−6.0%</td>
            <td align="char">4.0</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap id="t0015" position="float">
      <label>Table 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Tuning dependence of the pulsed <sup>1</sup>H-NMR signal of solid adamantane, rms-noise, derived <italic>S</italic>/<italic>N</italic>, and 90° pulse length (p90) obtained on a double resonance probe under CTO and SNTO conditions. Because of the long 90° pulse lengths and to allow us to use a higher receiver gain (RG set to 71.8, sufficient to avoid digitization noise problems on this spectrometer system), the spectra were acquired at 1/20 of the 90° pulse lengths.</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Double</th>
            <th>Tuning offset (kHz)</th>
            <th>Signal</th>
            <th>Noise</th>
            <th><italic>S</italic>/<italic>N</italic></th>
            <th>p90 (μs), 0 dB</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>CTO</td>
            <td align="char">0</td>
            <td>1.180 × 10<sup>6</sup></td>
            <td>649.042</td>
            <td>908.955</td>
            <td align="char">5.5</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>SNTO</td>
            <td align="char">5941<xref rid="tblfn3" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></td>
            <td>1.425 × 10<sup>6</sup></td>
            <td>730.267</td>
            <td>975.512</td>
            <td align="char">9.0</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Difference</td>
            <td align="char">5941</td>
            <td>+20.8%</td>
            <td>+12.5%</td>
            <td>+29.7%</td>
            <td align="char">3.5</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn id="tblfn3">
          <label>a</label>
          <p>Tuning offset of a “new” very broad global minimum, which resulted from significantly de-matching the probe.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>