<article xmlns="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="other">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Curr Biol</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Current Biology </journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0960-9822</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1879-0445</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Cell Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2747023</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18957252</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CURBIO6741</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2008.09.002</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Dispatch</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Planar Cell Polarity: A Bridge Too Far?</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lawrence</surname>
            <given-names>Peter A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>pal@mrc-lmb.cam.ac.uk</email>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
          <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Struhl</surname>
            <given-names>Gary</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Casal</surname>
            <given-names>José</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1">
        <addr-line><sup>1</sup>Department of Zoology, University of Cambridge, Downing Street, Cambridge CB2 3EJ, UK</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff2">
        <addr-line><sup>2</sup>MRC Laboratory of Molecular Biology, Hills Road, Cambridge CB2 0QH, UK</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <aff id="aff3">
        <addr-line><sup>3</sup>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons, 701 West 168th Street, New York, New York 10032, USA</addr-line>
      </aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>18</volume>
      <issue>20</issue>
      <fpage>R959</fpage>
      <lpage>R961</lpage>
      <history/>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2008 ELL &amp; Excerpta Medica.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/authorsview.authors/supplementalterms1.0">certain conditions</ext-link>.</p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <title>Summary</title>
        <p>The mechanisms of planar cell polarity are being revealed by genetic analysis. Recent studies have provided new insights into interactions between three proteins involved in planar cell polarity: Flamingo, Frizzled and Van Gogh.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec1">
      <title>Main Text</title>
      <p>We now understand much of how cells know where they are in an embryo, but little of how they know their orientation, anterior from posterior, distal from proximal. Yet we believe that many, perhaps all, epithelial cells are polarised in the plane of the sheet — that they exhibit planar cell polarity, and that this polarity is vital. Planar cell polarity is not used primarily to <italic>make</italic> structures but more to <italic>orient</italic> them, making its study conceptually difficult. But, genetics is the right approach and <italic>Drosophila</italic> has proved the model of choice — particularly as the genes identified in the fly are conserved in other animals, including vertebrates <xref rid="bib1 bib2 bib3" ref-type="bibr">[1–3]</xref>. In the 60s it was argued that pervasive gradients are set up in the main axes of the body; it was suggested that the slope of a gradient could specify the polarity of cells <xref rid="bib4 bib5" ref-type="bibr">[4,5]</xref>. This viewpoint is still very much alive and these gradients are now being identified with the help of genetics. There is now a resurgence of interest in the mechanisms of planar cell polarity: three new papers <xref rid="bib6 bib7 bib8" ref-type="bibr">[6–8]</xref> (one in this issue of <italic>Current Biology</italic> <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>) report the use of both genetics and molecular techniques to get to one of the two hearts of the matter.</p>
      <p><italic>Drosophila</italic> cells make oriented structures; examples are hairs and bristles on the wing and abdomen. In the 80s, pioneers such as Adler and Gubb found genes whose mutants altered these polarities <xref rid="bib9 bib10" ref-type="bibr">[9,10]</xref>. Early on <italic>frizzled</italic> (<italic>fz</italic>) was identified; and, significantly, it was found that clones of <italic>fz<sup>−</sup></italic> cells repolarised neighbouring wild-type cells so that they point their hairs towards cells with lower Fz activity <xref rid="bib9 bib10" ref-type="bibr">[9,10]</xref>. It helps to think of the <italic>fz<sup>−</sup></italic> cells as <italic>sending</italic> and the wild-type cells as <italic>receiving</italic> polarising information <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Many different genetic mosaics can be made in <italic>Drosophila</italic> and, for example, each gene can be tested to see if it is needed in the sending, in the receiving cells or in both. This repolarisation assay has proved an incisive aid in the analysis of planar cell polarity.</p>
      <p>The first working models used a small group of genes: <italic>prickle</italic> (<italic>pk</italic>), <italic>fz</italic>, <italic>Van Gogh</italic> (<italic>Vang</italic>) (also called <italic>strabismus</italic>, <italic>stbm</italic>) and <italic>dishevelled</italic> (<italic>dsh</italic>). In the 90s it was found that, just before polarised structures are formed, some of these proteins become localised to one or other ends of the cell <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. It was suggested that some small initial bias (unknown) is amplified by interactions and feedback between these four proteins to polarise each cell; propagation from cell to cell would be driven by interactions across the intercellular space <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. This model was simulated in a powerful computer <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref> and became popular; however, complex computers are no match for simple experiments and the model looked feeble when it was found (in repolarisation assays) that <italic>pk</italic> and <italic>dsh</italic> are dispensable in <italic>both</italic> sending and receiving cells and so, for this central process, could be ignored <xref rid="bib11 bib15 bib16 bib17" ref-type="bibr">[11,15–17]</xref>. The model suffered further blows when we found that a cell completely lacking <italic>fz</italic> could be repolarised <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref> and that protein localisation itself appeared to be dispensible for repolarisation <xref rid="bib11 bib16" ref-type="bibr">[11,16]</xref>.</p>
      <p><italic>Flamingo</italic> (<italic>fmi</italic>, also known as <italic>starry night</italic> or <italic>stan</italic>), was largely left out of these models. In our assays, however, it was the only gene needed in <italic>both</italic> sending and receiving cells and, because its protein product is able to form homodimers from one cell to the next <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, we placed it at the centre of a new model <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. In our model, the Fmi homodimers act as intercellular bridges. We suggested that, using Fmi to compare its neighbours, each cell points its hair towards the neighbour with the lowest level of Fz activity, and that there is an intercellular feedback via Fmi, which brings the level of Fz activity in one cell towards an average of its neighbours. We argued that Fmi–Fmi homodimers act asymmetrically to convey the level of Fz activity in the sending cell to Vang in the receiving cell. Because information is actually going in both directions — in the wild-type, each cell will both send and receive — it follows Fmi can act in two ways in the same cell depending on whether it sends (with Fz) or receives (with Vang) (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). A more detailed version of this model was elaborated subsequently <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> and another similar one simulated <italic>in silico</italic> <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>.</p>
      <p>Chen <italic>et al.</italic> <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> recently reported the results of similar experiments to ours <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref> but, instead of monitoring hairs, they mostly looked at localisation of the proteins, a concordant indicator of polarity. They reached the same conclusions as we did <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, namely that Fmi is needed in both sending and receiving cells, placing Fmi centrally in planar cell polarity. They also shifted their attention from Pk and Dsh, conceding (though not stating) that their earlier models have been superseded. So we now have a model in which homodimers of Fmi make intercellular bridges, and, as the three new papers <xref rid="bib6 bib7 bib8" ref-type="bibr">[6–8]</xref> make clear, a new question of whether these bridges are conduits for polarising information, or are more passive, for example helping Fz and Vang to contact each other as ligand and receptor.</p>
      <p>Chen <italic>et al.</italic> <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> believe direct contact is implausible because of the wide gulf between the cells. If they are right, Fz might be able to mediate planar cell polarity without the cysteine-rich domain (CRD), part of the protein's amino-terminal ectodomain, and Chen <italic>et al.</italic> <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> offer some evidence for this. But their evidence conflicts with previous findings that the Fz ectodomain is essential for planar cell polarity <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. Also, in contrast to Chen <italic>et al.</italic> <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, and with stronger evidence, Wu and Mlodzik <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> find once again that the Fz CRD is essential. Extending the disagreement between the two papers, Wu and Mlodzik <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> not only find the interaction of Fz and Vang quite plausible, they actually find direct binding using pulldowns and binding assays in tissue culture cells — but they do not determine whether the binding is in <italic>trans</italic> (from cell to cell, as they assume) or in <italic>cis</italic> (which would fit with our evidence that Vang acts in <italic>cis</italic> to regulate Fz <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>). The data reported by Strutt and Strutt <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> agree with Wu and Mlodzik <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, providing independent evidence from tissue culture experiments that Vang and Fz can bind in <italic>trans</italic>, a binding that is enhanced in the presence of Fmi.</p>
      <p>In spite of the possible significance of direct intercellular binding of Vang and Fz, we know that Fmi is essential for propagation of planar cell polarity information — so how do the three proteins relate? Chen <italic>et al.</italic> <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> describe evidence from immunoprecipitation that Fz binds to Fmi, and with this Strutt and Strutt <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> agree. But none of the groups shows biochemical evidence of binding between Vang and Fmi. Also, using overexpressed Fmi <italic>in vivo</italic>, Strutt and Strutt <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> report that Fmi needs both Vang and Fz if it is to stabilise properly in the cell membrane and that it prefers to bind to Fz rather than to Vang. These mixed observations tie Vang, Fz and Fmi closely together but they do not tell us clearly how the information about Fz activity is exchanged, nor what are the structural or functional relationships between the three proteins.</p>
      <p>Chen <italic>et al.</italic> <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> ask whether Fmi acts actively (as we previously proposed <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>) or passively (as now proposed by Wu and Mlodzik <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>). They claim to answer by showing that <italic>Vang<sup>−</sup> fz<sup>−</sup></italic> sending cells do repolarise receiving cells when they strongly overexpress <italic>Fmi</italic> and argue that this means that Fmi can act instructively. However, this argument is undermined by the conflicting and positive finding of Wu and Mlodzik <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> that <italic>Vang<sup>−</sup> fz<sup>−</sup></italic> sending cells repolarise receiving cells, even without overexpressing Fmi. The contradictory results and conclusions described in the three papers <xref rid="bib6 bib7 bib8" ref-type="bibr">[6–8]</xref> show that we are not yet ready to answer this enigmatic question.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <label>1</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Adler</surname>
              <given-names>P.N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Planar signaling and morphogenesis in Drosophila</article-title>
          <source>Dev. Cell</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>525</fpage>
          <lpage>535</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12015961</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <label>2</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Klein</surname>
              <given-names>T.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mlodzik</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Planar cell polarization: an emerging model points in the right direction</article-title>
          <source>Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol.</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>23</fpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <label>3</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zallen</surname>
              <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Planar polarity and tissue morphogenesis</article-title>
          <source>Cell</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>129</volume>
          <fpage>1051</fpage>
          <lpage>1063</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17574020</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <label>4</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lawrence</surname>
              <given-names>P.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gradients in the insect segment: The orientation of hairs in the milkweed bug Oncopeltus fasciatus</article-title>
          <source>J. Exp. Biol.</source>
          <year>1966</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>607</fpage>
          <lpage>620</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <label>5</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stumpf</surname>
              <given-names>H.F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Über gefälleabhängige Bildungen des Insektensegmentes</article-title>
          <source>J. Insect Physiol.</source>
          <year>1966</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>601</fpage>
          <lpage>617</lpage>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <label>6</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>W.S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Antic</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matis</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Logan</surname>
              <given-names>C.Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Povelones</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>G.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nusse</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Axelrod</surname>
              <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Asymmetric homotypic interactions of the atypical cadherin Flamingo mediate intercellular polarity signaling</article-title>
          <source>Cell</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>133</volume>
          <fpage>1093</fpage>
          <lpage>1105</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18555784</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <label>7</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Strutt</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strutt</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differential stability of Flamingo protein complexes underlies the establishment of planar polarity in Drosophila</article-title>
          <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>1555</fpage>
          <lpage>1564</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18804371</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib8">
        <label>8</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mlodzik</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Frizzled extracellular domain is a ligand for Van Gogh/Stbm during nonautonomous planar cell polarity signaling</article-title>
          <source>Dev. Cell</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>462</fpage>
          <lpage>469</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18804440</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <label>9</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Adler</surname>
              <given-names>P.N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krasnow</surname>
              <given-names>R.E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tissue polarity points from cells that have higher Frizzled levels towards cells that have lower Frizzled levels</article-title>
          <source>Curr. Biol.</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>940</fpage>
          <lpage>949</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9382848</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <label>10</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gubb</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garcia-Bellido</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A genetic analysis of the determination of cuticular polarity during development in Drosophila melanogaster</article-title>
          <source>J. Embryol. Exp. Morphol.</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          <lpage>57</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6809878</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib11">
        <label>11</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lawrence</surname>
              <given-names>P.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Casal</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Struhl</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cell interactions and planar polarity in the abdominal epidermis of Drosophila</article-title>
          <source>Development</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>131</volume>
          <fpage>4651</fpage>
          <lpage>4664</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15329345</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <label>12</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Strutt</surname>
              <given-names>D.I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The asymmetric subcellular localisation of components of the planar polarity pathway</article-title>
          <source>Semin. Cell Dev. Biol.</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>225</fpage>
          <lpage>231</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12137731</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib13">
        <label>13</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tree</surname>
              <given-names>D.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shulman</surname>
              <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rousset</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scott</surname>
              <given-names>M.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gubb</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Axelrod</surname>
              <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prickle mediates feedback amplification to generate asymmetric planar cell polarity signaling</article-title>
          <source>Cell</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>371</fpage>
          <lpage>381</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12015986</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <label>14</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Amonlirdviman</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khare</surname>
              <given-names>N.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tree</surname>
              <given-names>D.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>W.S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Axelrod</surname>
              <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tomlin</surname>
              <given-names>C.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mathematical modeling of planar cell polarity to understand domineering nonautonomy</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>307</volume>
          <fpage>423</fpage>
          <lpage>426</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15662015</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <label>15</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adler</surname>
              <given-names>P.N.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The function of the frizzled pathway in the Drosophila wing is dependent on inturned and fuzzy</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>160</volume>
          <fpage>1535</fpage>
          <lpage>1547</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11973308</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <label>16</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Strutt</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strutt</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differential activities of the core planar polarity proteins during Drosophila wing patterning</article-title>
          <source>Dev. Biol.</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>302</volume>
          <fpage>181</fpage>
          <lpage>194</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17045581</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib17">
        <label>17</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Strutt</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strutt</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nonautonomous planar polarity patterning in Drosophila: Dishevelled-independent functions of Frizzled</article-title>
          <source>Dev. Cell</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>851</fpage>
          <lpage>863</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12479810</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <label>18</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Usui</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shima</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shimada</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirano</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burgess</surname>
              <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schwarz</surname>
              <given-names>T.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takeichi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Uemura</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Flamingo, a seven-pass transmembrane cadherin, regulates planar cell polarity under the control of Frizzled</article-title>
          <source>Cell</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <fpage>585</fpage>
          <lpage>595</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10490098</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <label>19</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Le Garrec</surname>
              <given-names>J.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lopez</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kerszberg</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Establishment and maintenance of planar epithelial cell polarity by asymmetric cadherin bridges: a computer model</article-title>
          <source>Dev. Dyn.</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>235</volume>
          <fpage>235</fpage>
          <lpage>246</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16258926</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <label>20</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>C.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strapps</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tomlinson</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Struhl</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evidence that the cysteine-rich domain of Drosophila Frizzled family receptors is dispensable for transducing Wingless</article-title>
          <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>15961</fpage>
          <lpage>15966</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15514021</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-wrap>
    <fig id="fig1">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Possible intercellular and intracellular relations between Fmi (blue), Fz (red) and Vang (green), according to different authors.</p>
        <p>Two membranes from neighbouring cells are shown. If a direct physical interaction is suggested, the molecules are shown in contact. In (A), the size of lettering refers to the original gradient of Fz activity, with the strength of colour of the molecules indicating the subsequent localisation of the proteins. The arrows show the direction of the flow of information: black is strong, grey is weak signalling. (A) Lawrence <italic>et al.</italic><xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>; (B) Chen <italic>et al.</italic><xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>; (C) Strutt and Strutt <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>; (D) Wu and Mlodzik <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr1"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-wrap>
</article>