<article xmlns="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="brief-report">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Antimicrob Agents</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>International Journal of Antimicrobial Agents</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0924-8579</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1872-7913</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier Science Publishers</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3030749</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21074373</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ANTAGE3432</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2010.09.006</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Short Communication</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>In vitro activity of <italic>N</italic>-chlorotaurine (NCT) in combination with NH<sub>4</sub>Cl against <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Fürnkranz</surname>
            <given-names>Ursula</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Nagl</surname>
            <given-names>Markus</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gottardi</surname>
            <given-names>Waldemar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Duchêne</surname>
            <given-names>Michael</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Aspöck</surname>
            <given-names>Horst</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Walochnik</surname>
            <given-names>Julia</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>julia.walochnik@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
          <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
          <xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>Institute of Specific Prophylaxis and Tropical Medicine, Center for Pathophysiology, Infectiology and Immunology, Medical University of Vienna, Kinderspitalgasse 15, 1090 Vienna, Austria</aff>
      <aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>Department of Hygiene, Microbiology and Social Medicine, Division of Hygiene and Medical Microbiology, Innsbruck Medical University, Fritz-Pregl-Strasse 3, 6020 Innsbruck, Austria</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor0005"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. Tel.: +43 1 40490 79446; fax: +43 1 40490 79435. <email>julia.walochnik@meduniwien.ac.at</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>37</volume>
      <issue>2-4</issue>
      <fpage>171</fpage>
      <lpage>173</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>28</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2010</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2011 Elsevier B.V.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Elsevier B.V. and the International Society of Chemotherapy</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/authorsview.authors/supplementalterms1.0">certain conditions</ext-link>.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Trichomoniasis, caused by the protozoan <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic>, is usually treated with metronidazole, however resistance is on the rise. In this study, <italic>N</italic>-chlorotaurine (NCT), a new endogenous mild active chlorine compound for topical use, killed <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> in vitro within 15 min of treatment at a concentration of 55 mM (1%), which is well tolerated by human tissue. The activity of NCT was further enhanced by addition of ammonium chloride (NH<sub>4</sub>Cl). A combination of 5.5 mM (0.1%) NCT plus 19 mM (0.1%) NH<sub>4</sub>Cl killed 100% of trichomonads within 5 min.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>Susceptible</kwd>
        <kwd><italic>N</italic>-Chlorotaurine</kwd>
        <kwd>Oxidant</kwd>
        <kwd>In vitro</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="sec0005">
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p><italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> is the causative agent of trichomoniasis, the most common non-viral sexually transmitted disease worldwide. Typical symptoms are vaginitis and cervicitis in women; in men the infection can lead to chronic prostatitis syndrome <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Metronidazole is the drug of choice for trichomoniasis, however treatment during pregnancy is problematic <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> and resistance is increasing <xref rid="bib0015 bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[3,4]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In a previous study, we demonstrated the amoebicidal effect of <italic>N</italic>-chlorotaurine (NCT) (Cl-HN-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-SO<sub>3</sub>Na), thereby establishing the activity of this compound against protozoa <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. NCT, the <italic>N</italic>-chloro derivative of the amino acid taurine produced by granulocytes and monocytes during the oxidative burst, is a long-lived oxidant that can be synthesised chemically <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> and applied topically for treatment of infections <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. It has broad-spectrum microbicidal activity against bacteria, viruses, fungi and protozoa <xref rid="bib0025 bib0035 bib0040 bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[5,7–9]</xref>. Phase I and II clinical studies have revealed high tolerability and therapeutic effects of regular applications of 55 mM (1%) NCT in the eye, sinuses, oral cavity, outer ear canal, skin ulcerations and urinary bladder <xref rid="bib0035 bib0050" ref-type="bibr">[7,10]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The antimicrobial activity of NCT against bacteria <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, fungi <xref rid="bib0040 bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[8,9]</xref> and free-living amoebae <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref> can be enhanced markedly by addition of ammonium chloride (NH<sub>4</sub>Cl) owing to the formation of monochloramine (NH<sub>2</sub>Cl) in equilibrium by transfer of the active chlorine atom <xref rid="bib0030 bib0035 bib0040 bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[6–9]</xref>. NH<sub>2</sub>Cl is more lipophilic than NCT and penetrates microorganisms more rapidly. For special indications, e.g. treatment of viral conjunctivitis, addition of NH<sub>4</sub>Cl to NCT might be an advantage <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The aim of the current study was to investigate the activity of NCT and its combination with NH<sub>4</sub>Cl against <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> in vitro.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec0010">
      <label>2</label>
      <title>Material and methods</title>
      <p>A metronidazole-susceptible (ATCC 30001) and a metronidazole-resistant (ATCC 50138) strain of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> were investigated for their susceptibilities to NCT. Both strains were grown under microaerophilic conditions in trypticase–yeast extract–maltose (TYM) medium <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref> at 37 °C and were subcultured every 72 h.</p>
      <p>NCT was produced synthetically at Innsbruck Medical University (Innsbruck, Austria) and was used alone as well as in combination with NH<sub>4</sub>Cl as previous studies had revealed a high synergistic potential for this substance <xref rid="bib0030 bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[6,8]</xref>. NCT (molecular weight 181.57 g/mol) <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> was used at final concentrations of between 5.5 mM (0.1%) and 55 mM (1%) dissolved in either TYM or phosphate-buffered saline (PBS). Trichomonads were treated for 5, 15 and 60 min at 37 °C. Short intervals were chosen because stability testing revealed that the oxidative capacity of 55 mM NCT is reduced by 15% after 1 min, by 90% after 1 h and by &gt;95% after 2 h in TYM. NH<sub>4</sub>Cl was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (Vienna, Austria) and was used in the molar ratio 1:3.4 and 1:29 (NCT:NH<sub>4</sub>Cl) as in previous studies <xref rid="bib0025 bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[5,8]</xref>. Control experiments revealed no antiparasitic effects of NH<sub>4</sub>Cl alone. Additional experiments with 5.5 mM (0.1%) NCT plus 19 mM (0.1%) NH<sub>4</sub>Cl (1:3.4) in PBS instead of TYM medium were performed to investigate the efficacy in the absence of chlorine consumption caused by unspecific reactions of NCT with the culture medium.</p>
      <p>Viability of trichomonads was followed by phase contrast microscopy and trypan blue (0.4%) staining, and 50% and 90% effective concentrations (EC<sub>50</sub> and EC<sub>90</sub> values) were calculated using non-linear regression models. Cytotoxicity of NCT against vaginal epithelial cells (ATCC; CRL 2616) was investigated using the EZ4U test (Biomedica GmbH, Vienna, Austria), which is a tetrazolium reduction assay. All experiments were carried out in triplicate and were repeated in two independent set-ups. For each experiment, a control series without NCT and additives was included.</p>
      <p>Single-factor analysis of variance (ANOVA) and Tukey's HSD test (SPSS 14.0; SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL) were used for statistical analyses. <italic>P</italic>-values of &lt;0.05 were considered significant.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="sec0015">
      <label>3</label>
      <title>Results and discussion</title>
      <p>NCT showed cytotoxic effects against both strains of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> tested. Treatment with 55 mM NCT (1%), a concentration well tolerated by all human tissues tested so far <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, led to 100% killing of both strains tested within 15 min in TYM medium (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). At lower concentrations in this medium, strain ATCC 30001 was more susceptible than strain ATCC 50138. The EC<sub>50</sub> of NCT was 9.0 mM for strain ATCC 30001, whilst it was 28.7 mM for strain ATCC 50138 after 1 h of treatment. EC<sub>90</sub> values were 9.8 mM and 36.7 mM, respectively.</p>
      <p>The activity of NCT was markedly enhanced by the addition of NH<sub>4</sub>Cl, explained by formation of the small and more lipophilic monochloramine (NH<sub>2</sub>Cl), which penetrates pathogens better than NCT and leads to faster oxidation of intracellular proteins <xref rid="bib0030 bib0035 bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[6–8]</xref>. In strain ATCC 30001, only one-third of the concentration of NCT was needed to achieve 100% killing when NH<sub>4</sub>Cl was added, i.e. 17 mM (0.3%) NCT plus 57 mM (0.3%) NH<sub>4</sub>Cl (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>); moreover, the killing time was reduced to 5 min. This effect was even greater when experiments were carried out in PBS instead of culture medium. In PBS, co-treatment with 5.5 mM (0.1%) NCT plus 19 mM (0.1%) NH<sub>4</sub>Cl also resulted in complete killing of trichomonads within 5 min (data not shown). Inactivation of NCT and the formed NH<sub>2</sub>Cl by reaction with constituents of the TYM medium must be assumed to contribute significantly to delayed killing in this medium, particularly at concentrations below 10 mM. Such chlorine consumption in the presence of organic material, in particular reducing thio compounds, is well known <xref rid="bib0030 bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[6,7]</xref>. It may also explain the relatively sharp threshold between highly active and inactive concentrations of NCT (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). In strain ATCC 50138, higher concentrations of NH<sub>4</sub>Cl (molar ratio 1:29) were necessary to achieve enhancement of activity in TYM medium.</p>
      <p>The metronidazole-sensitive strain (ATCC 30001) was more susceptible to NCT than the metronidazole-resistant strain (ATCC 50138), and this difference was statistically significant (<italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.001). An approximately three- to four-fold concentration of NCT required to kill 50% of the metronidazole-sensitive trichomonads was required to achieve the same killing rate in the metronidazole-resistant strain. Although the modes of action are different, since both metronidazole and NCT produce oxidative stress one could hypothesise that the more resistant strain has a better anti-oxidative protection system. This may be the case, but at the applied millimolar concentrations of NCT such mechanisms would not be sufficient. Since penetration of the pathogen rather than oxidation of the surface is the decisive step for killing by NCT <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, we assume that several factors, particularly differences in the membrane composition, may play a major role as has already been observed in other microorganisms <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>.</p>
      <p>In vivo studies have shown that 55 mM NCT (1%) is well tolerated by human mucosal tissue <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. The in vitro tolerability of human cells in cell culture to NCT is known to be significantly (ca. 50–100-fold) lower <xref rid="bib0065 bib0070 bib0075" ref-type="bibr">[13–15]</xref>. However, vaginal epithelial cells were observed to be relatively resistant to NCT in the current study. The EC<sub>50</sub> of NCT for these cells in vitro was 5.5 mM and the survival rate was 25% after treatment with 55 mM NCT for 1 h (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Tolerability to NCT was altogether significantly higher than to metronidazole, the standard drug for treatment of trichomoniasis. Increased tolerability of human cells to the agent in vivo compared with that in vitro can be explained by the fact that within tissues the cells are coherently organised in a structure affording better protection to oxidative agents. This has already been proven with human skin in vivo as well as human epidermis carcinoma cells in vitro <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.</p>
      <p>The stability of the aqueous solution of NCT depends on temperature. At 37 °C its oxidation capacity decreases to zero within 3 weeks, whereas it remains at 75% after storage at room temperature for 2 months <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. At sites of inflammation, oxidation capacity decreases more quickly owing to halogen-consuming proteins. After 15 min the oxidation capacity is reduced by 30–50% and after 2 h by up to 90% <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. However, as trichomonads are killed within 15 min, and even faster with the addition of NH<sub>4</sub>Cl, these decomposition rates are not likely to affect a possible therapeutic approach against trichomoniasis. Moreover, since human exudates demonstrated enhanced rather than decreased microbicidal activity of 0.5–1% NCT after topical application <xref rid="bib0040 bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[8,9]</xref>, it may be expected that NCT is also microbicidal against <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> in vivo after topical application.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, we have shown that NCT has strong trichomonacidal effects that are further enhanced by the addition of NH<sub>4</sub>Cl. Further investigations of its utility in <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> infections are required.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bib0005">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Skerk</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krhen</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schonwald</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cajic</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Markovinovic</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roglic</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The role of unusual pathogens in prostatitis syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Int J Antimicrob Agents</source>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <issue>Suppl. 1</issue>
          <year>2004</year>
          <fpage>S53</fpage>
          <lpage>S56</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15364308</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0010">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kazy</surname>
              <given-names>Z.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Puho</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Czeizel</surname>
              <given-names>A.E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Teratogenic potential of vaginal metronidazole treatment during pregnancy</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Obstet Gynecol Reprod Biol</source>
          <volume>123</volume>
          <year>2005</year>
          <fpage>174</fpage>
          <lpage>178</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16316810</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0015">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dunne</surname>
              <given-names>R.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dunn</surname>
              <given-names>L.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Upcroft</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O’Donoghue</surname>
              <given-names>P.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Upcroft</surname>
              <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Drug resistance in the sexually transmitted protozoan <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title>
          <source>Cell Res</source>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <year>2003</year>
          <fpage>239</fpage>
          <lpage>249</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12974614</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0020">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schwebke</surname>
              <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barrientes</surname>
              <given-names>F.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prevalence of <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> isolates with resistance to metronidazole and tinidazole</article-title>
          <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>4209</fpage>
          <lpage>4210</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17000740</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0025">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fürnkranz</surname>
              <given-names>U.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nagl</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gottardi</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Köhsler</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aspöck</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Walochnik</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cytotoxic activity of <italic>N</italic>-chlorotaurine on <italic>Acanthamoeba</italic> spp.</article-title>
          <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>470</fpage>
          <lpage>476</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18039920</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0030">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gottardi</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nagl</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chemical properties of <italic>N</italic>-chlorotaurine sodium, a key compound in the human defense system</article-title>
          <source>Arch Pharm (Weinheim)</source>
          <volume>335</volume>
          <year>2002</year>
          <fpage>411</fpage>
          <lpage>421</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12447914</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0035">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gottardi</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nagl</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>N</italic>-Chlorotaurine, a natural antiseptic with outstanding tolerability</article-title>
          <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <year>2010</year>
          <fpage>399</fpage>
          <lpage>409</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20053689</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0040">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nagl</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gottardi</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Enhancement of the bactericidal efficacy of <italic>N</italic>-chlorotaurine of inflammation samples and selected N–H compounds</article-title>
          <source>Hyg Med</source>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <year>1996</year>
          <fpage>597</fpage>
          <lpage>605</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0045">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nagl</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lass-Florl</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neher</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gunkel</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gottardi</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Enhanced fungicidal activity of <italic>N</italic>-chlorotaurine in nasal secretion</article-title>
          <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <year>2001</year>
          <fpage>871</fpage>
          <lpage>874</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11389121</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0050">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nagl</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nguyen</surname>
              <given-names>V.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gottardi</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ulmer</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Höpfl</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tolerability and efficacy of <italic>N</italic>-chlorotaurine in comparison with chloramine T for the treatment of chronic leg ulcers with a purulent coating: a randomized phase II study</article-title>
          <source>Br J Dermatol</source>
          <volume>149</volume>
          <year>2003</year>
          <fpage>590</fpage>
          <lpage>597</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14510994</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0055">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Clark</surname>
              <given-names>C.G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Diamond</surname>
              <given-names>L.S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Methods for cultivation of luminal parasitic protists of clinical importance</article-title>
          <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <year>2002</year>
          <fpage>329</fpage>
          <lpage>341</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12097242</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0060">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Beach</surname>
              <given-names>D.H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Holz</surname>
              <given-names>G.G.</given-names>
              <suffix>Jr.</suffix>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anekwe</surname>
              <given-names>G.E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lipids of <italic>Leishmania</italic> promastigotes</article-title>
          <source>J Parasitol</source>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <year>1979</year>
          <fpage>201</fpage>
          <lpage>216</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">448607</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0065">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kontny</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grabowska</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kowalczewski</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kurowska</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Janicka</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marcinkiewicz</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Taurine chloramine inhibition of cell proliferation and cytokine production by rheumatoid arthritis fibroblast-like synoviocytes</article-title>
          <source>Arthritis Rheum</source>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <year>1999</year>
          <fpage>2552</fpage>
          <lpage>2560</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10616000</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0070">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marcinkiewicz</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nowak</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grabowska</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bobek</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petrovska</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chain</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of murine dendritic cell functions in vitro by taurine chloramine, a major product of the neutrophil myeloperoxidase–halide system</article-title>
          <source>Immunology</source>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <year>1999</year>
          <fpage>371</fpage>
          <lpage>378</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10583596</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0075">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Levis</surname>
              <given-names>W.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quinn</surname>
              <given-names>M.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>S.Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schuller-Levis</surname>
              <given-names>G.B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of nitric oxide induced by mycobacterial lipoarabinomannan in murine macrophages: effects of interferon-β and taurine-chloramine</article-title>
          <source>Int J Lepr Other Mycobact Dis</source>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <year>2000</year>
          <fpage>444</fpage>
          <lpage>451</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11332287</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The authors thank Susanne Glöckl, Iveta Häfeli and Jacek Pietrzak (Institute of Specific Prophylaxis and Tropical Medicine, Medical University of Vienna, Vienna, Austria) for excellent technical assistance.</p>
      <p><italic>Funding</italic>: This study was supported partly by the <funding-source>International Relations Office of the Medical University of Vienna</funding-source> (Austria). The contributions of MN and WG were supported by the <funding-source id="gs0005">Austrian Science Fund (FWF)</funding-source> (grant no. L313-B13).</p>
      <p><italic>Competing interests</italic>: None declared.</p>
      <p><italic>Ethical approval</italic>: Not required.</p>
    </ack>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="fig0005">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Treatment of <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> ATCC 30001 with <italic>N</italic>-chlorotaurine (NCT) and co-treatment with NH<sub>4</sub>Cl in trypticase–yeast extract–maltose (TYM) medium: ▾, 55 mM (1%) NCT; ▴, 10 mM (0.18%) NCT; ○, 5.5 mM (0.1%) NCT; , 17 mM (0.3%) NCT + 57 mM (0.3%) NH<sub>4</sub>Cl; - - <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1.gif"/> - -, control. Mean value of three independent experiments; the standard deviation ranged between 0.14 and 0.21 log<sub>10</sub> for values exceeding 4 log<sub>10</sub> (not shown). <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 versus control for all zero survival values.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig0010">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Survival of vaginal epithelial cells treated for 1 h with <italic>N</italic>-chlorotaurine (NCT) (full diamond) or metronidazole (open square).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr2"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>