<article xmlns="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="other">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biol Psychiatry</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Biological Psychiatry</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0006-3223</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1873-2402</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2927778</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">BPS10491</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2010.01.032</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Correspondence</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Response to: Testing the Association Between Smoking in Pregnancy and Attention-Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder in a Novel Design</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Thapar</surname>
            <given-names>Anita</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rice</surname>
            <given-names>Frances</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hay</surname>
            <given-names>Dale</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Boivin</surname>
            <given-names>Jacky</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Langley</surname>
            <given-names>Kate</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>van den Bree</surname>
            <given-names>Marianne</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rutter</surname>
            <given-names>Michael</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">g</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Harold</surname>
            <given-names>Gordon</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">h</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Psychological Medicine and Neurology, Medical Research Council Centre for Neuropsychiatric Genetics and Genomics, School of Medicine, Cardiff University, Cardiff, Wales, United Kingdom</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Psychological Medicine and Neurology, Medical Research Council Centre for Neuropsychiatric Genetics and Genomics, School of Medicine, Cardiff University, Cardiff, Wales, United Kingdom</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>School of Psychology, Cardiff University, Cardiff, Wales, United Kingdom</aff>
      <aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>School of Psychology, Cardiff University, Cardiff, Wales, United Kingdom</aff>
      <aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Department of Psychological Medicine and Neurology, Medical Research Council Centre for Neuropsychiatric Genetics and Genomics, School of Medicine, Cardiff University, Cardiff, Wales, United Kingdom</aff>
      <aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Department of Psychological Medicine and Neurology, Medical Research Council Centre for Neuropsychiatric Genetics and Genomics, School of Medicine, Cardiff University, Cardiff, Wales, United Kingdom</aff>
      <aff id="aff7"><label>g</label>SGDP Centre, Institute of Psychiatry, King's College London, London, United Kingdom</aff>
      <aff id="aff8"><label>h</label>School of Psychology, Cardiff University, Cardiff, Wales, United Kingdom</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>68</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>e13</fpage>
      <lpage>e14</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2010 Elsevier Inc.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Society of Biological Psychiatry</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/authorsview.authors/supplementalterms1.0">certain conditions</ext-link>.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>We thank the authors for their interest in our article (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). They raise a question about gender effects and highlight “it would be informative to look at the results stratified by gender.” We agree that examination of gender effects, where feasible, is important. To meaningfully examine associations between smoking in pregnancy and attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) among genetically related and unrelated mother-child pairs, further stratified by child gender and exposure to smoking in pregnancy, a substantially larger sample size would be required. However, to address the points raised by Obel <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), we provide the data stratified by gender, with the caveat that the sample size available becomes too small in the unrelated group to derive meaningful interpretations.</p>
    <p>In the total sample, there was no significant difference in the proportion of male and female offspring of smokers versus nonsmokers. There were 377 unexposed boys, 360 unexposed girls, 29 exposed boys, and 19 exposed girls (chi square = 1.76, <italic>p</italic> = .184). We also found no significant gender differences in related versus unrelated offspring as described in Table 2 in our article. In response to Obel <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), we have now explored associations between smoking in pregnancy by gender. In the unrelated group (104 unexposed boys, 2 exposed boys, 106 unexposed girls, 7 exposed girls; 2 unexposed with missing gender), there is no significant association between smoking in pregnancy and ADHD in either boys (β = −.114, <italic>p</italic> = .246) or girls (β = .010, <italic>p</italic> = .914). In the related group (262 unexposed boys, 26 exposed boys, 256 unexposed girls, 11 exposed girls), there is significant association between smoking in pregnancy in boys (β = .127, <italic>p</italic> = .031) but not for girls (β = .032, <italic>p</italic> = .601). Gender differences in the association between smoking in pregnancy and offspring ADHD have not been consistently reported (<xref rid="bib2 bib3" ref-type="bibr">2,3</xref>). It may be that the association (and inherited effect) is stronger in boys, but by subdividing our sample into such small numbers, we believe it is not safe to draw firm conclusions. However, we agree gender effects could be usefully examined in the future.</p>
    <p>On a separate note, the authors wonder if the birth weight difference between related and unrelated groups is an error. Although the mean birth weight appears higher in related children, this is not an error and the difference in birth weight for the related and unrelated groups is not statistically significant (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). We have also checked the birth weight means reported in the text for those exposed and not exposed to smoking in pregnancy. These too are correct. In addition, as we have previously reported, the same pattern of results is observed between smoking in pregnancy and birth weight when only singleton births are included and when statistically adjusting for gestational age (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p>
    <p>We are pleased that the authors find our design interesting. As highlighted in our original article, all designs have limitations and our sample size for those exposed is small. We believe it is important to consider our results in the context of those from other designs (animal studies, siblings discordant for exposure to smoking, and children of twin studies) as discussed in our article. Taken together, the pattern of findings suggests that the previously observed association between maternal smoking and ADHD might represent an inherited/familial confound. We also suggest it is important to consider the possibility that associations observed in epidemiological studies could arise from unmeasured confounds including inherited ones.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thapar</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rice</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hay</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boivin</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Langley</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van den Bree</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prenatal smoking might not cause attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder: Evidence from a novel design</article-title>
          <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>722</fpage>
          <lpage>727</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19596120</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Obel</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Linnet</surname>
              <given-names>K.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Henriksen</surname>
              <given-names>T.B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rodriguez</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Järvelin</surname>
              <given-names>M.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kotimaa</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Smoking during pregnancy and hyperactivity-inattention in the offspring—comparing results from three Nordic cohorts</article-title>
          <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>698</fpage>
          <lpage>705</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18250076</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Linnet</surname>
              <given-names>K.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dalsgaard</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Obel</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wisborg</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Henriksen</surname>
              <given-names>T.B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rodriguez</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Maternal lifestyle factors in pregnancy risk of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder and associated behaviors: Review of the current evidence</article-title>
          <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>
          <volume>160</volume>
          <year>2003</year>
          <fpage>1028</fpage>
          <lpage>1040</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12777257</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rice</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harold</surname>
              <given-names>G.T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boivin</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hay</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van den Bree</surname>
              <given-names>M.M.B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thapar</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Disentangling prenatal and inherited influences in humans with an experimental design</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <volume>106</volume>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>2464</fpage>
          <lpage>2467</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19188591</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rice</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harold</surname>
              <given-names>G.T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boivin</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hay</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>van den Bree</surname>
              <given-names>M.M.B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thapar</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The effects of gestational stress on offspring birthweight and psychopathology: Disentangling prenatal environmental and inherited influences</article-title>
          <source>Psychol Med</source>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <year>2010</year>
          <fpage>335</fpage>
          <lpage>345</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19476689</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <ack>
      <p>Author FR is currently affiliated with the Division of Psychology and Language Sciences, University College London, United Kingdom. Author GH is currently affiliated with the Centre for Research on Children and Families, University of Otago, Dunedin, New Zealand.</p>
      <p>All authors report no biomedical financial interests or potential conflicts of interest.</p>
    </ack>
  </back>
</article>