<article xmlns="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="research-article">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Energy Policy</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Energy Policy</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0301-4215</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Butterworths [etc.]</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3182315</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21976785</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JEPO5131</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.enpol.2011.07.009</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Sustainable energy development in Austria until 2020: Insights from applying the integrated model “e3.at”</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Stocker</surname>
            <given-names>Andrea</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>andrea.stocker@seri.at</email>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
          <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Großmann</surname>
            <given-names>Anett</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Madlener</surname>
            <given-names>Reinhard</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wolter</surname>
            <given-names>Marc Ingo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>SERI—Sustainable Europe Research Institute, Garnisongasse 7/21, 1090 Vienna, Austria</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Institute of Economic Structures Research, Heinrichstr. 30, 49080 Osnabrück, Germany</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Institute for Future Energy Consumer Needs and Behavior (FCN), School of Business and Economics/E.ON Energy Research Center, RWTH Aachen University, Mathieustrasse 6, 52074 Aachen, Germany</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. Tel.: +43 4352 30 276; fax: +43 1 969 07 28 17. <email>andrea.stocker@seri.at</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2011</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>39</volume>
      <issue>10-2</issue>
      <fpage>6082</fpage>
      <lpage>6099</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>5</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2011 Elsevier Ltd.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/authorsview.authors/supplementalterms1.0">certain conditions</ext-link>.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>This paper reports on the Austrian research project “Renewable energy in Austria: Modeling possible development trends until 2020”. The project investigated possible economic and ecological effects of a substantially increased use of renewable energy sources in Austria. Together with stakeholders and experts, three different scenarios were defined, specifying possible development trends for renewable energy in Austria. The scenarios were simulated for the period 2006–2020, using the integrated environment–energy–economy model “e3.at”. The modeling results indicate that increasing the share of renewable energy sources in total energy use is an important but insufficient step towards achieving a sustainable energy system in Austria. A substantial increase in energy efficiency and a reduction of residential energy consumption also form important cornerstones of a sustainable energy policy.</p>
      </abstract>
      <abstract abstract-type="graphical">
        <title>Highlights</title>
        <p>► Together with stakeholders three renewable energy scenarios for Austria were defined. ► The scenarios were simulated using an integrated environment–energy–economy model. ► Increasing the share of renewables in total energy use is important but insufficient. ► Efficiency and a cut of energy use are also essential for a sustainable energy system.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Renewable energy</kwd>
        <kwd>Macro-econometric modeling</kwd>
        <kwd>Scenario development</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s0005">
      <label>1</label>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Renewable energy plays an important role in Austria for reducing the country’s dependence on imported fossil fuels and for supporting the reduction of greenhouse gas emissions. This role will become more important within the next years due to the fact that the share of renewables – which amounts to about 24% of the entire final energy mix in 2005 – has to increase to 34% by 2020 in order to fulfill EU targets (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">CEC, 2009</xref>).<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref> In this respect, it is important to estimate and quantify the effects of an intensified use of renewable energy on the environment, the economy and society.</p>
      <p>The project “Renewable Energy in Austria: Modeling possible development trends until 2020” (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Stocker et al., 2008</xref>) investigated potential economic, employment and environmental effects of an increasing use of renewable energy resources for heat and power generation in Austria. More specifically, the integrated environment–energy–economy model “e3.at” was developed and used to simulate different renewable energy technology (RET) scenarios with a focus on different developments of renewable energy use in Austria up to 2020. The scenarios were developed jointly with stakeholders and experts. The e3.at model enables a much deeper impact assessment of renewable energy policy than more conventional less integrated models.</p>
      <p>The process of scenario modeling (from the development of scenarios up to the dissemination of the modeling results) integrates participative elements. A stakeholder and expert group of 30 people were formed, actively accompanying the project by means of bilateral discussions and participation in workshops. In total, four workshops were held, with the objective of presenting and discussing the set-up and functioning of the simulation model and to elaborate the scenarios. Thanks to these discussions, valuable inputs and helpful suggestions were received and duly considered in the project work. Thus, the research results are not only built upon the work of researchers, but they also integrate the knowledge, the expertise and the preferences of the major stakeholders, thus enriching the policy value and relevance of the research still further.</p>
      <p>The remainder of this paper is organized as follows: <xref rid="s0010" ref-type="sec">Section 2</xref> introduces the integrated model “e3.at” and <xref rid="s0015" ref-type="sec">Section 3</xref> describes the scenarios. On the basis of the simulation results, reported in <xref rid="s0035" ref-type="sec">Section 4</xref>, we draw some policy implications in <xref rid="s0040" ref-type="sec">Section 5</xref> and derive some conclusions from this analysis in <xref rid="s0045" ref-type="sec">Section 6</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0010">
      <label>2</label>
      <title>The integrated environment–energy–economy model “e3.at”</title>
      <p>In this section, we briefly introduce the integrated environment–energy–economy model e3.at (for a detailed description see the Appendix and <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Großmann and Wolter, 2010</xref>), which was developed and applied within the project to analyze different scenarios aiming at increasing renewable energy use.</p>
      <p>e3.at is a multi-sector model that permits the illustration of structural change and, as such, is able to identify particular burdens on certain industries. This fact is important for the design of a social reconciliation and of supporting measures to offset these burdens. The transition to a sustainable development can thereby be arranged under consideration of social and economic compatibility aspects.</p>
      <p>The model also illustrates the interdependencies between the environment and the economy, allowing not only for the analysis of economic growth and employment effects, but also the impact on resource use and CO<sub>2</sub> emissions.</p>
      <p>The integration of the environmental and socio-economic systems, with their various linkages and feedbacks, is needed to appropriately assist energy policy-makers in their decisions on suitable strategies to tackle the most challenging environmental and socio-economic problems related to energy supply and use.</p>
      <p>A major advantage of integrated modeling with e3.at is the representation of direct and indirect rebound effects (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Sorrell, 2010)</xref>. Forcing renewable energy in Austria means increasing both economic activity and energy consumption. Moreover, the additional added value leads to an increased demand (e.g. for transport and other consumer goods). These effects can be calculated within e3.at.</p>
      <p>The model is based on the philosophy that agents act in imperfect markets under conditions of bounded rationality (see, e.g. <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Rubinstein, 1998</xref>). The application of econometric methods facilitates an empirically validated parameterization of the model. As an empirically validated model, it is able to produce reliable baseline projections, which, when confronted with environmental and economic targets, allow for the calculation of sustainability gaps.</p>
      <p>The construction of the model follows two principles: bottom-up modeling and full integration—both typical characteristics of the INFORUM philosophy (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Almon, 1991</xref>). “Bottom-up” means that each of the 57 sectors of the Austrian economy is modeled in great detail. Macroeconomic variables, such as GDP, disposable income or the consumer price index, are calculated by explicit aggregation. Full integration implies complex modeling, which simultaneously depicts interindustry connections and the generation, distribution, redistribution and use of income for consuming goods. It further depicts the influence of the economy on the environment and vice versa.</p>
      <p>The detailed structure of the model is necessary because the linkage between the economy and the environment requires a detailed production structure. With regard to data, time series of input–output (IO) tables are consistently linked with time series of a full system of national accounts and balancing items (SNAB).</p>
      <p>The core model of e3.at consists of an <italic>economic model</italic>, consisting of an input–output (IO) model, the SNAB and the labor market; and an <italic>energy model</italic>, illustrating the relationship between economic development, energy use and CO<sub>2</sub> emissions. Additionally, the core model can be expanded by a <italic>material model</italic>, a <italic>regional housing inventory model</italic> and a <italic>transportation model for private households</italic> in order to show the manifold relationships between the economy, the energy system and the environment. With the aim of displaying social and distributional impacts, the model was extended by 25 household groups according to their income and size of household. Furthermore, e3.at has a soft link to the world model GINFORS (Global INterindustry FORcasting System; see <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Meyer et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Lutz et al., 2010</xref>), in order to illustrate the effects of international trade on the Austrian economy.</p>
      <p>Since in the reported project only the economic and the energy model components are used, we only describe these shortly in the following. For further information see the Appendix or <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Großmann and Wolter (2010)</xref>.</p>
      <p><xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> provides a brief overview of the structure of the model.</p>
      <p>The <italic>economic model</italic> consists of an input–output (IO) model, the SNAB and the labor market. It shows a very high degree of endogenization, although tax rates and labor supply are exogenous. As already stated, sectoral exports and import prices are taken from GINFORS, but they are endogenous to that system. The high degree of endogenization leads to the advantage of the effects calculated in simulations being complete and including also direct and indirect rebound effects.</p>
      <p>In addition to the usual interdependencies between the circular flow of income, e3.at depicts the interdependencies between prices and volumes as well as between prices and wages. The model is non-linear, due to the many multiplicative connections of variables in definitions and many behavioral equations estimated in double logarithms. It is a dynamic model because of the capital stock adjustment and the lags in behavioral equations. The dynamic structure allows a year-by-year solution for a longer time path.</p>
      <p>The core of the economic model is an <italic>IO model</italic>, which shows the interdependencies of all industries, and which is also important for linking the economic model with the material and the energy model.</p>
      <p>The <italic>SNAB</italic> is also part of the model and is consistently linked with the input–output system. It calculates the aggregate variables and the income redistribution between government, households, firms and the rest of the world. It covers production, primary and secondary distribution of income, use of income, acquisition of non-financial assets and accumulation accounts. The government’s budget, including the tax system and the social security system, is endogenously determined. The detail of this system allows the identification of the expenditures and revenues of the social security system, so that the system can be linked to the labor market and other parts of the model.</p>
      <p>The labor market consists of both an aggregated part and a part modeled in detail. In the aggregate part, the demographic development determines the macroeconomic labor supply. Unemployment is given by definition, subtracting aggregated labor demand from the exogenous labor supply.</p>
      <p>In the part modeled in detail, for each of the 57 production sectors, the labor demand is explained by gross production and the real costs of labor per capita in that sector, as well as by a time trend.</p>
      <p>The <italic>energy model</italic> describes the interrelations between economic development, energy consumption and CO<sub>2</sub> emissions. On the one hand, economic development influences primary energy use. On the other hand, expenditure for energy consumption has a direct impact on the economic variables.</p>
      <p>Since final energy usually cannot be provided directly to the consumer, the transformation sector converts domestic and imported (primary) energy to final energy. Primary energy commodities are extracted or captured directly from natural resources, such as crude oil, hard coal, natural gas or renewable energy. In contrast to secondary energy (e.g. electricity), they are not converted by physical and/or chemical processes. Partly, primary energy is transformed directly into final energy. The primary energy required can either be produced in Austria or imported from abroad. Also, part of the domestic production can be exported. Furthermore, final energy is provided by transformation of primary energy carriers to secondary energy (e.g. electricity and heat), where, however, large transformation losses may occur.</p>
      <p>An adequate energy model must, therefore, be able to consider primary and secondary sources of energy, final energy, as well as losses occurring from energy conversion. In addition, the differentiation of a multiplicity of sources of energy and sufficiently detailed sector levels are necessary.</p>
      <p>The model serves as a basis for quantifying the effects of different scenarios for a more ambitious use of renewable energy in Austria.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0015">
      <label>3</label>
      <title>The RET scenarios</title>
      <p>Hydropower and the biomass resources make a substantial contribution to energy supply in Austria, whereas all other renewables still play a minor role. Against the climate problem and dwindling fossil resources, it is necessary to produce useful energy in other ways than the combustion of oil, coal or natural gas. As already mentioned in the introduction, renewable energy sources are environmentally more friendly alternatives to fossil fuels and, therefore, should contribute much more to meet the energy needs of society. The question arises, which potential the renewables in Austria have, and which economic, ecological and social consequences their increased use may have.</p>
      <p>Based on the experience gained in the project “ARTEMIS” (see <xref rid="bib23 bib24 bib28" ref-type="bibr">Kowalski et al., 2006, 2009; Madlener et al., 2007</xref>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.project-artemis.net">www.project-artemis.net</ext-link>), scenarios until 2020 were defined to specify how an increased share of renewable energy could look like. Together with stakeholders and experts in energy technology and policy, three scenarios were elaborated, illustrating different pathways to promoting renewable energy.</p>
      <p>The RET scenarios were analyzed in comparison to a Business as Usual (BAU) scenario, which reflects the policy situation of 2005. This scenario serves as a reference scenario, showing the expected future development up to 2020, under the assumption that aside of already implemented measures no additional promotion of renewables takes place. Comparing the BAU scenario with the RET scenarios allows to recognize effects of changes induced by the scenario design.</p>
      <p>The RET scenarios focus on heat and power generation. They refer neither to the transport sector nor to measures for improving efficiency in the manufacturing industries, nor to the thermal reconstruction of buildings. However, energy efficiency improvements are considered in the BAU scenario.</p>
      <p>The three alternative scenarios considered range from more centralized to decentralized technologies, from a focus on land-intensive to land-saving technologies, and from electricity to heat technologies. They also differ with respect to their feasibility in the short-, medium- and long-term as well as their investment costs and competitiveness.</p>
      <p>In the following, the scenarios are described by presenting their general intention, their key technologies involved, the potentials of their promotion until 2020, their learning curves as well as their prices. The definition of the key parameters is based on a comprehensive literature review and on intensive discussions with stakeholders and experts.</p>
      <p>In all scenarios we assume that the Austrian government is at least partly willing to bear the investment and credit risks of companies in the form of guarantees. This support is especially important for those technologies that are associated with high investment costs. The effects of misdirected investments can be significant even for large utilities. Therefore, it is implicitly assumed that the government is collaterizing half of the investment volume with guarantees. In the model simulation, it is implied that the income tax is increased to finance the guarantees. One advantage of this funding is that it has positive effects on distributive justice: Because of the tax progression, households with higher incomes pay more income or payroll taxes. However, their pro rata share of expenditures for energy is rather low. The opposite is true for households with low incomes.</p>
      <sec id="s0020">
        <label>3.1</label>
        <title>Scenario “Improve Strengths”—IS (short-term oriented)</title>
        <p>The scenario “Improve Strengths” (IS) is based on renewable energy technologies that have low actual heat or power generation costs and that are able to promptly expand their capacities. Thus, “Improve Strengths” primarily focuses on the extension of wind power and small hydropower for power generation, as well as on wood pellets for heat generation. All these technologies have good chances for further implementation in Austria, because they will further improve technological leadership and competitiveness (<xref rid="bib6 bib9" ref-type="bibr">BMVIT, 2002; Bodenhöfer et al., 2004</xref>).</p>
        <p>Just like biomass, hydropower is of great importance in Austria, too. Between 1980 and 2004, depending on weather conditions, between 60% and 74% of total electricity production was realized by (mainly large-scale) hydropower.<xref rid="fn2" ref-type="fn">2</xref> The potential of large-scale hydropower is mostly exhausted. Optimistic estimates of the remaining potential show that power production from large-scale hydropower could be increased further by some 4% until 2020. In absolute numbers, this is equivalent to an increase by about 5200 TJ until 2020 (compared to 124,711 TJ in 2005).</p>
        <p>An important role in this scenario has the expansion of small-scale hydropower.<xref rid="fn3" ref-type="fn">3</xref> Currently, small-scale hydro accounts for some 4440 TJ (2005) of renewable electricity regulated by the Austrian Green Electricity Act (Ökostromgesetz), ranking second after wind power. The additional potential (until 2020) has been estimated to be about 7900 TJ (equivalent to an increase by 178%).</p>
        <p>In the case of wind power an exploitation of the potential of currently (2005) 4780 TJ to more than 22,200 TJ (i.e. almost a quintupling) is assumed. Especially for wind power the potential rises with increasing technological know-how, as more and more surface areas can be used for wind power production, the installed capacity per m<sup>2</sup> rises with rising size of the plants, and full-load hours rise as well with increasing nacelle height (e.g. <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Haas et al., 2007</xref>).</p>
        <p>Regarding heat and combined-heat-and-power (CHP) production the expansion of plants for using wood pellets and wood residues is forced more than in the other scenarios. For CHP plants the increase is 3000 TJ between 2005 and 2020, whereas the capacity of heat-only plants doubles (increase by 7500 TJ between 2005 and 2020). An expansion beyond this level is considered unlikely, given the increasing competition with the use of wood residues (esp. sawdust and shavings) in the particle board industry (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Nemestothy, 2006</xref>). In other words, the limiting factor here is resource availability and not so much the time construction of the plants.</p>
        <p>Due to the limited capacity expansion with respect to hydropower, wind power and wood pellets, this scenario would result in relatively small CO<sub>2</sub> savings. The expansion of hydropower is limited due to environmental and social acceptance constraints. Missing areas with favorable wind conditions as well as lacking social acceptance restrict the further exploitation for wind power as well. For wood pellet heating systems, a doubling of the capacity is assumed, but a higher expansion is limited due to increasing competition within the timber processing industry. For these reasons, an increase in photovoltaics is also assumed.</p>
        <p>With regard to the electricity and heat generation costs, the IS Scenario is favorable compared to the other two scenarios, at least in the initial phase. Due to the much higher oil and gas prices in this scenario, small hydropower plants and certain types of biomass plants can successfully compete with those based on fossil fuels. Also thanks to the promotion of green electricity wind power shows relatively low investment and operating costs, and the cost of solar thermal collectors – at least in the decentralized supply of hot water – is no big obstacle any more.</p>
        <p><xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarizes the parameterization for the “Improve Strength” scenario.</p>
        <p>Concerning the security of supply, the scenario is not expected to be able to significantly reduce energy imports, and the structure of supply will be centrally organized. In the IS scenario the supply of electricity (electricity to heat in a 3:1 ratio) is dominant. Electricity is produced mostly by small hydropower, wind power and photovoltaics, but also by nuclear power plants, and is structured more centrally. Heat is mainly provided in a localized manner through biomass district heating and combined heat and power (CHP) plants.</p>
        <p>Although security of supply is supported by a diverse energy mix, electricity supply must be secured with other indigenous power generating capacity and electricity imports, since wind power is subject to strong fluctuations. The market for wood pellets is already an international one. Since Austria exports a high proportion of the wood pellet production, but also imports from other countries, it is not very easy to reduce the dependence on imports (although the transport costs generally account for a large fraction of the total fuel costs and are expected to rise further due to increasing transport distances).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0025">
        <label>3.2</label>
        <title>Scenario “Biomassive”—BIO (medium-term oriented)</title>
        <p>The scenario “Biomassive” (BIO) was designed in light of the importance of biomass as an energy carrier for Austria and due to the fact that a comprehensive and sustainable use of the available biomass potentials is very likely (e.g. high share of forest land, tradition, successful timber industry, technological know-how). These technologies, where considerable experience has been gained in the last few decades, and which hold great potential for further development, are extended the most. In principle, the use of solid biomass and biogas receives the strongest governmental support, leading to a central structure of supply with a focus on heat generation.</p>
        <p>Just like in the IS scenario, the focus lies also on the provision of electricity (electricity-to-heat in a ratio 3:1 ratio), yet the contribution of renewable heat production is the highest in this scenario. A major advantage of biomass is that it can be directly stored and is not as much subject to seasonal variations such as wind and solar energy.</p>
        <p>The scenario is constructed to estimate the maximum biomass use within critical framework conditions. In this respect, additional biomass capacity, recycling capacity, land-use conflicts with the timber, paper and pulp and food industries, and biofuels as well as biomass imports have to be considered. As was the case for the first scenario (“Improve Strengths”), the technological conditions for the implementation are also given. However, a strong expansion of biomass utilization will require increasing imports of investment goods in order to offset the missing production capacity in Austria.</p>
        <p>Regarding security of supply, biomass for heat production should mainly be supplied from domestic sources, in order to reduce foreign dependence. It must be noted that the available domestic space for increased cultivation of biomass for energy purposes (energy crops) is limited and different users (wood industry, paper and pulp industry, food industry, agrofuels) compete for the raw material. It is generally expected that a shortage of domestic fuel supply will occur, leading to rising import shares.</p>
        <p>With regard to the time horizon this scenario is medium-term oriented. Those technologies are used that are already widely disseminated, but that are relatively land-intensive and thus in competition with other land use options. Moreover, the cascadic use of biomass is fostered, aimed at yielding the maximum material and energetic use of biomass with a minimal input. A central aim is the maximization of sustainable agricultural land use for energy crops and the extensive exploitation of the yield potential of the forest biomass for energy use (to the extent that this is economically viable).</p>
        <p>The price development for the energy resources forced in this scenario is assumed to be modestly rising, since some biomass technologies are already available at relatively low cost, but the exploitation of the entire potential incurs high additional investment cost. Also, despite economies of scale and learning effects, higher prices can be expected due to resource scarcities. We assume that the price of wood logs, for instance, rises from €37 today to €57 per m<sup>3</sup> in 2020. For biofuels (stationary and transport use) we assume a moderate increase in price.</p>
        <p>Concerning the expansion potentials it is assumed that biogenic fuels for power production increase from currently about 11,000 TJ to more than 45,000 TJ in 2020, and for heating plants from about 240 to 390 TJ. In the private household sector the use of log wood increases from currently 59,500 to 65,500 TJ in 2020. Note that the assumptions made about the expansion potentials for biofuels only address heat and power supply, as an investigation of the transport sector was deliberately excluded from the project. Implicitly, we take into account that the share of agricultural biofuels envisaged at the EU level has to be increased as well, even though this is not explicitly modeled. The assumed expansion paths, therefore, do not exploit the maximum available potentials, but do account for the resource competition with transport fuels.</p>
        <p>With regard to the investment costs we made the following assumptions:<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(1)</label><p>The feed-in tariffs are reduced in line with the learning rates.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(2)</label><p>The installation of additional capacity causes an investment volume of 3420 €/kW in 2006. The costs in the subsequent years diminish in line with the learning rates.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(3)</label><p>The learning rate (per doubling of the global capacity for biogenic fuel) until 2010 is assumed to be 12.5% and from 2011–2020 10%.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(4)</label><p>We assume that the capacity increases with 10% per annum on average.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(5)</label><p>For simplicity, we assume that the plants are in permanent use (24 h a day, 7 days a week).</p></list-item></list></p>
        <p><xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> summarizes the parameterization for the “Biomassive” scenario.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0030">
        <label>3.3</label>
        <title>Scenario “Think about Tomorrow”—TAT (long-term oriented)</title>
        <p>On the one hand, the scenario “Think about Tomorrow” (TAT) is based on a long-term investment strategy, which is provided by the promotion of costly but very promising future technologies (e.g. photovoltaics, geothermal energy). On the other hand, market-ready technologies with low land use requirements are fostered in order to distinguish this scenario from the BIO scenario.</p>
        <p>Thus, “TAT” disregards the combustion and the gasification of biomass resources. Following the advice of the stakeholder group, solar power is used in the form of a massive expansion of photovoltaics. Apart from large-scale hydropower, photovoltaics has the second-largest technical potential for renewable electricity generation in Austria (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Kaltschmitt and Neubarth, 2000</xref>). We presume the most expensive growth path suggested in the literature (e.g. <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Fechner and Lugmaier, 2007</xref>), and an expansion to an installed capacity of 82,000 TJ until 2020, which constitutes a massive extension, as compared to today’s PV production level of some modest 50 TJ (2005).</p>
        <p>In order to model the significant expansion in this scenario reasonably well, we have made the following assumptions:<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>•</label><p>The installation of additional capacity induces an investment volume of 4000 €/kW in 2006. The costs in the subsequent years diminish according to the learning rate.</p></list-item><list-item><label>•</label><p>The learning rate from 2005 to 2010 is assumed at 20% (per doubling of worldwide PV capacity installed), while from 2011 to 2020 a lower learning rate of 12% applies. The feed-in tariffs develop in line with the learning rates.</p></list-item><list-item><label>•</label><p>We assume that, globally, a doubling of installed capacity can be achieved every second year.</p></list-item><list-item><label>•</label><p>Capacity expansion is done stepwise: 1000 TJ in 2006, 2000 TJ in 2007, 3000 TJ in 2008–2010, 4000 TJ in 2011, 5000 TJ each in 2012 and 2013, 6000 TJ in 2014, etc. Moreover, it is taken into account that the investment path cannot follow an exponential trajectory, since then an average growth of 64% per annum would be implied, which in the years 2015–2020 would result in major capacity jumps (2018: +12,000 TJ, 2019 +20,000 TJ, 2020 +32,000 TJ). Whether such a rapid capacity expansion is really feasible, i.e. whether a sufficient amount of solar cells can actually be produced, transported and constructed is uncertain. If capacity expansion remains constant for several years, <italic>ceteris paribus</italic> the required investments fall due to the learning rate. Only at the next jump in capacity expansion they rise again.</p></list-item><list-item><label>•</label><p>It is assumed that the daily useable solar irradiation has a duration of 3 h on average. An installed unit can then produce 1050 kWh per year.</p></list-item><list-item><label>•</label><p>We assume that a plant remains in operation for 20 years, implying that over the simulation period no plant is removed from the capital stock.</p></list-item><list-item><label>•</label><p>It is assumed that the feed-in remuneration for a plant is constant over time (on average), i.e. the later one invests, the lower is the feed-in tariff granted. Therefore, the average feed-in tariff does not coincide with the feed-in tariff of the last unit installed.</p></list-item><list-item><label>•</label><p>We assume further that the electricity produced in PV plants is used locally.</p></list-item></list></p>
        <p>Due to the high investment costs involved, the financing of this scenario would have to be strongly supported by the government, and would require substantial subsidy funding.</p>
        <p>This fact is related to high prices of the technology (the primary costs) and, at least initially, the lack of profitability. It is to be expected that the initially high prices decrease significantly in the long term. It is assumed that the feed-in tariff scheme is maintained until the year 2020 and private households participate in the financing through higher electricity prices. Furthermore, there will be considerable need for communication between policy-makers and utilities. Since the risks are substantial, investments at the assumed scale can hardly be sustained by new companies.</p>
        <p>In addition, it is not easily possible to create the necessary production capacity for solar cells in Austria, leading to additional imports of solar cells and the related diminution of domestic value added. If a similar behavior in other countries is assumed, then demand-driven price increases for solar cells are likely. Furthermore, the provision of the technology is very resource-intensive.</p>
        <p>In addition to PV, geothermal electricity, solar thermal heat and wind power are forced as well.</p>
        <p>Specifically geothermal energy currently only plays a minor role in Austria. Whereas in 2005 only two geothermal plants were in operation in Austria (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Proidl, 2006</xref>), yielding 562 TJ, a capacity expansion to (the equivalence of) 1125 TJ of thermal energy is envisaged until 2020 (under present economic and geological framework conditions). The capacity of heat pumps is increased from 688 TJ in 2005 to 1215 TJ in 2020. Solar thermal capacity is increased from 2285 TJ in 2005 to 7232 TJ in 2020. For both geothermal energy and solar thermal energy we assume constant prices between 2005 and 2020. The assumptions about the expansion of wind power are the same as in the scenario “Improve Strengths”.</p>
        <p><xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> summarizes the parameterization for the scenario “Think about Tomorrow”.</p>
        <p>The ratio of additional electricity and heat generation in this scenario is about 4.5–1, meaning that proportionally much electricity can be provided. Electricity generation, which is characterized by the key technologies of photovoltaics and wind power, is characterized by a central structure. Although solar thermal and geothermal energy will be stepped up, heat is still produced in large part by using biomass.</p>
        <p>Regarding supply security, the recent past has shown that the growing electricity consumption could not be covered by increases in domestic power generation capacity. Therefore, Austria turned into a net importer of electricity in 2001. The additional development of local generation capacities can improve this situation in the future, but does not guarantee the supply security by itself. Overall, the supply security in this scenario is classified as high, as the long-term oriented technologies unfold their potential already in 2020.</p>
        <p>Further positive factors of this scenario are the exploitation of a sustainable energy source, the achievement of significant CO<sub>2</sub> reductions and the decrease in fossil fuel imports.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0035">
      <label>4</label>
      <title>Results of scenario simulation</title>
      <p>With respect to the economic development, the BAU scenario as well as the RET scenarios is supposed to have positive effects (see <xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). In the BAU scenario, the gross domestic product (GDP) increases by 2.1% p.a., while in the RET scenarios this growth is even higher. While consumption, exports and imports develop rather similarly in all scenarios, they substantially differ in the dynamics of investment growth. The TAT scenario requires considerable investments, which entail the strongest growth in GDP. The model assumes that a large part of the solar cells can actually be produced in Austria. If this is not the case, rising imports will slow down domestic economic growth.</p>
      <p>Economic growth also leads to an increase in employment. Whereas in the BAU scenario some 198,000 additional jobs can be created by 2020, this figure is still higher in the three RET scenarios envisaged: In comparison to the BAU scenario, the scenario “TAT” would lead to 19,000 new jobs, “BIO” to about 15,000 and “IS” to about 10,000 additional jobs per year.</p>
      <p>The scenarios differ significantly in the pricing of the gross production of energy. Higher depreciation, due to higher investment and higher feed-in tariffs, influences the price. In the IS and the BIO scenarios the price is 9.2% and 9.4% higher compared with the BAU scenario in 2020; in the TAT scenario, it is 23.3% higher. Concerning the TAT scenario, it is important to keep in mind the assumption that a shortage of solar cells would inflate the price even further.</p>
      <p>The macroeconomic impacts of these price increases are minor, because, for example, the private consumption is only around 3.2% for electricity, gas and other fuels. In 2020, the price of the total household consumption in “Improve Strengths” and in “Biomassive” is by approximately 0.2% higher than in the BAU scenario. Prices in the scenario “Think about Tomorrow” are about 0.5% above those of the BAU scenario. The average price development of the total gross production increases by 0.36% in IS, 0.39% in BIO and 0.9% in TAT.</p>
      <p>The composition of the final energy consumption<xref rid="fn4" ref-type="fn">4</xref> according to energy sources develops very heterogeneously between the scenarios. The use of heating oil is lower in “BIO” and in “TAT” than in “IS”. Especially in the BIO scenario, the higher use of firewood in private households reduces the use of fuel oil significantly. In the scenario “Think about Tomorrow”, it is the generation of heat by solar energy which decreases the use of heating oil.</p>
      <p>A comparison of the shares of renewable energy in the course of time shows that, in the BAU scenario, the share between 2005 and 2020 decreases, due to the lacking expansion of hydropower use. In the RET scenarios, this decrease can be stopped (see <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>).</p>
      <p>The Austrian energy policy target, i.e. to cover 34% of final energy consumption by renewable energy by 2020, cannot be met in any of the scenarios (see <xref rid="t0025" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). The highest share with 27.5% in 2020 can be expected in the scenario “Think about tomorrow”. “Improve Strengths” supposes that the share for 2005 can be maintained, while in “Biomassive”, even a slight decrease in the percentage over time is possible.</p>
      <p>By combining the assumptions of the different scenarios, the overall share can be extended to 28.3%. Yet it has to be noted that energy use will strongly increase up to 2020 (see row “Final energy consumption (total)” in <xref rid="t0025" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>), so that despite the massive expansion of renewable energy supply, additional heat and power consumption cannot be adequately covered (rebound effect). On the other hand, the Austrian Energy Strategy (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">BMWFJ, 2010</xref>) foresees that the level of final energy consumption is stabilized in 2020 at the 2005 level (ca. 1100 PJ). Such a stabilization (e.g. through efficiency gains and changes in consumption behavior) could lead to a situation where the share increases to 37%.</p>
      <p>The resulting CO<sub>2</sub> reduction is caused by the realized shares of renewable energy. It is true that, in all RET scenarios, the CO<sub>2</sub> emissions can be reduced vis-a-vis the BAU scenario, since fossil fuels can be replaced by renewable energy sources.</p>
      <p>In the TAT scenario, with its significant additional investments, at the beginning of the projection period there is even an increase in CO<sub>2</sub> emissions, due to the positive impact of the investments on the economic system. In other words, there are two countervailing forces. On the one hand, the increased use of photovoltaics leads to a reduction in the share of fossil fuels. On the other hand, the energy consumption rises due to the boost to the economy. Only when the investment volumes decrease relative to the installed capacity, the replacement effect of fossil fuels starts to dominate.</p>
      <p>An absolute reduction of CO<sub>2</sub> emissions over time is, however, not possible in any of the RET scenarios (see <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). Thus, with an exclusive expansion of renewable energy, the respective EU regulation of reducing CO<sub>2</sub> emissions until 2020 by 20% (compared to 1990 levels) will not be met.<xref rid="fn5" ref-type="fn">5</xref> Furthermore, the Austrian Kyoto target is clearly missed. It stipulates that the total greenhouse gas emissions have to be reduced by 13% between 2008 and 2012, relative to the base year 1990, when they amounted to 68.8 million tons of CO<sub>2</sub> equivalents. Since the e3.at model only accounts for CO<sub>2</sub>, and not all greenhouse gases that are included in the Kyoto Protocol, the relevant CO<sub>2</sub> stabilization target of 1990 would be at 62.08 million tons of CO<sub>2</sub> (assuming that the share of CO<sub>2</sub> emissions in total greenhouse gas emissions is about 80%; see e.g. <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Umweltbundesamt, 2009</xref>). If the Austrian Kyoto target of −13% is referred to this amount only, the CO<sub>2</sub> reference value would be at about 54 million tons.</p>
      <p>The three scenarios differ primarily with regard to their technology mixes. One commonality is the high growth of photovoltaics. Overall, for the assumptions made in scenario “Think about Tomorrow” the strongest expansion of renewables arises (with an additional contribution of almost 176,000 TJ between 2005 and 2020), which is primarily achieved by an increase in electrical energy (mainly PV). Consequently, also the CO<sub>2</sub> emission reductions are largest in this scenario.</p>
      <p>All scenarios have in common that they focus on electricity supply from power plants that do not make use of combined heat-and-power production (CHP). Although this does not lead to the most energy-efficient energy supply, several arguments can be put forward for this simplification. First, over the coming years the need for electricity is expected to rise faster than that for heat. Second, we did not find any sound evidence about how much capacity can actually be used by CHP. Finally, the framework conditions required for the use of heat from CHP is not always there.</p>
      <p>A further important distinctive feature of the scenarios is the degree of centrality of energy supply. As an indicator we use the ratio between more centralized technologies (energy conversion facilities: power-only plants, CHP and heat-only plants) to the more decentralized technologies (solar thermal plants, heat pumps, logwood and wood pellet heating systems). The degree of centrality is assumed to rise further in the BAU scenario (see <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Only in the BIO scenario marked reductions in this indicator are realized. Nevertheless, also in this scenario the degree of centralization of energy supply rises.</p>
      <p>In order to model supply security, total energy imports are used (measured in Terajoule, TJ). Also for this comparison none of the scenarios differs markedly from the general development path. Compared to the BAU scenario, the strongest decrease in imports takes place in the “Think about Tomorrow“ Scenario, followed by “Biomassive” and “Improve Strength“. This result was to be expected, as electricity production from PV depends on the number of solar irradiation hours and because a part of the biomass can be produced domestically, whereas fossil fuels have to be predominantly imported.</p>
      <p>In summary, one can conclude that the RET scenarios do not provide a formula for success concerning the extension of renewable energy. In other words: There is no free lunch. The IS scenario features cost efficiency and competitiveness, but the expansion of wind and hydropower is limited and problematic from an environmental and social acceptance point of view. The BIO scenario is supposed to have a high potential for political implementation, but suffers from land use conflicts and resource scarcity. The TAT scenario, in turn, is able to achieve a high augmentation of renewable energy and large CO<sub>2</sub> savings, but requires high investment costs.</p>
      <p>Finally, it is obvious that there is no alternative but to reduce energy consumption. Only if this can be achieved, for instance through huge efficiency gains and changes in behavior, can renewable energy live up to the high expectations placed on it for achieving a sustainable energy system in Austria.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0040">
      <label>5</label>
      <title>Policy implications</title>
      <p>Even though the share of renewable energies in gross energy consumption in Austria is relatively high (25% in 2007), about three quarters of domestic energy consumption are met by fossil fuels. Due to only modest fossil fuel resources, Austrian energy supply depends to about 70% on imports (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Anderl et al., 2007</xref>). Hence a reduction of fossil fuel imports is an important goal in Austrian energy and climate policy. Massive expansion of renewable energy use can help to reduce import dependency.</p>
      <p>The increasing scarcity of fossil fuels in the long run and the related rising oil prices seem to pave the way to a more intensive use of renewable energies. In order to achieve a breakthrough, however, suitable framework conditions and sustainable energy policy strategies have to be implemented.</p>
      <p>Whereas the framework conditions in a few areas still seem to be insufficient (see, e.g. the revision of the Green Electricity Act), the commitments to an increased use of renewables are already definitive. The individual EU Member States, for example, have committed themselves in the Energy and Climate Agreement to ambitious goals for reducing greenhouse gases and to promote renewable energies until 2020. For Austria this results in an obligation to increase the share of renewables to 34% of the entire energy mix by 2020 (cf. EU Website “Energy Strategy for Europe”<xref rid="fn6" ref-type="fn">6</xref>).</p>
      <p>In the course of the envisaged increase it is important to estimate the expected impacts of the expansion of using the various renewable energy carriers (e.g. solid biomass, biogas, wind, solar thermal and photovoltaics) on the environment, economy and society also quantitatively. The underlying research project was dedicated to such a quantification, by developing various expansion scenarios for renewable energy sources (RET scenarios) and to simulate these with the integrated environment–energy–economic model e3.at developed ad hoc for this project.</p>
      <p>By means of this new tool of analysis political actors are offered a significantly improved decision-making framework, compared to the typically much less comprehensive standard analysis in this field. A major advantage of integrated modeling, in contrast to straightforward potential assessments, lies in the fact that the economic interdependencies are modeled in much more detail and complexity, and that the costs of measures are fully accounted for (i.e. any financial input in one part of the system needs to be funded in another part of the system and thus is effective also there). The investments in the expansion of renewable energy thus have an immediate impact on market prices.</p>
      <p>The results provide insights as to which technologies, strategies and measures can help to achieve the increased use of renewable energy sources and also whether the resulting consequences are socially balanced, economically viable and ecologically beneficial.</p>
      <p>The developments assumed in the various scenarios can also occur in a bundled manner. By deliberately focusing on differing policy objectives and technologies, it is possible to shed some light on the impact of specific aspects. For instance, the implications of an especially ambitious expansion of biomass energy can be contrasted with the enforcement of technologies that have no fuel needs and enormous long-term potentials. Nevertheless, Austria should exploit the potential of all renewable resources available, in order to reduce the dependency of fossil fuels and reach a high diversification of the energy mix. Besides the cost-effective technologies, such as hydropower and biomass, other sources that are more investment-intensive should also be supported now, in order to unfold their potentials.</p>
      <p>The project results show clearly that an increase in the share of renewables is an important element of an “energy change”, but in itself is insufficient for reaching the energy and climate policy goals of Austria.</p>
      <p>Whereas in a scenario dedicated to the expansion of renewables, a large part of the energy-saving potential can be foregone due to direct (larger living space, inefficient heating behavior, etc.) and indirect or macroeconomic rebound (higher energy consumption due to economic growth induced by investments) effects, by <italic>additional</italic> attitude changes the entire potential could be exhausted. Only when a further increase in energy demand can be stopped by behavioral change, renewable energies can fulfill their ascribed role for achieving a sustainable energy system.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s0045">
      <label>6</label>
      <title>Summary and conclusion</title>
      <p>In the course of the project, the emphasis of the work was on two main focus areas: first, the development of the simulation model e3.at and, second, its application within a participatory modeling process, in which RET scenarios were developed in close cooperation with stakeholders and experts.</p>
      <p>The model e3.at, which integrates energy, environmental and economic aspects in an integral and consistent way, is well-suited for illustrating the impacts of an increased portion of renewable energy technologies. The integration of the environmental and the socio-economic system, with their various linkages and feedbacks, is needed in order to appropriately assist policy-makers in their decisions on suitable strategies to tackle the most challenging environmental and socio-economic problems in Austria.</p>
      <p>The valuation of energy scenarios in an integrated model such as e3.at enables to consider a wide range of aspects of the energy system, and to link economic and energy impacts. Still, the complexity of the matter requires a concentration on selected aspects only. In the case of the research project described here, the focus was on the expansion of renewable energy use for electricity and heat. A widening of the scope to further aspects, e.g. the transport sector or increases in energy efficiency and energy consumer behavior, was not part of the project.</p>
      <p>Furthermore, it has to be noted that even a very comprehensive model like e3.at is not able to provide information for a wide range of important aspects concerning the very ambitious use of renewable energy. For instance, for maintaining energy supply security it is important to account for balancing energy. Our modeling accounts for the expansion of renewable energy use over a year, but does not account for the intra-day and intra-year availability of energy. Among the renewable energy sources, especially hydropower and biomass can contribute to the balancing of the system, both with respect to the total potential and also with respect to the possibility of energy storage and load shifting. Moreover, we have to keep in mind that an adequate infrastructure (e.g. power transmission and distribution grids and electric storage systems) has to be realized, which enables the exploitation of the renewable energy potentials. However, the costs of providing this infrastructure were excluded from the analysis.</p>
      <p>From the results reported it becomes clear that achieving the Austrian target of a 34% share of renewable energy sources is not realistic on the basis of the scenarios calculated. Note, however, that the scenarios discussed focus exclusively on renewables and thus ignore other important components, such as energy retrofits of the dwelling stock or a more energy-efficient use of energy in private households. Also, the economic development and the behavior of energy consumers were not varied in the scenarios.</p>
      <p>Through its participatory approach, the project fosters the intensive exchange of experience between researchers and actual users of the results from the political, economic and societal domains. This enables an illustration of the potential impacts of renewable energy resources, which reflects actual stakeholders’ concerns. Furthermore, the involvement of various actors (energy suppliers, NGOs, public administration, etc.) with their different interests and values represents a crucial element of a democratic decision process towards a sustainable energy future. In this respect, the project contributes to the connection of science and practice by improving the dialog between stakeholders and researchers and by enhancing the transparency of the modeling process.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Adriaanse, A., Bringezu, S., Hammond, A., Moriguchi, Y., Rodenburg, E., Rogich, D., Schütz, H., 1997. Resource Flows: The Material Basis of Industrial Economies, Washington, DC.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Almon</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The INFORUM approach to interindustry modeling</article-title>
          <source>Economic Systems Research</source>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <year>1991</year>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Anderl</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gangl</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kampel</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Köther</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lorenz-Meyer</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muik</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schodl</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Poupa</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wappel</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Emissionstrends 1990–2005. Ein Überblick über die österreichischen Verursacher von Luftschadstoffen (Datenstand 2007)</chapter-title>
          <year>2007</year>
          <publisher-name>Umweltbundesamt</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Wien</publisher-loc>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bittermann, W. Mayer, B., 2011. Standard-Dokumentation. Metainformationen zu den Energiebilanzen für Österreich und die Bundesländer, Statistik Austria, Wien.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">BMVIT, Bundesministerium für Verkehr, Innovation und Technologie, 2002. Österreichisches Energieforschungs- und -technologiekonzept. Wien, Juli 2002.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">BMWFJ and BMLFUW, 2010. Energie Strategie Österreich, Bundesministerium für Wirtschaft, Familie und Jugend sowie Bundesministerium für Land- und Forstwirtschaft, Umwelt und Wasserwirtschaft, Wien, März 2010.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib9">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bodenhöfer</surname>
              <given-names>H.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wohlgemuth</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bliem</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Michael</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weyerstraß</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Bewertung der volkswirtschaftlichen Auswirkungen der Unterstützung von Ökostrom in Österreich. Endbericht</chapter-title>
          <year>2004</year>
          <publisher-name>Institut für Höhere Studien und Wissenschaftliche Forschung Kärnten</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib10">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bohunovsky L., Stocker A., Hinterberger F., Großmann A., Wolter M.I., Hutterer H., Madlener R., 2010. Volkswirtschaftliche Auswirkungen eines nachhaltigen Energiekonsums, Publizierbarer Endbericht des Projektes e-co, im Auftrag des Klima- und Energiefonds.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib12">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">CEC, 2008. Proposal for a directive of the European parliament and of the council on the promoting of the use of energy from renewable sources, Brussels, 2008/0016 (COD), 23.1.2008.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib14">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">CEC, 2009. Directive 2009/28/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 23 April 2009 on the promotion of the use of energy from renewable sources and amending and subsequently repealing Directives 2001/77/EC and 2003/30/EC.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib15">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Energy Agency, 2004. Energieeffizienz und Erneuerbare 2010. Endbericht, Wien.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib16">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">EUROSTAT, 2001. Economy-wide Material Flow Accounts and Derived Indicators. A Methodological Guide. Statistical Office of the European Union, Luxembourg.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib18">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fechner, H., Lugmaier, A., 2007. Technologie Roadmap für Photovoltaik in Österreich. Berichte aus Energie- und Umweltforschung 28/2007, BMVIT, Wien.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib19">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Großmann, A., Wolter, M.I., 2010. Dokumentation des Modells “e3.at.” E-co Working Paper Nr. 3. Wien.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib20">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Haas</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Biermayr</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kranzl</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Müller</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schriefl</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Wärme und Kälte aus Erneuerbaren 2030. Studie im Auftrag des Dachverband Energie-Klima. International Energy Agency, 2007</chapter-title>
          <year>2007</year>
          <publisher-name>Energy Prices and Taxes, IEA/OECD</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib51">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">IEA (International Energy Agency), 2007. World Energy Outlook 2007.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib21">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kaltschmitt</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neubarth</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Erneuerbare Energien in Österreich, 1. Auflage</chapter-title>
          <year>2000</year>
          <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Heidelberg, New York</publisher-loc>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib23">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kowalski, K., Madlener, R., Stagl, S., 2006. Neue Wege der integrierten Bewertung von nationalen Energieszenarien für Österreich, Symposium Energieinnovation “Dritte Energiepreiskrise—Anforderungen an die Energieinnovation”, 15–17 Februar 2006, TU Graz, Austria.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib24">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kowalski</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stagl</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Madlener</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Omann</surname>
              <given-names>I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sustainable energy futures: methodological challenges in combining scenarios and participatory multi-criteria analysis</article-title>
          <source>European Journal of Operational Research</source>
          <volume>197</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>1063</fpage>
          <lpage>1074</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib27">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lutz</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meyer</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolter</surname>
              <given-names>M.I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The global multisector/multicountry 3E-Model GINFORS. A description of the model and a baseline forecast for global energy demand and CO<sub>2</sub>-emissions</article-title>
          <source>International Journal of Global Environmental</source>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>1–2</issue>
          <year>2010</year>
          <fpage>25</fpage>
          <lpage>45</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib28">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Madlener</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kowalski</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stagl</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>New ways for the integrated appraisal of national energy scenarios: the case of renewable energy use in Austria</article-title>
          <source>Energy Policy</source>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>6060</fpage>
          <lpage>6074</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib33">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Meyer</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lutz</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schnur</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zika</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Economic policy simulations with global interdependencies: a sensitivity analysis for Germany</article-title>
          <source>Economic Systems Research</source>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>37</fpage>
          <lpage>55</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib34">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nemestothy</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Abschätzung des Holzpelletsbedarfs in Österreich</chapter-title>
          <year>2006</year>
          <publisher-name>Austrian Energy Agency</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>BMVIT, Wien</publisher-loc>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib36">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Proidl, H., 2006. Daten über Erneuerbare Energieträger in Österreich. Wien.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib37">
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rubinstein</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <chapter-title>Modeling Bounded Rationality</chapter-title>
          <year>1998</year>
          <publisher-name>The MIT Press Cambridge</publisher-name>
          <publisher-loc>Massachusetts, London, England</publisher-loc>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib38">
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sorrell</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Energy, economic growth and environmental sustainability: five propositions</article-title>
          <source>Sustainability</source>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <year>2010</year>
          <fpage>1784</fpage>
          <lpage>1809</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib40">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stocker, A., Bohunovsky, L., Großmann, A., Hinterberger F., Madlener, R., Wolter, M.I., 2008. Erneuerbare Energie in Österreich: Modellierung möglicher Entwicklungsszenarien bis 2020, Projekt-Endbericht im Rahmen der Programmlinie “Energiesysteme der Zukunft”, April 2008, Wien.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib41">
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Umweltbundesamt, 2009. Klimaschutzbericht 2009. Report, REP-0226, Wien.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <sec id="s0055">
      <label>Appendix A</label>
      <title>The integrated environment–energy–economy model “e3.at”</title>
      <p>The core of the macro-econometric model system e3.at consists of an economy model, including input–output tables, labor market data, and the system of national accounting and balancing items. Additional modules are an energy model, a material model, a transportation model, a regional housing inventory model and a model for international trade. In this annex, the model structure and components of the model e3.at are presented.</p>
      <p>Furthermore, “e3.at” has a soft link to the world model GINFORS (Global INterindustry FORcasting System, see <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Meyer et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Lutz et al., 2010</xref>), in order to illustrate the effects of international trade on the Austrian economy.</p>
      <p>e3.at was recently extended by a regional housing inventory model (see <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Bohunovsky et al., 2010</xref>), showing the energy consumption of private households on a regional level. Differences in demographic and economic aspects, such as disposable income, on the level of federal states affect the demand for housing. Depending on the improvement of accommodation (including heating systems), the energy consumption and CO<sub>2</sub> emissions are influenced by changing energy sources and/or energy-efficient heating systems. e3.at comprises also a transportation module for private households. This enables the analysis of mobility and allows valuable insights about the effects of transport on total energy consumption and CO<sub>2</sub> emissions. However, since in the reported project these two modules of e3.at are not used, we do not describe them in detail. For further information, see <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Großmann and Wolter (2010)</xref>.</p>
      <p>In the following, we describe the economic model, the material model and the energy model, respectively.</p>
      <sec id="s0060">
        <label>A.1</label>
        <title>The economic model</title>
        <p>The economic model shows a high degree of endogenization, although tax rates and labor supply are exogenous. As already stated, sectoral exports and import prices are taken from GINFORS, but they are endogenous to that system. The high degree of endogenization leads to the advantage of the effects calculated in simulations being complete, and including also direct and indirect rebound effects.</p>
        <p>In addition to the usual interdependencies between the circular flow of income, e3.at depicts the interdependencies between prices and volumes as well as between prices and wages. The model is non-linear, due to the many multiplicative connections of variables in definitions and many behavioral equations estimated in double logarithms (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Großmann and Wolter, 2010</xref>).</p>
        <p>It is a dynamic model because of the capital stock adjustment and the lags in behavioral equations. The non-linearity, combined with the interdependency of the system, requires an iterative solution procedure, which is given by the Gauss–Seidel algorithm. The dynamic structure allows a year-by-year solution for a longer time path.</p>
        <p>The core of the economic model is an IO model, which shows the interdependencies of all industries, and which is also important for linking the economic model with the material and the energy model. <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. A1</xref> shows the structure of the IO model.</p>
        <p>Within the IO model, demand determines production. First, the model specifies the final demand categories at purchasers’ prices. Then these categories are transformed to final demand categories at basic prices. In particular, this requires the exclusion of net commodity taxes and the redistribution of trade and transport margins. Based on the Leontief inverse, gross production at basic prices is then calculated as a function of final demand.</p>
        <p>However, the demand is also explained within the system, since all demand variables depend on relative prices. Prices, in turn, are given by the unit costs of the firms using the mark-up hypothesis, which is typical for oligopolistic markets. Profits and unit costs for every sector are given by definition. Together with the import price of the specific good, the unit costs determine producer prices, a calculation that is carried out for each of the components of final consumption (intermediate consumption, gross fixed capital formation, final consumption expenditures by households and government, and exports) and for each of the 57 sectors. Thus, firms set their prices depending on their costs and on the prices of competing imports. Demand reacts to price signals and, in turn, determines production as indicated above. An important feature is that the e3.at model includes both demand and supply elements and is thus not only demand-driven.</p>
        <p>The SNAB is also part of the model and is consistently linked with the input–output system. It calculates the aggregate variables and the income redistribution between government, households, firms and the rest of the world. It covers production, primary and secondary distribution of income, use of income, acquisition of non-financial assets and accumulation accounts. The behavioral equations of this system explain the expenditures; the revenues are given by definition. Net lending, respectively, net borrowing is calculated by definition for each institutional sector. The government’s budget, including the tax system and the social security system, is endogenously determined. The detail of this system allows the identification of the expenditures and revenues of the social security system, so that the system can be linked to the labor market and other parts of the model.</p>
        <p>The labor market consists of both an aggregated part and a part modeled in detail. <xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. A2</xref> depicts the structure of the labor market.</p>
        <p>In the aggregate part, the demographic development determines the macroeconomic labor supply. Unemployment is given by definition, subtracting aggregated labor demand from the exogenous labor supply.</p>
        <p>In the part modeled in detail, for each of the 57 production sectors, the labor demand is explained by gross production and the real costs of labor per capita in that sector, as well as by a time trend.</p>
        <p>A macro wage rate is calculated in a function which forecasts the result of the bargaining process between the unions and the firms: Macroeconomic labor productivity, the deflator for overall consumption and the situation on the labor market determine the macro wage rate, which, in turn, explains besides – some sector-specific variables – the sectoral wage rate. Adding social security contributions yield the labor costs per capita.</p>
        <p>The database of the labor model additionally consists of the average weekly working time, labor volume as well as of the employees’ qualifications. It is assumed that the structure of employee qualification in each sector remains constant over the entire simulation period.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0065">
        <label>A.2</label>
        <title>The material model</title>
        <p>The material input model calculates the direct material inputs (DMI) according to the “Eurostat guide on economy-wide material flow accounts” (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">EUROSTAT, 2001)</xref>. The DMI comprises “the flow of natural resource commodities that enter the industrial economy for further processing. Included in this category are grains used by a food processor, petroleum sent to a refinery, metals used by a manufacturer, and logs taken to a mill” (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Adriaanse et al., 1997</xref>, p. 8).</p>
        <p>As can be seen from <xref rid="t0030" ref-type="table">Table A1</xref>, the material model differentiates 12 material categories that are part of three material groups (biomass, minerals and fossil fuels). The model covers materials extracted in Austria as well as those import materials induced in other countries by Austrian imports. The material data was provided by a Eurostat time series from 1970 to 2001.</p>
        <p>Domestic material extraction (in tons) is linked to the extracting production sector. The direct physical material imports are driven by the imports in monetary terms (measured in constant prices). It is assumed that the development of material extraction and of economic variables is proportional.</p>
        <p>Modeling the effects of material savings considers the following process levels (see <xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. A3</xref>): At the extraction level (1), no savings are possible. This means that the production value and extraction of materials develop proportionally. The extractor delivers either to final consumption (2) or to the first process level (3). In both cases, material savings are possible due to increased efficiency. Goods produced by the first process level are used by the final consumption (4) as well as by other process levels (5). In summary, there are various interdependencies affecting material extraction.</p>
        <p>If the comparison of the historical development of the production value and material consumption shows that the production value was higher than material consumption, an increased material productivity is assumed and the input coefficients (in constant prices) in the baseline scenario are adapted. In addition, it is possible to change the input coefficients in the scenarios.</p>
        <p>The design of the material model allows to consider not only the direct changes of material use but also the indirect ones, which take place because of the various interdependencies between the different sectors. These indirect effects, induced by structural change of the IO coefficients, and the change of the structure of final demand, both of which are endogenous, are very important for the structure of physical inputs.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="s0070">
        <label>A.3</label>
        <title>The energy model</title>
        <p>The energy model describes the interrelations between economic development, energy consumption and CO<sub>2</sub> emissions. On the one hand, economic development influences primary energy use. On the other hand, expenditure for energy consumption has a direct impact on the economic variables.</p>
        <p>An adequate energy model must, therefore, be able to consider primary and secondary sources of energy, final energy, as well as losses occurring from energy conversion. In addition, the differentiation of a multiplicity of sources of energy and sufficiently detailed sector levels are necessary.</p>
        <p>The database of the energy model is the energy balance in physical units compiled by Statistik Austria, which has been available on an annual basis since 1970. The data on CO<sub>2</sub> emissions, which are connected with the primary energy use via fixed emission factors, are provided by the Austrian Environment Agency. Energy price data are taken from national statistical sources (e.g. Austrian <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Energy Agency, 2004</xref>) and the International Energy Agency (IEA, 2007). The IEA provides prices with and without taxes (excise and value added tax for selected energy sources). In order to ensure the comparability of the data, all prices refer to Terajoule (TJ).</p>
        <sec id="s0075">
          <label>A.3.1</label>
          <title>Projection of energy balances</title>
          <p>The energy balance of Statistics Austria differentiates between 37 energy sources and 21 industries. It is the starting point for the construction of the energy model. First, the energy balance is aggregated to 17 sources that comprise fossil fuels and renewable energies in much more detail than fossil fuels (see the blue cells in <xref rid="f0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. A4</xref>).</p>
          <p>Regarding the structure (see <xref rid="f0045" ref-type="fig">Fig. A5</xref>), the energy balance comprises three main parts: energy supply, transformation and energy demand. This structure holds for all energy sources considered.</p>
          <p>Starting with energy supply, domestic energy production, plus imports and stocks, minus exports, yields <italic>gross domestic consumption</italic>. The supply is determined by definition from the transformation and final energy demand.</p>
          <p>The transformation sector comprises the conversion of primary forms of energy to secondary or final energy. The transformation output is the result of this transformation process. In the transformation process, the plants do not only require primary energy (i.e. the transformation input) but also energy to operate.</p>
          <p>Total energy demand is the sum of the uses for transformation input, use within the energy sector for needs other than transformation, any losses between the points of production of the energy commodities and their final use, and final consumption. A number of fuels may also be used for <italic>non-energy purposes</italic>. An example is the transformation of fossil fuels (oil, natural gas and coke-oven by-products) and biomass carbon to synthetic organic products. Thus, final consumption consists of non-energy and energy uses.</p>
          <p>In order to determine the energy balances for all 17 energy sources in the simulation period, the final energy consumption of each of the 21 economic sectors (given by the energy balance) has to be calculated, followed by the determination of transformation input and output. Gross domestic consumption is, by definition, determined on the demand side. Finally, the imported energy goods are calculated as residuals from gross domestic consumption, stocks, exports and domestic production.</p>
          <p>In a first step, for each of the 17 sources, final energy consumption for the considered 21 industries is projected with the growth rates of real production (see <xref rid="f0050" ref-type="fig">Fig. A6</xref>). For this purpose, the 57 economic sectors of the IO model were allocated to the 21 industries that are captured in the energy model. The final energy demand of the 21 economic sectors is explained – unless better information was available – for all energy sources together.</p>
          <p>Logarithmic estimation only enters real production of the respective economic sectors, since no correlation to the price relations and, therefore, also no substitution possibilities between the sources of energy were found. The development of the total energy demand of a sector then determines the growth of final energy demand for each energy source and each economic sector.</p>
          <p>For the sectors “iron and steel“ and “private households“, more detailed information is available, so that final energy consumption can be estimated separately for each energy source. The estimation is based on real production and average energy prices as well as on technological trends and learning curves. Assumptions for the learning curves are based on recognized literature (for detailed information, see <xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Stocker et al., 2008</xref>).</p>
          <p>Final energy consumption (electricity and heat) of private households is modeled subject to the development of real consumption expenditures for electricity, natural gas and other fuels (see <xref rid="f0055" ref-type="fig">Fig. A7</xref>). Demand for heat by private households is a function of the use of fossil fuels (e.g. oil, gas), district heating and renewable energy (e.g. heat pumps, wood pellets).</p>
          <p>Apart from the oil products, the remaining sources of energy for the heat production of private households are estimated. Heat demand from oil products (fuel oil) is residually determined, i.e. it results from the difference of the entire energetic final demand of the households, electricity demand as well as heat demand from the remaining sources of energy.</p>
          <p>Final energy consumption for each energy source <italic>FEC</italic><sub><italic>ES</italic></sub> is the sum of the final energy demands over all 21 economic industrial sectors <italic>IS</italic>:<disp-formula id="eq0005"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si0001.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>with <italic>FEC</italic><sub><italic>IS,ES</italic></sub> … final energy consumption of the energy source <sub><italic>ES</italic></sub> and the industry <italic>IS</italic><disp-formula id="eq0010"><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">(∀  ∈ <italic>I</italic><italic>S</italic>[1, 21];   ∀  ∈ <italic>E</italic><italic>S</italic>[1, 17],  <italic>t</italic> =  time)</textual-form><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si0002.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>∀</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>21</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width=".1em"/><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mo>∀</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>17</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mtext>time</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula><italic>Ebtl</italic><sub><italic>IS</italic></sub><italic>…</italic> total final energy demand of the respective industry (<inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">∀  ∈ <italic>I</italic><italic>S</italic>[1, 21]</textual-form><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si0003.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>∀</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>21</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>)</p>
          <p>Total final energy consumption <italic>FEC</italic><sub><italic>ES</italic></sub> implies, in principle, the transformation output <italic>ETO</italic><sub><italic>p,ES</italic></sub>. For the subsequent years, the transformation output is determined by projecting the relationship between transformation output and final consumption from the year 2005 onwards. It is assumed that the transformation output and the final energy consumption are directly proportional to each other. The transformation output is differentiated according to the individual energy transformation plants <italic>p</italic> (coking plant, blast furnace, refinery, power stations, cogeneration plants, heating stations and gas production). The transformation output of oil and photovoltaics is modeled as a function of the transformation input, since a direct relationship exists. The transformation input is identical to the transformation output. The energy sources “gas”, “water”, “geothermal heat”, “solar heat”, “wind”, “energy from heat pumps”, “firewood”, “wood fuel” and “biofuels” have, by definition, no transformation output.<disp-formula id="eq0015"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si0004.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2005</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2005</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula><italic>ETO</italic> … transformation output of plants (<inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">∀  ∈ <italic>p</italic>[1, 7]</textual-form><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si0005.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>∀</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>), <italic>FEC</italic><sub><italic>ES</italic></sub> … total final energy consumption over all industries (<inline-formula><alternatives><textual-form specific-use="jats-markup">∀  ∈ <italic>E</italic><italic>S</italic>[1, 17]</textual-form><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si0006.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo>∀</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>17</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>).</p>
          <p>The transformation output results from converting or using primary energy (for heating or power). The output depends on the amount of primary energy used and on the technology. The technological coefficient is assumed to be constant, so that the transformation input can be calculated as<disp-formula id="eq0020"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si0007.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2005</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2005</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
          <p>In general, it is assumed that, under normal conditions, power and heat output develops proportionally (at a ratio of 1:1), i.e. if the entire final energy demand increases, the change in production of power and heat rises equally. In the scenarios, the transformation input of the energy sources, with given final energy demand, can be varied so that the power-to-heat ratio can be changed.</p>
          <p>Domestic production, changes in stocks and non-energy uses are constant. Transport losses and own use of the energy sector are modeled subject to the size of use of the respective energy source, so that these grow proportionally. Energy exports vary according to the related exports in the economic model.</p>
          <p>Gross domestic energy consumption can, by definition, be calculated either from the supply or demand perspective. On the demand side, gross domestic energy consumption is determined by transformation input, minus transformation output, plus use within the energy sector, plus non-energy use, plus transport losses and final energy use. On the supply side, gross domestic energy consumption consists of domestic energy production, plus imports and stocks, minus exports.</p>
          <p>In this modeling framework, gross domestic consumption of energy is calculated from the demand side perspective (see <xref rid="f0060" ref-type="fig">Fig. A8</xref>).</p>
          <p>After determining gross domestic energy consumption, imports can be calculated as residuals (see <xref rid="f0060" ref-type="fig">Fig. A8</xref>). A change in energy imports influences economic imports in the IO model. An increased demand for oil, for instance, on the one hand augments the amount of imports and, on the other hand, affects the price, which again causes further reactions. Energy supply is determined by definition.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0080">
          <label>A.3.2</label>
          <title>Projection of energy prices</title>
          <p>The determination of energy prices follows the duality of the selected modeling approach: On the one hand, energy prices have to be captured correctly in the energy model. On the other hand, production price indices in the concept of basic prices have to be adapted in the economic model, in order to correctly record the developments in the energy model.</p>
          <p>For the economic development, the production price indices are crucial. Due to the information that the IO model provides, the cost structure for the sector “energy and services of the energy industry” is well-known. It contains the costs for intermediate demand, capital use in the form of depreciations and labor costs. Further cost components are the net taxes on products and production.</p>
          <p>In the energy model, the development of the prices is determined on the basis of scenario assumptions and “learning curves”: These assumptions are based on various studies. The source for import prices of the fossil sources of energy is the IEA World Energy Outlook 2007 (<xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">IEA, 2007</xref>). The price history for industry and households follows the growth rates of the respective sources of energy.</p>
          <p>The energy balance is the basis for calculating changes in the input coefficients of the energy industry. In the transformation sector, the input of the different energy sources (<italic>EB</italic><sub><italic>PP&amp;CHP,ES,t</italic></sub>) is shown explicitly for power plants (PP) and combined heat and power plants (CHP), and also the sum of the energy sources used (<italic>EB</italic><sub><italic>PP&amp;CHP,t</italic></sub>). From these components it is possible to determine the ratio of use:<disp-formula id="eq0025"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si0008.gif" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>&amp;</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>&amp;</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
          <p>The changed coal and gas inputs during power generation are connected to the IO table: The price-adjusted input coefficient (input of coal and gas into the energy sector), <italic>AR</italic><sub><italic>GC,E,t</italic></sub>, is defined as the ratio of price-adjusted intermediate flows to price-adjusted production, and determines the necessary amount of electricity.</p>
          <p>Accordingly, the input coefficient <italic>AR</italic><sub><italic>GC,E,t</italic></sub> decreases proportionally when the portion of fossil energy sources in power generation declines. The consequence of additional inputs of renewable energy – with unchanged electricity consumption – thereby leads to savings in inputs (coal and gas) and thus, <italic>ceteris paribus,</italic> to a reduction of the basic prices in the related sector.</p>
          <p>So far, only one part of the changes to the cost structure of the energy industry has been captured. In addition, we have to analyze renewable energy by sources: (1) fuel-based renewable energy (firewood, wood pellets, combustible wastes, biogas, etc.) and (2) other renewable energy (solar, water, wind, etc.). For both cases, it is true that an increasing use implies that additional production capacity has to be generated.</p>
          <p>Investments have to be made, which are included in the cost accounting of the firms by the size of the consumption of fixed capital. The size of the investments depends on the costs per installed capacity unit (in kW) and the operating time (in hours). While renewable energy that is based on the regenerating of raw materials can be operated continuously, power stations using wind and solar energy are dependent on the weather situation. Accordingly, for each energy source, an investment path is computed, which entails a change in the depreciation. Thereby, it is assumed that the investments in renewable energy are additive and added to the “usual” investments in the energy sector. Hence, it follows that the depreciations in the cost calculation of the energy sector rise and thus accelerate the development of prices.</p>
          <p>In the first case, additional costs (e.g. for the use of fuels) must be added. A higher use of fuels implies proportional changes in the input coefficients of the cost structure to the ratio of use in the energy balance. Depending on the energy source, the timber industry, the chemical industry or the agricultural sector increase their portion in the cost structure of the energy industry.</p>
          <p>In the second case, the situation is more complex: For wind, water and solar energy, no intermediate consumption arises in the cost structure of the energy industry, since no costs emerge. From this, it cannot be concluded, however, that the electricity tariff declines, as long as the depreciations for, e.g. photovoltaic systems, are smaller than the savings of fossil energy sources.</p>
          <p>In both cases, renewable energy is fed into the electricity grid. The grid operator (“distributor”) pays the feed-in compensation to the renewable power producers. The power distribution companies record the costs of the electricity fed into the grid in their cost calculations. Since the feed-in compensation per kWh for renewable energy is usually higher than for conventionally produced energy, within the energy sector the input coefficient increases.</p>
          <p>Due to the missing decomposition of the energy sector (production and distribution of energy cannot be divided), the portion of renewable energy shifted within the energy sector is not known. Thus, a proper allocation has to use assumptions. In the following, it is postulated that this sector-internal flow increases by twice the savings of fossil energy resources. This hypothesis stems from the consideration that each renewable energy (except for water and firewood) is at least twice as expensive as conventionally produced energy. From this, it follows that the price changes are all the more underestimated the higher the feed-in compensation is. Especially strong is the underestimation in the case of photovoltaics. For labor costs, due to lacking information, we assume a constant development.</p>
          <p><xref rid="f0065" ref-type="fig">Fig. A9</xref> provides an overview of the connections between the economy and the energy model. Furthermore, the price effects of a higher use of renewable energy are summarized. At first glance, the figure conveys that the use of renewable energy leads to augmenting prices. However, it has to be considered that increasing prices for fossil fuels may cause an overall decelerated price development. The beneficiary of a particular energy source is thus dependent on the assumptions about energy prices in the scenarios.</p>
          <p>In addition, it has to be noted that prices for final consumption are based on the purchaser price principle, i.e. electricity tax, etc. still positively affect the development of the purchaser prices. Furthermore, the energy sector can include additional criteria – e.g. the development of the price for electricity on the stock exchange – and, accordingly, further mark-ups in the price setting. This is not the case in the modeling; rather, a constant relationship between unit costs and production prices is assumed.</p>
          <p>Finally, the consequences of the CO<sub>2</sub> emission trading are included in a simplified way. The energy industry pays the costs of the CO<sub>2</sub> certificates – the arising payment stream is accordingly booked in the SNAB – and allocates these costs equally in a way that all the production prices increase, but without additional profits for the energy industry.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s0085">
          <label>A.3.3</label>
          <title>Feedbacks between the energy model and the economic model</title>
          <p>The existing feedbacks between the economic model and the energy model are illustrated in <xref rid="f0070" ref-type="fig">Fig. A10</xref>. The economic and the energy imports and/or exports of fossil and renewable energy resources mutually influence each other in their development. A quantitative increase of the imported energy resources, such as coal or gas, equally causes a rise in the amount of the price-adjusted imported goods of the economic model. The fossil sources of energy, such as coal, gas and oil, can be added directly to the economic goods imported. Firewood, however, is only one part (approx. 4%) of the imported goods of the commodity group “forest products”.</p>
          <p>A similar logic applies to the exports. Here, however, the imported economic products determine the energy exports (i.e. the exports of the energy balance). The reason lies in the structure of the model. It is assumed that Austria’s exports are dependent on the world import demand. This is given by the world trade model GINFORS. The level of the exports depends on the market shares, which change according to the competitiveness of the observed country.</p>
          <p>Changes in industry-specific final energy demand also affect the intermediate flows of the “energy and services of the energy supply industry” as well as the associated transformation input of primary energy (coal, crude oil, natural gas, etc.) for the production of the secondary energy (district heating, electricity). Changes in the transformation input and, concomitantly, the transformation output of secondary energy in the respective converters (coking plant, refinery, heating plants, etc.) lead to a changed cost structure (see previous remarks).</p>
          <p>The change in final energy demand must be integrated into the intermediate consumption matrix accordingly. This is realized by projecting the input coefficients with the quantitative change of the assigned energy sources used for heat and power generation.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>The work for this paper was carried out within the project “Renewable energy in Austria: Modeling possible development trends until 2020” of the Research Program “Energy Systems of Tomorrow”, funded by the Austrian Ministry for Transport, Innovation and Technology (Contract no. 810709). Helpful comments from two anonymous referees and participants in the International Input Output Meeting on Managing the Environment, 9–11 July 2008, Seville, Spain, are gratefully acknowledged.</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="fn1">
        <label>1</label>
        <p>Besides the 34% goal Austria also agreed within the EU Climate and Energy Package upon reducing greenhouse gas emissions in the non-ETS sectors by 16% with regard to the 2005 level; and reducing primary energy use by 20% compared with projected levels, to be achieved by improving energy efficiency (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">BMWFJ and BMLFWU, 2010</xref>).</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn2">
        <label>2</label>
        <p>Cf. 〈<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eva.ac.at/(de)/enz/res-dat_strom.htm">www.eva.ac.at/(de)/enz/res-dat_strom.htm</ext-link>〉, accessed January 15, 2008.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn3">
        <label>3</label>
        <p>The distinction between large- and small-scale hydropower production in the model is done on the basis of the split in the energy balance between self-producing firms (so-called “Unternehmen mit Eigenanlagen”, UEA) and energy utilities (Energieversorgungsunternehmen, EVU).</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn4">
        <label>4</label>
        <p>Final energy consumption is the energy that households, industry, services, agriculture and the transport sector use.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn5">
        <label>5</label>
        <p>The overall emission reduction goal of the EU Climate and Energy Package is a reduction of 20% below 1990 levels by 2020. This reduction should on the one hand be met through binding targets for emissions from sectors not included in EU Emissions Trading System (ETS) such as transport, buildings, agriculture and waste; and on the other hand, through a reduction resulting from the ETS. While sectors in the ETS are regulated at the EU level, it will be the responsibility of the member states to define and implement policies and measures to limit emissions of “non-ETS sectors”. The Austrian target for CO<sub>2</sub> emission reduction in the non-ETS sectors is minus 16% emissions with regard to the 2005 level (see <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">BMWFJ and BMLFUW, 2010</xref>).</p>
      </fn>
      <fn id="fn6">
        <label>6</label>
        <p>〈<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/energy/index_en.htm">http://ec.europa.eu/energy/index_en.htm</ext-link>〉, accessed March 27, 2008.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="f0005">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Structure of the e.3.at model.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr1"/>
      <attrib><italic>Source</italic>: own illustration.</attrib>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0010">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Share of renewable energy in final energy consumption (in %).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr2"/>
      <attrib><italic>Source</italic>: own calculations.</attrib>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0015">
      <label>Fig. 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Development of CO<sub>2</sub> emissions (in million tons).</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr3"/>
      <attrib><italic>Source</italic>: own calculations.</attrib>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0020">
      <label>Fig. 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Centralized vs. decentralized technologies.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr4"/>
      <attrib><italic>Source</italic>: own calculations.</attrib>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0025">
      <label>Fig. A1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Structure of the input–output model.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr5"/>
      <attrib><italic>Source</italic>: own illustration.</attrib>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0030">
      <label>Fig. A2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Structure of the labor market.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr6"/>
      <attrib><italic>Source</italic>: own illustration.</attrib>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0035">
      <label>Fig. A3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Potential material savings along the process chain.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr7"/>
      <attrib><italic>Source</italic>: own illustration.</attrib>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0040">
      <label>Fig. A4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Energy sources considered.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr8"/>
      <attrib><italic>Source</italic>: own illustration.</attrib>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0045">
      <label>Fig. A5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Structure of the energy balance. <italic>Note</italic>: ES=energy sources.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr9"/>
      <attrib><italic>Source</italic>: own illustration.</attrib>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0050">
      <label>Fig. A6</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Modeling final energy demand. <italic>Note</italic>: ES=energy sources.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr10"/>
      <attrib><italic>Source</italic>: own illustration.</attrib>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0055">
      <label>Fig. A7</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Transformation of energy. <italic>Note</italic>: ES=energy sources.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr11"/>
      <attrib><italic>Source</italic>: own illustration.</attrib>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0060">
      <label>Fig. A8</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Balance equations.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr12"/>
      <attrib>
        <italic>Source:</italic>
        <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Bittermann and Mayer (2011).</xref>
      </attrib>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0065">
      <label>Fig. A9</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Modeling of the development of energy prices.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr13"/>
      <attrib><italic>Source</italic>: own illustration.</attrib>
    </fig>
    <fig id="f0070">
      <label>Fig. A10</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Feedbacks between the energy model and the economic model.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr14"/>
      <attrib><italic>Source</italic>: own illustration.</attrib>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="t0005" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Quantitative description of the “Improve Strength” (IS) Scenario.</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>
              <bold>Key technologies</bold>
            </th>
            <th colspan="2">
              <bold>Capacity</bold>
              <hr/>
            </th>
            <th colspan="2">
              <bold>Price (incl. learning curve)</bold>
              <hr/>
            </th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th/>
            <th>in TJ, 2005</th>
            <th>in TJ, 2020</th>
            <th>in ct/kWh (unless stated otherwise), 2005</th>
            <th>in ct/kWh (unless stated otherwise), 2020</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Hydro (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char">129,150</td>
            <td align="char">142,194</td>
            <td>4.90</td>
            <td>5.10</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Photovoltaics (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char">51,000</td>
            <td align="char">22,810</td>
            <td>65.14</td>
            <td>37.54</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Wind (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char">4781</td>
            <td align="char">22,235</td>
            <td>7.75</td>
            <td>6.73</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Combustible waste (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char">3634</td>
            <td align="char">40,305</td>
            <td>10.69</td>
            <td>12.64</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Biofuels (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char">10,879</td>
            <td align="char">13,525</td>
            <td>11.27</td>
            <td>11.67</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Pellets, wood residues (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char">529,000</td>
            <td align="char">1057</td>
            <td>3.26</td>
            <td>5.01</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <bold>Sum power plants</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>149,024</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>242,125</bold>
            </td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="5">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Combustible waste (CHP)</td>
            <td align="char">4065</td>
            <td align="char">6384</td>
            <td>10.69</td>
            <td>12.64</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Biofuels (CHP)</td>
            <td align="char">12,325</td>
            <td align="char">19,398</td>
            <td>11.27</td>
            <td>11.39</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Pellets, wood residues (CHP)</td>
            <td align="char">1000</td>
            <td align="char">3998</td>
            <td>3.26</td>
            <td>5.01</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <bold>Sum CHP</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>17,390</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>29,780</bold>
            </td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="5">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Geothermal energy (heating plant)</td>
            <td align="char">562,000</td>
            <td align="char">867,000</td>
            <td>8.15</td>
            <td>8.76</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Combustible waste (heating plant)</td>
            <td align="char">1976</td>
            <td align="char">3048</td>
            <td>10.69</td>
            <td>12.64</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Biofuels (heating plant)</td>
            <td align="char">236,000</td>
            <td align="char">365,000</td>
            <td>11.27</td>
            <td>11.41</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Pellets, wood residues (heating plant)</td>
            <td align="char">10,182</td>
            <td align="char">16,699</td>
            <td>3.26</td>
            <td>5.01</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <bold>Sum heating plants</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>12,956</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>20,979</bold>
            </td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="5">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Solar thermal (private households)</td>
            <td align="char">2285</td>
            <td align="char">4821</td>
            <td>8.15</td>
            <td>8.28</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Firewood (private households)</td>
            <td align="char">59,532</td>
            <td align="char">59,532</td>
            <td>37.05 €/m<sup>3</sup></td>
            <td>56.98 €/m<sup>3</sup></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Pellets, wood residues (private households)</td>
            <td align="char">6603</td>
            <td align="char">14,079</td>
            <td>3.26</td>
            <td>5.01</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Heat pump (private households)</td>
            <td align="char">688</td>
            <td align="char">1215</td>
            <td>8.15</td>
            <td>8.76</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <bold>Sum private households</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>69,108</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>79,647</bold>
            </td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="5">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <bold>Overall sum</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>248,478</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char">
              <bold>372,531</bold>
            </td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap id="t0010" position="float">
      <label>Table 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Quantitative description of the “Biomassive” (BIO) Scenario.</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>
              <bold>Key technologies</bold>
            </th>
            <th colspan="2">
              <bold>Capacity</bold>
              <hr/>
            </th>
            <th colspan="2">
              <bold>Price (incl. learning curve)</bold>
              <hr/>
            </th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th valign="middle"/>
            <th>In TJ, 2005</th>
            <th>In TJ, 2020</th>
            <th>In ct/kWh (unless stated otherwise), 2005</th>
            <th>In ct/kWh (unless stated otherwise), 2020</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Hydro (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">129,150</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">137,028</td>
            <td>4.90</td>
            <td>5.10</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Photovoltaics (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">51</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">22,810</td>
            <td>65.14</td>
            <td>37.54</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Wind (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">4781</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">12,331</td>
            <td>7.75</td>
            <td>7.13</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Combustible waste (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">3634</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">12,718</td>
            <td>10.69</td>
            <td>12.64</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Biofuels (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">10,879</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">45,445</td>
            <td>11.27</td>
            <td>10.26</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Pellets, wood residues (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">529</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">5864</td>
            <td>3.26</td>
            <td>5.01</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">
              <bold>Sum power plants</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>149,024</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>236,195</bold>
            </td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="5" valign="middle">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Combustible waste (CHP)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">4065</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">6384</td>
            <td>10.69</td>
            <td>12.64</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Biofuels (CHP)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">12,325</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">19,358</td>
            <td>11.27</td>
            <td>11.39</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Pellets, wood residues (CHP)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">1000</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">3998</td>
            <td>3.26</td>
            <td>5.01</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">
              <bold>Sum CHP</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>17,390</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>29,740</bold>
            </td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="5" valign="middle">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Geothermal energy (heating plant)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">562</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">867</td>
            <td>8.15</td>
            <td>8.76</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Combustible waste (heating plant)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">1976</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">3048</td>
            <td>10.69</td>
            <td>12.64</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Biofuels (heating plant)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">236</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">388</td>
            <td>11.27</td>
            <td>11.33</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Pellets, wood residues (heating plant)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">10,182</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">16,699</td>
            <td>3.26</td>
            <td>5.01</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">
              <bold>Sum heating plants</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>12,956</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>21,002</bold>
            </td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="5" valign="middle">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Solar thermal (private households)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">2285</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">4821</td>
            <td>8.15</td>
            <td>8.28</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Firewood (private households)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">59,532</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">65,485</td>
            <td>37.05 €/m<sup>3</sup></td>
            <td>56.98 €/m<sup>3</sup></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Pellets, wood residues (private households)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">6603</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">14,079</td>
            <td>3.26</td>
            <td>5.01</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Heat pump (private households)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">688</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">1215</td>
            <td>8.15</td>
            <td>8.76</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">
              <bold>Sum private households</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>69,108</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>85,600</bold>
            </td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="5" valign="middle">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">
              <bold>Overall sum</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>248,478</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>372,537</bold>
            </td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap id="t0015" position="float">
      <label>Table 3</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Quantitative description of the “Think about Tomorrow” (TAT) Scenario.</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>
              <bold>Key technologies</bold>
            </th>
            <th colspan="2">
              <bold>Capacity</bold>
              <hr/>
            </th>
            <th colspan="2">
              <bold>Price (incl. learning curve)</bold>
              <hr/>
            </th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th valign="middle"/>
            <th>In (TJ), 2005</th>
            <th>In (TJ), 2020</th>
            <th>In ct/kWh (unless stated otherwise), 2005</th>
            <th>In ct/kWh (unless stated otherwise), 2020</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Hydro (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">129,150</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">137,028</td>
            <td>4.90</td>
            <td>5.10</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Photovoltaics (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">51</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">82,722</td>
            <td>65.14</td>
            <td>32.33</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Wind (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">4781</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">22,235</td>
            <td>7.75</td>
            <td>6.73</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Combustible waste (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">3634</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">12,718</td>
            <td>10.69</td>
            <td>12.64</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Biofuels (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">10,879</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">13,525</td>
            <td>11.27</td>
            <td>11.67</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Pellets, wood residues (power plants)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">529</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">1057</td>
            <td>3.26</td>
            <td>5.01</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">
              <bold>Sum power plants</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>149,024</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>269,285</bold>
            </td>
            <td valign="middle"/>
            <td valign="middle"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="5" valign="middle">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Combustible waste (CHP)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">4065</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">6384</td>
            <td>10.69</td>
            <td>12.64</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Biofuels (CHP)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">12,325</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">19,398</td>
            <td>11.27</td>
            <td>11.39</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Pellets, wood residues (CHP)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">1000</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">3998</td>
            <td>3.26</td>
            <td>5.01</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">
              <bold>Sum CHP</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>17,390</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>29,780</bold>
            </td>
            <td valign="middle"/>
            <td valign="middle"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="5" valign="middle">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Geothermal energy (heating plant)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">562</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">1125</td>
            <td>8.15</td>
            <td>8.06</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Combustible waste (heating plant)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">1976</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">3048</td>
            <td>10.69</td>
            <td>12.64</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Biofuels (heating plant)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">236</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">365</td>
            <td>11.27</td>
            <td>11.41</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Pellets, wood waste (heating plant)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">10,182</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">16,699</td>
            <td>3.26</td>
            <td>5.01</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">
              <bold>Sum heating plants</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>12,956</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>21,237</bold>
            </td>
            <td valign="middle"/>
            <td valign="middle"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="5" valign="middle">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Solar thermal (private households)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">2285</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">7232</td>
            <td>8.15</td>
            <td>.02</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Firewood (private households)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">59,532</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">59,532</td>
            <td>37.05 €/m<sup>3</sup></td>
            <td>56.98 €/m<sup>3</sup></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Pellets, wood residues (private households)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">6603</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">14,079</td>
            <td>3.26</td>
            <td>5.01</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">Heat pump (private households)</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">688</td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">1215</td>
            <td>8.15</td>
            <td>8.06</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">
              <bold>Sum private households</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>69,108</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>82,058</bold>
            </td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="5" valign="middle">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td valign="middle">
              <bold>Overall sum</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>248,478</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="char" valign="middle">
              <bold>402,360</bold>
            </td>
            <td valign="middle"/>
            <td valign="middle"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap id="t0020" position="float">
      <label>Table 4</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Components of gross domestic product (GDP), inflation-adjusted—average growth rates (5-year intervals).</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th/>
            <th>1995–2000</th>
            <th>2000–2005</th>
            <th>2005–2010</th>
            <th>2010–2015</th>
            <th>2015–2020</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="6">Business as Usual</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> GDP</td>
            <td>2.94</td>
            <td>1.45</td>
            <td align="char">2.26</td>
            <td align="char">1.96</td>
            <td align="char">2.20</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Consumption private households</td>
            <td>2.23</td>
            <td>1.46</td>
            <td align="char">1.96</td>
            <td align="char">1.76</td>
            <td align="char">1.91</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Consumption public sector</td>
            <td>2.02</td>
            <td>1.00</td>
            <td align="char">0.67</td>
            <td align="char">0.28</td>
            <td align="char">0.94</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Investments</td>
            <td>3.24</td>
            <td>−0.22</td>
            <td align="char">2.33</td>
            <td align="char">1.69</td>
            <td align="char">1.96</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Exports</td>
            <td>9.74</td>
            <td>5.65</td>
            <td align="char">6.14</td>
            <td align="char">5.26</td>
            <td align="char">4.99</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Imports</td>
            <td>7.44</td>
            <td>5.37</td>
            <td align="char">5.52</td>
            <td align="char">4.76</td>
            <td align="char">4.67</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="6" align="right">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="6">Improve Strength</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> GDP</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">2.33</td>
            <td align="char">1.99</td>
            <td align="char">2.19</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Consumption private households</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">2.01</td>
            <td align="char">1.77</td>
            <td align="char">1.90</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Consumption public sector</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">0.78</td>
            <td align="char">0.34</td>
            <td align="char">0.96</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Investments</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">2.65</td>
            <td align="char">1.91</td>
            <td align="char">1.99</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Exports</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">6.13</td>
            <td align="char">5.25</td>
            <td align="char">4.98</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Imports</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">5.59</td>
            <td align="char">4.79</td>
            <td align="char">4.66</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="6" align="right">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="6">Biomassive</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> GDP</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">2.35</td>
            <td align="char">1.99</td>
            <td align="char">2.20</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Consumption private households</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">2.02</td>
            <td align="char">1.78</td>
            <td align="char">1.91</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Consumption public sector</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">0.80</td>
            <td align="char">0.36</td>
            <td align="char">0.99</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Investments</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">2.72</td>
            <td align="char">1.94</td>
            <td align="char">2.03</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Exports</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">6.13</td>
            <td align="char">5.25</td>
            <td align="char">4.98</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Imports</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">5.61</td>
            <td align="char">4.79</td>
            <td align="char">4.67</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="6" align="right">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="6">Think about Tomorrow</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> GDP</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">2.46</td>
            <td align="char">1.99</td>
            <td align="char">2.15</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Consumption private households</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">2.10</td>
            <td align="char">1.76</td>
            <td align="char">1.86</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Consumption public sector</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">0.96</td>
            <td align="char">0.37</td>
            <td align="char">0.94</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Investments</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">3.27</td>
            <td align="char">2.07</td>
            <td align="char">1.88</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Exports</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">6.11</td>
            <td align="char">5.24</td>
            <td align="char">4.97</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td> Imports</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">5.74</td>
            <td align="char">4.80</td>
            <td align="char">4.62</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap id="t0025" position="float">
      <label>Table 5</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Share of renewable energy (in % and in TJ).</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left"/>
            <th align="left"/>
            <th align="left">
              <bold>BAU</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="left">
              <bold>IS</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="left">
              <bold>BIO</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="left">
              <bold>TAT</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="left">
              <bold>Total</bold>
            </th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th align="left"/>
            <th align="left">
              <bold>2005</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="left">
              <bold>2020</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="left">
              <bold>2020</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="left">
              <bold>2020</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="left">
              <bold>2020</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="left">
              <bold>2020</bold>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">
              <italic>Final energy consumption (total)</italic>
            </td>
            <td>
              <italic>1,105,190</italic>
            </td>
            <td>
              <italic>1,448,683</italic>
            </td>
            <td>
              <italic>1,451,472</italic>
            </td>
            <td>
              <italic>1,452,544</italic>
            </td>
            <td>
              <italic>1,453,400</italic>
            </td>
            <td>
              <italic>1,453,400</italic>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="7" align="left">
              <italic>Final energy consumption (renewables)</italic>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"> Geothermal</td>
            <td>259</td>
            <td>351</td>
            <td>353</td>
            <td>354</td>
            <td>354</td>
            <td>354</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"> Solar thermal</td>
            <td>3816</td>
            <td>6895</td>
            <td>6904</td>
            <td>6908</td>
            <td>9323</td>
            <td>9323</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"> Heat pumps</td>
            <td>4976</td>
            <td>7125</td>
            <td>7161</td>
            <td>7174</td>
            <td>7200</td>
            <td>7200</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"> Firewood</td>
            <td>64,737</td>
            <td>66,439</td>
            <td>66,451</td>
            <td>72,388</td>
            <td>66,464</td>
            <td>72,388</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"> Combustible waste</td>
            <td>10,615</td>
            <td>13,957</td>
            <td>13,972</td>
            <td>13,981</td>
            <td>13,981</td>
            <td>13,981</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"> Biofuels</td>
            <td>16,139</td>
            <td>20,500</td>
            <td>20,514</td>
            <td>20,516</td>
            <td>20,529</td>
            <td>20,529</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"> Pellets, wood residues</td>
            <td>25,954</td>
            <td>40,232</td>
            <td>40,317</td>
            <td>40,336</td>
            <td>40,389</td>
            <td>40,336</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">
              <italic>Sum renewable energy in TJ</italic>
            </td>
            <td>260,477</td>
            <td>306,222</td>
            <td>342,771</td>
            <td>333,685</td>
            <td>399,719</td>
            <td>410,757</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">
              <italic>Share renewable energy in %</italic>
            </td>
            <td>23.6</td>
            <td>21.1</td>
            <td>23.6</td>
            <td>23.0</td>
            <td>27.5</td>
            <td>28.3</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn>
          <p><italic>Note</italic>: The share of renewable energy is based on the EC definition (see <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">CEC, 2008</xref>/0016 (COD)).</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap id="t0030" position="float">
      <label>Table A1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Overview of material inputs covered by the material model.</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left"/>
            <th align="left">
              <bold>Domestic extraction</bold>
            </th>
            <th align="left">
              <bold>Material imports</bold>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">
              <bold>Biomass</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="left">Food</td>
            <td align="left">Food</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"/>
            <td align="left">Feed stock</td>
            <td align="left">Feed stock</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"/>
            <td align="left">Animals</td>
            <td align="left">Animals</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"/>
            <td align="left">Forestry</td>
            <td align="left">Forestry</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"/>
            <td align="left">Non-edible biomass</td>
            <td align="left">Non-edible biomass</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="3" align="left">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">
              <bold>Minerals</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="left">Construction minerals</td>
            <td align="left">Construction minerals</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"/>
            <td align="left">Industrial minerals</td>
            <td align="left">Industrial minerals</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"/>
            <td align="left">Ores</td>
            <td align="left">Ores</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td colspan="3" align="left">  </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">
              <bold>Fossil fuels</bold>
            </td>
            <td align="left">Coal</td>
            <td align="left">Coal</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"/>
            <td align="left">Crude oil</td>
            <td align="left">Crude oil</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"/>
            <td align="left">Natural gas</td>
            <td align="left">Natural gas</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left"/>
            <td align="left">Other fossil fuels</td>
            <td align="left">Other fossil fuels</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>