<article xmlns="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="other">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biol Psychiatry</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Biological Psychiatry</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0006-3223</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1873-2402</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2930212</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">20678755</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">BPS10615</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2010.02.026</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Correspondence</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>No Correlation Between Childhood Maltreatment and Telomere Length</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Glass</surname>
            <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>dan.glass@kcl.ac.uk</email>
          <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Parts</surname>
            <given-names>Leopold</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Knowles</surname>
            <given-names>David</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Aviv</surname>
            <given-names>Abraham</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Spector</surname>
            <given-names>Tim D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Kings' College London, Department of Twin Research and Genetic Epidemiology, St. Thomas' Hospital Campus, Westminster Bridge Road, London SE1 7EH, United Kingdom</aff>
      <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute, Hinxton, United Kingdom</aff>
      <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>University of Cambridge, Cambridge, United Kingdom</aff>
      <aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>University of Medicine and Dentistry New Jersey, Newark, New Jersey</aff>
      <aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Kings' College London, Department of Twin Research and Genetic Epidemiology, London, United Kingdom</aff>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2010</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>68</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>e21</fpage>
      <lpage>e22</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2010 Elsevier Inc.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2010</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Society of Biological Psychiatry</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/authorsview.authors/supplementalterms1.0">certain conditions</ext-link>.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p content-type="salutation">To the Editor:</p>
    <p>Telomeres are lengths of repetitive DNA that cap the ends of chromosomes. They protect the ends of the chromosome and shorten with each cell division. Short leukocyte telomere length has been related to a number of age-related diseases (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). In addition, shorter telomere length has been associated with environmental factors such as smoking and lack of exercise (<xref rid="bib2 bib3" ref-type="bibr">2,3</xref>). In a recent issue of <italic>Biological Psychiatry</italic>, Tyrka <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) published a report suggesting a link between maltreatment in childhood and telomere shortening in 31 subjects. Individuals who had suffered maltreatment had telomere length .70 ± .24 compared with 1.02 ± .52 in individuals who had not been abused.</p>
    <p>We were interested in this plausible theory and decided to investigate these findings in the larger Twins UK cohort. Twins UK is a registry of ∼11,000 British twins that has been shown to be representative of the general population. Twins have answered questionnaires on two occasions relating to maltreatment, be it sexual, physical, or emotional abuse. One questionnaire asked specifically about maltreatment in childhood (2005) and one referred to maltreatment at any time (2008). The specific questions asked were the following: “As a child, were you ever a victim of physical abuse?” “As a child, were you ever a victim of sexual abuse?” “Have you ever been physically abused?” “Have you ever been emotionally abused?” “Have you ever been sexually abused?”</p>
    <p>The possible answers were Yes, No, or no answer. We only considered subjects that gave a consistent answer to the physical abuse or the sexual abuse questions in both questionnaires. We felt it further strengthened our phenotype to have corroborative data at two time points.</p>
    <p>Mean leukocyte telomere length was derived from the mean of the terminal restriction fragment length by using the Southern blot method on DNA extracted from peripheral leukocytes, as described elsewhere (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Each DNA sample was analyzed twice. If the difference between the duplicates was &gt;5%, a third measurement was performed, and the mean of the two results &lt;5% apart was taken. The coefficient of variation of the terminal restriction fragment length assay in the study was 1.5%. Telomere length was essentially normally distributed.</p>
    <p>There is no significant difference in telomere length between people who have been abused and those who have not been abused (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The result holds for parametric and nonparametric tests and including or excluding possible confounding factors (age, gender, smoking, and body mass index).</p>
    <p>When we looked at individuals who had answered the maltreatment in childhood questionnaire alone, we had a much larger sample size. With 123 cases and 1751 control subjects, there remains no significant difference in the mean telomere length between those subjects who had suffered sexual abuse and those who had not. The mean telomere length in this group is identical in cases and control subjects. This result was unchanged when possible confounders (age, body mass index, smoking status, and gender) were included in the linear model.</p>
    <p>We have failed to replicate the findings of Tyrka <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), despite a sample size several-fold larger. There are certain methodological differences that may account for this lack of replication. Our telomere measurements were performed with Southern blot as opposed to quantitative polymerase chain reaction used in the previous article. We have, however, previously demonstrated significant changes using these assays with other phenotypes, such as lack of exercise, obesity, smoking, social class, and number of nevi. The assays are significantly correlated and the Southern blot method, although labor intensive, is thought to be the gold standard (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>).</p>
    <p>The questionnaires to assess abuse used by Tyrka <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) and Twins UK are different. We have confidence in our phenotype; by using twins who have reported maltreatment in both questionnaires, we have isolated a robust group of cases for analysis.</p>
    <p>Many different environmental factors are known to reduce telomeres, such as cigarette smoking, obesity, lack of exercise, and social class, as well as genes (<xref rid="bib2 bib3 bib7" ref-type="bibr">2,3,7</xref>). With a small selected sample such as that used by Tyrka <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), rather than the abuse, any of these confounding external factors could actually be responsible for the difference in telomere length they observed or it could have been due to chance.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bib1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Calado</surname>
              <given-names>R.T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Young</surname>
              <given-names>N.S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Telomere diseases</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med</source>
          <volume>361</volume>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>2353</fpage>
          <lpage>2365</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20007561</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Valdes</surname>
              <given-names>A.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrew</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gardner</surname>
              <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kimura</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oelsner</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cherkas</surname>
              <given-names>L.F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Obesity, cigarette smoking, and telomere length in women</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <volume>366</volume>
          <year>2005</year>
          <fpage>662</fpage>
          <lpage>664</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16112303</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cherkas</surname>
              <given-names>L.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hunkin</surname>
              <given-names>J.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kato</surname>
              <given-names>B.S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Richards</surname>
              <given-names>J.B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gardner</surname>
              <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Surdulescu</surname>
              <given-names>G.L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The association between physical activity in leisure time and leukocyte telomere length</article-title>
          <source>Arch Intern Med</source>
          <volume>168</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>154</fpage>
          <lpage>158</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18227361</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tyrka</surname>
              <given-names>A.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Price</surname>
              <given-names>L.H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kao</surname>
              <given-names>H.T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Porton</surname>
              <given-names>B.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marsella</surname>
              <given-names>S.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carpenter</surname>
              <given-names>L.L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Childhood maltreatment and telomere shortening: Preliminary support for an effect of early stress on cellular aging</article-title>
          <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>531</fpage>
          <lpage>534</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19828140</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Andrew</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aviv</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Falchi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Surdulescu</surname>
              <given-names>G.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gardner</surname>
              <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lu</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mapping genetic loci that determine leukocyte telomere length in a large sample of unselected female sibling pairs</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>480</fpage>
          <lpage>486</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16400618</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>O'Callaghan</surname>
              <given-names>N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dhillon</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fenech</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A quantitative real-time PCR method for absolute telomere length</article-title>
          <source>BioTechniques</source>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <year>2008</year>
          <fpage>807</fpage>
          <lpage>809</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18476834</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cherkas</surname>
              <given-names>L.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aviv</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valdes</surname>
              <given-names>A.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hunkin</surname>
              <given-names>J.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gardner</surname>
              <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Surdulescu</surname>
              <given-names>G.L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The effects of social status on biological aging as measured by white-blood-cell telomere length</article-title>
          <source>Aging Cell</source>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>361</fpage>
          <lpage>365</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16856882</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <ack>
      <p>The Twins UK study was supported by the Wellcome Trust; the Department of Health via the National Institute for Health Research, a comprehensive Biomedical Research Centre award to Guy's and St. Thomas' National Health Service Foundation Trust in partnership with King's College London, European Commission Framework 7 Health-2007-A ENGAGE project, and the Chronic Disease Research Foundation.</p>
      <p>We thank all the volunteer twins who gave their time.</p>
      <p>TDS is a National Institute for Health Research senior investigator. DG is a Medical Research Council Clinical Research Fellow. LP is supported by the Wellcome Trust. DK is supported by Microsoft through the Needham Scholarship. The authors report no biomedical financial interest or potential conflicts of interest.</p>
      <p>Authors DG and LP contributed equally to this work.</p>
    </ack>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="fig1">
      <label>Figure 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>A graph showing no significant difference in mean telomere length in those who had suffered physical or sexual abuse compared with those who had not suffered abuse (<italic>t</italic> test <italic>p</italic> value .61 and .10, respectively). LCL, .</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr1"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Telomere Length in Individuals with a History of Abuse Compared with Those with No History of Abuse</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left"/>
            <th align="center">Mean and Standard Deviation of Telomere Length in Subjects with a History of Abuse</th>
            <th align="center">Mean and Standard Deviation of Telomere Length in Subjects with no History of Abuse</th>
            <th align="center">Number of Subjects (Abused)</th>
            <th align="center">Number of Subjects (Not Abused)</th>
            <th align="center">Two-Sample <italic>t</italic> Test <italic>p</italic> Value</th>
            <th align="center">Mann–Whitney Test <italic>p</italic> Value</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Physical Abuse</td>
            <td align="char">7.04 (.58)</td>
            <td align="char">6.97 (.67)</td>
            <td align="center">20</td>
            <td align="center">520</td>
            <td align="char">.61</td>
            <td align="char">.71</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Sexual Abuse</td>
            <td align="char">6.86 (.53)</td>
            <td align="char">7.05 (.66)</td>
            <td align="center">34</td>
            <td align="center">516</td>
            <td align="char">.10</td>
            <td align="char">.13</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>