<article xmlns="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="brief-report">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Biochem Parasitol</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Molecular and Biochemical Parasitology</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0166-6851</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1872-9428</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier/North-Holland Biomedical Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3223521</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22008417</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">MOLBIO10602</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molbiopara.2011.10.001</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Short Communication</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>UDP-xylose and UDP-galactose synthesis in <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Rosenberger</surname>
            <given-names>Andrea F.N.</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hangelmann</surname>
            <given-names>Lydia</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hofinger</surname>
            <given-names>Andreas</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Wilson</surname>
            <given-names>Iain B.H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <email>iain.wilson@boku.ac.at</email>
          <xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff>Department für Chemie, Universität für Bodenkultur, A-1190 Wien, Austria</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor0005"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. Tel.: +43 1 47654 6541; fax: +43 1 47654 6076. <email>iain.wilson@boku.ac.at</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>181</volume>
      <issue>1-2</issue>
      <fpage>53</fpage>
      <lpage>56</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>3</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2011</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2012 Elsevier B.V.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2011</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Elsevier B.V.</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/authorsview.authors/supplementalterms1.0">certain conditions</ext-link>.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract abstract-type="graphical">
        <sec>
          <title>Graphical abstract</title>
          <p>The genes encoding the enzymes required for UDP-xylose and UDP-galactose synthesis in <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> have been identified and the products of the recombinant enzymes analysed.<fig id="fig0005" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="fx1"/></fig></p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Highlights</title>
          <p>► Xylose and galactose are components of <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> glycans. ► <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> UDP-xylose synthase and UDP-galactose epimerase genes identified. ► Enzymes were expressed in recombinant form, purified and assayed.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <abstract>
        <p>The presence of xylose and galactose residues in the structure of trichomonad lipoglycans was indicated by previous studies and the modification of any glycoconjugate with either monosaccharide requires the respective presence of the nucleotide sugars, UDP-xylose and UDP-galactose. Biosynthesis of UDP-xylose <italic>de novo</italic> is mediated by UDP-xylose synthase (UXS; UDP-glucuronic acid decarboxylase), which converts UDP-glucuronic acid to UDP-xylose, whereas UDP-galactose can be generated from UDP-glucose by UDP-galactose epimerases (GalE). <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> cDNAs, encoding proteins with homology to these enzymes from other eukaryotes, were isolated. The recombinant <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> UDP-xylose synthase and UDP-galactose epimerase were expressed in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and tested via high pressure liquid chromatography to demonstrate their enzymatic activities. Thereby, in this first report on enzymes involved in glycoconjugate biosynthesis in this organism, we demonstrate the existence of xylose and galactose synthesising pathways in <italic>T. vaginalis</italic>.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Abbreviations</title>
        <kwd>GalE, UDP-galactose-4′-epimerase</kwd>
        <kwd>UDP-GlcA, UDP-glucuronic acid</kwd>
        <kwd>UXS, UDP-xylose synthase</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>UDP-xylose</kwd>
        <kwd>UDP-galactose</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic>
        </kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p><italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> is a parasitic flagellated protozoan which causes human trichomoniasis, one of the most common sexually transmitted diseases in humans. Despite its wide spread and high prevalence, with more than 200 million affected people and at least three million new cases per year in the USA <xref rid="bib0005 bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[1,2]</xref>, it has proven to be an underestimated disease. Indeed, an infection with <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> causes not only vaginitis, exocervicitis and urethritis, it is also implicated in miscarriages and occurrence of human immunodeficiency virus. Cytopathogenicity starts with the adhesion of the protozoan to the host cell and indeed glycoconjugates such as a lipoglycan covering its cell surface are important for the parasite's interaction with its host <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. The structure of this lipoglycan <xref rid="bib0020 bib0025" ref-type="bibr">[4,5]</xref>, as well as of its protein-linked N-glycans <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, have been recently determined to contain monosaccharides such as xylose and galactose. In order to perform the relevant xylosylation and galactosylation reactions necessary for the biosynthesis of these glycan structures <italic>in vivo</italic>, the organism requires the relevant nucleotide sugars, UDP-xylose and UDP-galactose.</p>
    <p>UDP-xylose is the product of a two-step conversion from UDP-glucose: first, dehydrogenation of UDP-glucose is catalyzed by UDP-glucose dehydrogenase (UGD, EC 1.1.1.22) thus forming UDP-glucuronic acid (UDP-GlcA). Then, UDP-glucuronic acid decarboxylase (UDP-xylose synthase; UXS, EC 4.1.1.35) acts on UDP-GlcA to form UDP-xylose <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Depending on the organism, UXS may be cytosolically or lumenally located. In plants, the biosynthesis of UDP-xylose by different UXS isoforms occurs both in the cytosol and in membrane-bound compartments <xref rid="bib0035 bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[7,8]</xref>. Mammals and nematodes on the other hand express only one UXS, which is located in the golgi apparatus <xref rid="bib0045 bib0050" ref-type="bibr">[9,10]</xref>, whereas the fungus <italic>Cryptococcus</italic> expresses only one, probably cytosolic, form <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. In bacteria such as <italic>Micromonospora echinospora</italic> and <italic>Sinorhizoboium meliloti</italic> UDP-xylose is also synthesised from UDP-glucuronic acid <xref rid="bib0060 bib0065" ref-type="bibr">[12,13]</xref>. On the other hand, the <italic>de novo</italic> biosynthesis of UDP-galactose from UDP-glucose is mediated by the cytosolic UDP-galactose epimerase (GalE; EC 5.1.3.2); the relevant GalE genes have been identified from a number of organisms and in <italic>T. brucei</italic> GalE is essential for growth <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>.</p>
    <p>Considering that xylose and galactose are components of several <italic>Trichomonas</italic> glycoconjugates we expected that this organism possesses at least one UXS and one GalE gene. Homology searching of the <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> genome from the G3 strain <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref> was performed and the annotation suggested the presence of two putative homologues of UDP-galactose epimerase (GalE1, TVAG_186740 and TVAG_101620) and one putative homologue of UDP-xylose synthase (TVAG_178290). In the case of the UDP-xylose synthase the relevant reading frame is predicted to encode a protein of 313 residues lacking a transmembrane domain; therefore, the <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> enzyme is proposed to be a cytosolic protein as is the case with the fungal and some plant isoforms. Using RNA extracted from <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> (C1 strain; ATCC 30001), the UXS and one of the GalE reading frames were isolated by two-step RT-PCR using the primer pairs Tv-UXS-for-NcoI (catgccatggtgagtacacctaccaagagtac) and Tv-UXS-rev-SacI (ccgagctctagtaacatttagaaaatgtttta) or Tv-GalE1-for-BamHI (cgcggatccatgtctatcctcatacaggc) and Tv-GalE1-rev-HindIII (cccaagcttttaagctctgtagccatttgg) prior to ligation into the pET30a vector. The recombinant proteins were expressed in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> (DE3) pLysS Gold cells upon induction with isopropyl-β-<sc>d</sc>-thiogalactopyranoside at 25 or 37 °C for 3 h; cells were lysed and the recombinant proteins isolated by purification on Ni/nitrilotriacetate resin and elution with 250 mM imidazole. The purified forms of the recombinant proteins were analysed by SDS–PAGE and Western blotting and displayed molecular masses of ∼40 kDa (data not shown) in agreement with the size predicted from the amino acid sequences.</p>
    <p>In the UXS sequence, two ‘silent’ nucleotide alterations were observed in the UXS cDNA cloned from the C1 strain; the amino acid sequence is thereby identical with that predicted from the genomic sequence available from the G3 strain (data not shown; Genbank/EBI accession number HE575670). The trichomonad UXS protein is 57% identical to the human sequence over 307 amino acids and 50% identical to predicted, but uncharacterised, proteins from <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:XP_820252">XP_820252</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-p:XP_806161">XP_806161</ext-link>). UDP-xylose synthase activity of UXS was verified by assaying with UDP-glucuronic acid (UDP-GlcA) as substrate and NAD<sup>+</sup> as a cofactor. The negative control (with <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> GDP-mannose dehydratase) displayed no conversion of UDP-GlcA to UDP-Xyl, whereas incubations with the positive control (UXS from <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic> <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>) and the UXS from <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> showed the generation of a clear UDP-xylose peak as judged by either SAX (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A) or RP-HPLC (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>B). Substrate conversion was dependent on incubation time and the amount of protein, whereas no product was formed after heat inactivation of the protein (data not shown). The UDP-xylose produced by the purified <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> enzyme was collected from a number of HPLC runs prior to analysis by MALDI-TOF MS and NMR. The <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> value of 535.4 for the [M−H]<sup>−</sup> molecular ion (<xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>C) is as expected, whereas the in-source fragment of 403.1 corresponds to loss of a pentose to yield UDP. Key chemical shifts in the <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>31</sup>P NMR spectra, as compared to literature data <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, confirm the identity of the UXS enzymatic product as UDP-xylose (<xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p>
    <p>The purified UXS was examined further in terms of its pH and temperature optima. The enzyme exhibited a good activity over a broad pH range (5.5–8.0) with an optimum of around pH 7.0 (<xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>A). This optimum compares well to that for <italic>Cryptococcus</italic> UXS <xref rid="bib0030 bib0055" ref-type="bibr">[6,11]</xref>, <italic>Sinorhizobium</italic> UXS <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> and endomembrane-associated <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> UXS2 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, but is higher than that for the plant UXS3 <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. The activity of the enzyme was not significantly affected by either MgCl<sub>2</sub> or MnCl<sub>2</sub> (data not shown). The expressed protein was active at temperatures from 4 to 50 °C whereas its activity was nearly abolished at 70 °C (<xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>B) and the highest activity could be achieved at 37 to 50 °C, consistent with efficient function within a mammalian host; a similar temperature optimum has been observed for <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> UXS2 <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Incubating UDP-xylose synthase for 1 h, in the absence of substrate or cofactor, at various temperatures indicated that the enzyme is quite stable between 4 and 30 °C, whereas its stability decreases with higher temperatures (data not shown).</p>
    <p>In the case of UDP-galactose epimerase, the two identified (TVAG_186740 and TVAG_101620) open reading frames predicted protein sequences of 340 residues with 92% identity. Therefore we decided to clone only one of these cDNAs and designated the reading frame TVAG_186740 as GalE1. One consistent nucleotide alteration in three cDNA clones suggests that the GalE1 from the C1 strain differs in one non-conserved amino acid as compared to the G3 strain (residue 98 is Glu rather than Lys). The trichomonad GalE1 is 57% identical to the 335 amino acids long human homologue and 38% to the characterised <italic>T. cruzi</italic> enzyme (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ncbi-n:AJ577814">AJ577814</ext-link>). Incubations to test epimerase activity were analysed using the same ion-pair RP-HPLC system as for the UDP-xylose synthase assays; it was found that <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> GalE1 could convert UDP-glucose into UDP-galactose and vice versa with final ratios of either 22:78 or 24:76 UDP-Gal:UDP-Glc (<xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>D), suggesting that the equilibrium favours the formation of UDP-Glc. A similar ratio of 1:3 UDP-Gal:UDP-Glc was found when using <italic>Saccharomyces fragilis</italic> as a source of epimerase activity <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. A control experiment with the purified <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> UXS indicated no such conversion, verifying that no UDP-galactose epimerase activity from the <italic>E. coli</italic> host was present in fractions eluted from the Ni(II)-chelation column.</p>
    <p>In conclusion, we show that recombinant forms of <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> UDP-xylose synthetase (UXS) and UDP-galactose epimerase (GalE1) are indeed enzymatically active and so are the first glycosylation-related enzymes from this organism to be characterised; furthermore, this UXS is the first to be studied from a unicellular parasite.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="bib0005">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fiori</surname>
              <given-names>P.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rappelli</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Addis</surname>
              <given-names>M.F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The flagellated parasite <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic>: new insights into cytopathogenicity mechanisms</article-title>
          <source>Microbes Infect</source>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <year>1999</year>
          <fpage>149</fpage>
          <lpage>156</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10594979</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0010">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schwebke</surname>
              <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burgess</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Trichomoniasis</article-title>
          <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <year>2004</year>
          <fpage>794</fpage>
          <lpage>803</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15489349</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0015">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bastida-Corcuera</surname>
              <given-names>F.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Okumura</surname>
              <given-names>C.Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colocoussi</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> lipophosphoglycan mutants have reduced adherence and cytotoxicity to human ectocervical cells</article-title>
          <source>Eukaryot Cell</source>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <year>2005</year>
          <fpage>1951</fpage>
          <lpage>1958</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16278462</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0020">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>B.N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hayes</surname>
              <given-names>G.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lucas</surname>
              <given-names>J.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Structural details and composition of <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> lipophosphoglycan in relevance to the epithelial immune function</article-title>
          <source>Glycoconj J</source>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <lpage>17</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18604640</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0025">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ryan</surname>
              <given-names>C.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mehlert</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Richardson</surname>
              <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chemical structure of <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic> surface lipoglycan: a role for short galactose (β1-4/3) N-acetylglucosamine repeats in host cell interaction</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>2011</year>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0030">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ankel</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feingold</surname>
              <given-names>D.S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Biosynthesis of uridine diphosphate <sc>d</sc>-xylose. II. Uridine diphosphate <sc>d</sc>-glucuronate carboxy-lyase of <italic>Cryptococcus laurentii</italic></article-title>
          <source>Biochemistry</source>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <year>1966</year>
          <fpage>182</fpage>
          <lpage>189</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4287217</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0035">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harper</surname>
              <given-names>A.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bar-Peled</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Biosynthesis of UDP-Xylose. Cloning and characterization of a novel <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> gene family, UXS, encoding soluble and putative membrane-bound UDP-glucuronic acid decarboxylase isoforms</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <volume>130</volume>
          <year>2002</year>
          <fpage>2188</fpage>
          <lpage>2198</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12481102</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0040">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Suzuki</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watanabe</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Masumura</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterization of soluble and putative membrane-bound UDP-glucuronic acid decarboxylase (OsUXS) isoforms in rice</article-title>
          <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source>
          <volume>431</volume>
          <year>2004</year>
          <fpage>169</fpage>
          <lpage>177</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15488465</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0045">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moriarity</surname>
              <given-names>J.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hurt</surname>
              <given-names>K.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Resnick</surname>
              <given-names>A.C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>UDP-glucuronate decarboxylase, a key enzyme in proteoglycan synthesis. Cloning, characterisation and localisation</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <volume>277</volume>
          <year>2002</year>
          <fpage>16968</fpage>
          <lpage>16975</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11877387</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0050">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hwang</surname>
              <given-names>H.-Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Horvitz</surname>
              <given-names>H.R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The SQV-1 UDP-glucuronic acid decarboxylase and the SQV-7 nucleotide-sugar transporter may act in the golgi apparatus to affect <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> vulval morphogenesis and embryonic development</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <year>2002</year>
          <fpage>14218</fpage>
          <lpage>14223</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12391314</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0055">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bar-Peled</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Griffith</surname>
              <given-names>C.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Doering</surname>
              <given-names>T.L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Functional cloning and characterisation of a UDP-glucuronic acid decarboxylase: the pathogenic fungus <italic>Cryptococcus neoformans</italic> elucidates UDP-xylose synthesis</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <year>2001</year>
          <fpage>12003</fpage>
          <lpage>12008</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11593010</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0060">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gu</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>S.G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bar-Peled</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Biosynthesis of UDP-xylose and UDP-arabinose in <italic>Sinorhizobium meliloti</italic> 1021: first characterization of a bacterial UDP-xylose synthase, and UDP-xylose 4-epimerase</article-title>
          <source>Microbiology</source>
          <volume>157</volume>
          <year>2011</year>
          <fpage>260</fpage>
          <lpage>269</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20847005</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0065">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Simkhada</surname>
              <given-names>D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oh</surname>
              <given-names>T.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pageni</surname>
              <given-names>B.B.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterization of CalS9 in the biosynthesis of UDP-xylose and the production of xylosyl-attached hybrid compound</article-title>
          <source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source>
          <volume>83</volume>
          <year>2009</year>
          <fpage>885</fpage>
          <lpage>895</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19290519</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0070">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Roper</surname>
              <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guther</surname>
              <given-names>M.L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Macrae</surname>
              <given-names>J.I.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The suppression of galactose metabolism in procylic form <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic> causes cessation of cell growth and alters procyclin glycoprotein structure and copy number</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <volume>280</volume>
          <year>2005</year>
          <fpage>19728</fpage>
          <lpage>19736</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15767252</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0075">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Carlton</surname>
              <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirt</surname>
              <given-names>R.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silva</surname>
              <given-names>J.C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Draft genome sequence of the sexually transmitted pathogen <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <volume>315</volume>
          <year>2007</year>
          <fpage>207</fpage>
          <lpage>212</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17218520</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0080">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ernst</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klaffke</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chemical synthesis of uridine diphospho-<sc>d</sc>-xylose and UDP-<sc>l</sc>-arabinose</article-title>
          <source>J Org Chem</source>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <year>2003</year>
          <fpage>5780</fpage>
          <lpage>5783</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12839484</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0085">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pattathil</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harper</surname>
              <given-names>A.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bar-Peled</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Biosynthesis of UDP-xylose: characterization of membrane-bound AtUxs2</article-title>
          <source>Planta</source>
          <volume>221</volume>
          <year>2005</year>
          <fpage>538</fpage>
          <lpage>548</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15655675</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0090">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Leloir</surname>
              <given-names>L.F.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The enzymatic transformation of uridine diphosphate glucose into a galactose derivative</article-title>
          <source>Arch Biochem Biophys</source>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <year>1951</year>
          <fpage>186</fpage>
          <lpage>190</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14885999</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0095">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Oka</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jigami</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reconstruction of de novo pathway for synthesis of UDP-glucuronic acid and UDP-xylose from intrinsic UDP-glucose in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title>
          <source>FEBS J</source>
          <volume>273</volume>
          <year>2006</year>
          <fpage>2645</fpage>
          <lpage>2657</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16817893</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="bib0100">
        <label>20</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Paschinger K, Hykollari A, Razzazi-Fazeli E, Greenwell P, Leitsch D, Walochnik J, Wilson IBH. The N-glycans of Trichomonas vaginalis contain variable core and antennal modifications. Glycobiology 2011, in press, <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/glycob/cwr149">doi:10.1093/glycob/cwr149</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We thank Julia Walochnik (Medizinische Universität Wien) for providing <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> RNA, Ebrahim Razzazi-Fazeli (Veterinärmedizinische Universität Wien) for access to the mass spectrometer, Katharina Paschinger for aiding revision of the text and Tamara Doering (Washington University, St Louis) for the kind gift of the <italic>C. neoformans</italic> UXS plasmid. This work was funded by the Austrian Fonds zur Förderung der wissenschaftlichen Forschung [P20565 to I.B.H.W.].</p>
    </ack>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="fig0010">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Test of UDP-xylose synthase and UDP-galactose epimerase activities. UDP-xylose synthase (UXS) and UDP-galactose/glucose epimerase (GalE1) activities were assayed by incubating the enzyme (1 μl purified enzyme or 5 μl <italic>E. coli</italic> crude extract) in the presence of the relevant 3 mM UDP-sugar and 3 mM NAD<sup>+</sup> in 80 mM Tris–Cl, pH 7.7 at 30 or 37 °C (final volume 50 μL). (A) SAX-HPLC of 4 h assays performed using UDP-glucuronic acid as substrate and lysates of bacteria expressing <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> UXS, <italic>Drosophila</italic> GMD (negative control) or <italic>Cryptococcus</italic> UXS (positive control). After injection onto a Hypersil column (0.5 × 25 cm), the column was washed for 10 min with buffer A (2 mM ammonium formate, pH 3.2; the flow rate was 1.5 ml/min) prior to elution with a linear gradient from 0 to 40% buffer B (600 mM ammonium formate, pH 3.2) as described <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>; absorbance at 254 nm was recorded. Standard UDP-xylose elutes at around 6 min as compared to the UDP-glucuronic acid at 7 min (Stds). The peak at 4.5 min corresponds to imidazole present in the lysis buffer. (B) Ion-pair RP-HPLC of assays of recombinant UXS in either purified form or in an <italic>E. coli</italic> extract (+IPTG) showing conversion of UDP-GlcA to UDP-Xyl. A control extract of <italic>E. coli</italic> transformed with the UXS plasmid but not induced (-IPTG) showed no such activity. Analysis was performed using a Cosmosil C18-AR-II column (250 mm × 4.6 mm; Nacalai Tesque, Kyoto, Japan): buffer A was 20 mM triethylamine-acetate (pH 7) and buffer B was 20 mM triethylamine-acetate (pH 7) containing 10% acetonitrile <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. After isocratic elution with 100% buffer A, a gradient of 1% per minute (buffer B) was applied after 15 min. (C) Negative-mode MALDI-TOF MS of pooled UXS products; the <italic>m</italic>/<italic>z</italic> of UDP-xylose [M-H]<sup>−</sup> of 535.3 compares to the calculated molecular mass of 536.2. For analysis, 1 μl of an aliquot of UDP-Xyl was spotted onto a MALDI plate, vacuum dried prior to application of 1 μl 2,5-dihydroxybenzoic acid (DHB; 2% in 30% acetonitrile/70% 50 mM (NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>); the dried and crystallized sample was analysed by MALDI-TOF MS using a Bruker Ultraflex instrument. (D) Ion-pair RP-HPLC of GalE1 assays; purified recombinant <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> GalE converted UDP-Gal partly into UDP-Glc and also UDP-Glc partly into UDP-Gal, whereas purified recombinant <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> UXS displayed no such activity.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr1"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="fig0015">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Enzymatic characteristics of purified recombinant <italic>T. vaginalis</italic> UXS. A. The variation of UDP-xylose yield with pH was examined by incubations in the presence of McIlvaine buffer (black squares, pH 5.0–8.0; <italic>n</italic> = 2), HEPES buffer (open rhombi, 7.0–8.0) and MES buffer (grey triangles, 5.5–7.0) for 2 h at 30 °C. (B) The dependency of UXS reaction on temperature was based on assays (<italic>n</italic> = 3) performed at pH 7.4 for 2 h; the error bars correspond to the standard deviation.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gr2"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="tbl0005" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>NMR analysis of the UXS assay product. Chemical shifts (<sup>1</sup>H and <sup>31</sup>P NMR) are expressed as ppm. Approximately 300 μg of HPLC-purified reaction product was lyophilised twice and taken up in 0.6 ml D<sub>2</sub>O. Spectra were recorded at 300 K at 600.18 MHz for <sup>1</sup>H and at 242.96 MHz for <sup>31</sup>P with a Bruker AV III 600 spectrometer. Data acquisition and processing were performed with the standard Bruker software. <sup>1</sup>H spectra were referenced internally to sodium 2,2-dimethyl-2-silapentane-5-sulphonate and <sup>31</sup>P spectra to phosphoric acid (<italic>δ</italic> = 0).</p>
      </caption>
      <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th/>
            <th align="left">H1</th>
            <th align="left">H2</th>
            <th align="left">H3</th>
            <th align="left">H4</th>
            <th align="left">H5, 5′</th>
            <th align="left">H6</th>
            <th align="left">
              <italic>α</italic>
            </th>
            <th align="left">
              <italic>β</italic>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Xylose</td>
            <td align="char">5.59</td>
            <td align="char">3.55</td>
            <td align="char">3.69</td>
            <td align="char">3.61</td>
            <td align="char">3.71</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Ribose</td>
            <td align="char">6.01</td>
            <td align="char">4.41</td>
            <td align="char">4.44</td>
            <td align="char">4.27</td>
            <td align="char">4.24</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Uracil</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="char">6.02</td>
            <td align="char">7.99</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">Pyrophosphate</td>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td/>
            <td align="left">−11.28 (19.5 Hz)</td>
            <td align="left">−12.98 (21.4 Hz)</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>