<article xmlns="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/2.0/xsd/archivearticle.xsd" article-type="correction">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heart Rhythm</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Heart Rhythm</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1547-5271</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1556-3871</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3014096</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">HRTHM3155</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.hrthm.2008.09.005</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Erratum</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Erratum</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the
							<pub-date pub-type="ppub"/>. -->
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>5</volume>
      <issue>10-6</issue>
      <fpage>1499</fpage>
      <lpage>403</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>© 2008 Elsevier Inc.</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
        <copyright-holder>Heart Rhythm Society</copyright-holder>
        <license>
          <license-p>This document may be redistributed and reused, subject to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.elsevier.com/wps/find/authorsview.authors/supplementalterms1.0">certain conditions</ext-link>.</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <related-article related-article-type="corrected-article" id="d30e11" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.hrthm.2008.01.016"/>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Conflict of interest disclosure statements for some authors of the Heart Rhythm June supplement (5:(6S)S1-S76) were inadvertently omitted. All disclosures are submitted below.<table-wrap id="d30e30" position="float"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Cellular bases for human atrial fibrillation</bold></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Antony J. Workman, Kathleen A. Kane, Andrew C. Rankin</italic></p></list-item></list></td><td>Anthony J. Workman received British Heart Foundation Basic Science Lectureship award BS/06/003. Drs. Kane and Rankin have no conflict of interest.</td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Visualizing ion channel dynamics at the plasma membrane</bold></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>James W. Smyth, Robin M. Shaw</italic></p></list-item></list></td><td>Supported by the National Institutes of Health, National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, and GlaxoSmithKline Research and Education Foundation (Dr. Shaw). Dr. Smyth has no conflict of interest.</td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>The renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system (RAAS) and cardiac arrhythmias</bold></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Shahriar Iravanian, Samuel C. Dudley, Jr.</italic></p></list-item></list></td><td>Dr. Dudley has received grants from Pfizer, owns stock in Medtronic and Johnson &amp; Johnson, has consulted for Ortho Clinical Diagnostics and is an inventor on a patent entitled, “Oxidative Stress Markers Product Atrial Fibrillation (60/835,074).” Dr. Iravanian has no conflicts of interest.</td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Macroreentrant atrial tachycardia: Pathophysiological concepts</bold></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Frédéric Anselme</italic></p></list-item></list></td><td>Dr. Anselme has served on advisory boards and received lecture fees from SORIN and Medtronic.</td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Dynamics factors preceding the initiation of atrial fibrillation in humans</bold></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Sanjiv M. Narayan, David E. Krummen</italic></p></list-item></list></td><td>This work was supported in part by grants from the National Institutes of Health (K23 HL70529, R01 HL83359) and the Doris Duke Clinical Foundation (to Dr Narayan) and by a grant from the American College of Cardiology Foundation/Merck (to Dr Krummen). Dr. Narayan is co-inventor of a patent (U.S. patent no. 7,123,954) in the analysis of atrial tachyarrhythmias and is on the speaker's bureau for Boston Scientific and St. Jude Medical Corporations.</td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Pharmacotherapy for atrial arrhythmias: Present and future</bold></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Michael M. Mazzini, Kevin M. Monahan</italic></p></list-item></list></td><td>Drs. Mazzini and Monahan have no conflict of interest.</td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>What have we learned about atrial arrhythmias from ablation of paroxysmal atrial fibri</bold></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Navinder Sawhney, Gregory K. Feld</italic></p></list-item></list></td><td>Dr. Feld is a member of the scientific advisory boards of and holds stock options in CryoCor, Inc., and Medwaves, Inc., San Diego, California. Dr. Sawhney has no conflict of interest.</td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>What have we learned about atrial arrhythmias from ablation of chronic atrial fibrillation?</bold></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Hakan Oral</italic></p></list-item></list></td><td>Dr. Oral is a founder and equity owner of Ablation Frontiers, Inc. Dr. Oral has received research grants from St. Jude Medical and Boston Scientific.</td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Surgical lessons learned from the treatment of atrial fibrillation</bold></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Richard J. Shemin</italic></p></list-item></list></td><td>Dr. Shemin has no conflict of interest.</td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Beyond the implantable cardioverter-defibrillator: Are we making progress?</bold></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>James N. Weiss</italic></p></list-item></list></td><td>Supported by NIH/NHLBI Grant P01 HL078931 and by the Laubisch and Kawata Endowments.</td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Electrophysiologic implications of myocardial stem cell therapies</bold></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Lior Gepstein</italic></p></list-item></list></td><td>Dr. Gepstein is one of the founders of Genegrafts, a Technion University incubator company. This study was supported in part by the Israel Science Foundation (#520/01), and by the Stephen and Nancy Grand Foundation.</td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Mechanistic insights into ventricular arrhythmias from mapping studies in humans</bold></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Mina Attin, Raymond E. Ideker, Steven M. Pogwizd</italic></p></list-item></list></td><td>Drs. Attin, Ideker and Pogwizd have no conflict of interest.</td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Catheter ablation of ventricular tachycardia: Two decades of progress</bold></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>David J. Wilber</italic></p></list-item></list></td><td>Supported in part by a grant from the George M. Eisenberg Foundation. Dr. Wilber is a consultant and lecturer for Biosense/Webster, a consultant for CardioInsight, and a lecturer for St. Jude Medical (level: moderate).</td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>“Focal” ventricular tachycardia: Insights from catheter ablation</bold></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Suneet Mittal</italic></p></list-item></list></td><td>Dr. Mittal received fellowship support from Boston Scientific and Medtronic; research support from Biotronik, Boston Scientific, Medtronic, and St. Jude Medical; and speaking honoraria from Boston Scientific, Medtronic, and St. Jude Medical. Dr. Mittal is a consultant to Bard, Biotronik, and Lifewatch.</td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Catheter ablation of bundle branch reentrant ventricular tachycardia</bold></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Ramprakash Balasundaram, Hygriv B. Rao, Sharada Kalavakolanu, Calambur Narasimhan</italic></p></list-item></list></td><td>Drs. Balasundaram, Rao, Kalavakolanu and Narasimhan have no conflict of interest.</td></tr><tr><td><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><bold>Epicardial catheter ablation of ventricular tachycardia</bold></p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>Andre d'Avila</italic></p></list-item></list></td><td>Dr. Avila was lecturer for Biosense/Webster, Medtronic, Boston Scientific, and St. Jude Medical. Consultant for St. Jude Medical. Recipient of research grants from St. Jude Medical, Biosense, Cardiofocus, and Voyage Medical.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
  </body>
</article>